<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- custom: AdvCiv-SAS specific tags (if i am not mistaken these are tags,
not in terms of content added but in terms of the type of content), here is
mostly but not only documentation pages aobut AdvCiv-SAS itself, hopefully
easier to manage here, anyways -->



<!-- custom: 
Before starting, a note about translations:

If we define only the <English>My translation example</Example> tag without
putting the other language tags, then (according to ChatGPT), the other languages will
see the English version, no need to copy paste the same version many times, thanks ChatGPT
etc too maybe anyways.
Detailed explanations of ChatGPT below (i modified the formatting of it a bit but same content (i may have added Upper cases instead or Change a bit some sentences to connect them, should be mostly the same)).

1) For new content we add (for example if we were to add a new sniper unit (great memory ChatGPT thanks a lot, anyways, )):
:
Quote:
"
What happens if you only define an XML entry in English?

If you only define one language (like English) in your XML (e.g., CIV4GameText.xml), and leave out translations for other languages, then:
Yes — other languages will see the English version.

Why?
Because Civ4's text system falls back to English if:
- A translation is missing for the current language.
- The player's selected language is not found in the XML at all.

So for example:
<TEXT>
	<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SNIPER</Tag>
	<English>Sniper</English>
</TEXT>

If the player has their game language set to French, Spanish, or anything else — they'll still see "Sniper" in English, because:
- The game didn’t find <French>, <German>, etc., for that tag.
- So it shows <English> as a fallback.

Exceptions / Notes:
- If the <English> field is missing entirely, the game will show the tag name (like TXT_KEY_UNIT_SNIPER) instead.
- If you include a <French> tag but leave it empty, it may show nothing or just whitespace — so it's better to leave other languages out entirely unless you have a proper translation.
"


2) For content already existing in the game (for example FEATURE_ICE):
Quoting ChatGPT again, thanks ChatGPT and etc thanks all too or not too etc, anyways:

Quote:
"
This gets into how overrides work in Civ4's XML system. Here's the breakdown:
You override an existing in-game text key (e.g. TXT_KEY_FEATURE_ICE) in your mod's XML:

<TEXT>
	<Tag>TXT_KEY_FEATURE_ICE</Tag>
	<English>Frozen Hell</English>
</TEXT>

But you do not include <French>, <German>, etc.

What happens in-game?
Civ4 will completely override the original text entry, even in non-English languages.

So:
- English players will see: "Frozen Hell"
- French players will not see the original Firaxis French translation — they’ll see "Frozen Hell" too.
- Other languages will also see your new English text, not the base game's translation.
"

Important Note:
Once you override a <Tag> in your mod, the original translations are no longer used, even if you only replace <English>.
That means:
- You're responsible for translations if you want to preserve them.
- If not, it's totally fine — Civ4 will fall back to your <English> string in all languages.

Pro Tip:
If you're just changing English and want to keep the original translations, you can rename the tag, like:

<Tag>TXT_KEY_FEATURE_ICE_ALT</Tag>

Then use TXT_KEY_FEATURE_ICE_ALT wherever you want (e.g. in your modified CIV4FeatureInfos.xml). That way:
- The original TXT_KEY_FEATURE_ICE stays untouched.
- You can localize or not as you like.

Summary:
What You Do										What Players See
Only override <English> of a base tag			All languages will see your English string
Don't touch a tag								Players see base game translations
Rename the tag									Original untouched; you're free to localize your version
"
-->



<Civ4GameText>
	<!-- custom: remove BTS links, unneeded, see CIV4NewConceptInfos.xml for details -->
	<!-- custom: the other conceptinfo entries have been moved to file with similar filename than in civ4 bts -->



	<!-- custom: rename "BtS Rules Changes" to "0_BtS Rules Changes (Outdated)", really important to not confuse the user/player about how this data is unrelated to us, but they may still want to access it, espcially if they are in knowledge of that/aware of that, as they prefer maybe or not etc but etc anyways" -->
	<!-- advc.002b: Shortening "Beyond the Sword" to "BtS" so that the page
		 names can be displayed despite the increased font size.
		 Originally in CIV4GameText_BTS.xml and CIV4GameText_Objects_BTS.xml. -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BTS_RULES_CHANGES</Tag>
		<English>0_BtS Rules Changes (Outdated)</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BASE_ADVCIV_SOME_CHANGES</Tag>
		<English>2_Base AdvCiv Some Changes</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_ADVCIV_SAS_CORE_CHANGES</Tag>
		<English>3_AdvCiv-SAS Core Changes</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_ADVCIV_SAS_CORE_AI_PERSONALITY_PANEL_INTRO</Tag>
		<English>4_AdvCiv-SAS AI Personality Panel Intro</English>
	</TEXT>



	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BASE_ADVCIV_SOME_CHANGES_PEDIA_SR</Tag>
		<English>[H1]K-Mod to AdvCiv Changes[\H1][PARAGRAPH:2]Provided by AdvCiv-SAS maintainer/developer, and non-exhaustive list of some info i'd want to display there as well, from AdvCiv's (adjust to your mod path anyways etc) C:\Program Files (x86)\Steam\steamapps\common\Sid Meier's Civilization IV Beyond the Sword\Beyond the Sword\Mods\AdvCiv-SAS\_0_Common_Docs\AdvCiv Base Doc\manual.pdf or similar path anyways etc for manual.txt or some other AdvCiv-related sources or not anyways etc.[PARAGRAPH:1]Info below may also not be updated with latest version of the manual.pdf or similar format, view them rather at base AdvCiv's github https://github.com/f1rpo/AdvCiv or some other place that has them or/and is relevant anyways etc for latest updated content or/and more exhaustive info, this below only provides some key or excerpted info for quick view and hopefully helpful too and as i (AdvCiv-SAS maintainer/developer) wanted to, anyways etc.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][BOLD]Notable adjustments to K-Mod AI behavior (non-exhaustive as well anyways etc):[\BOLD][NEWLINE]- AI razes fewer cities and less randomly; 116[NEWLINE]- uses Slavery and Drafting less aggressively, though still frequently; 121b, 017[NEWLINE]- uses destructive espionage missions only against civs it dislikes; 120[NEWLINE]- will rarely found a religion before a second city (reinforcing K-Mod changes that make the AI less interested in the early religions). 171[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][BOLD]Reverted by AdvCiv (i (AdvCiv-SAS maintainer/developer anyways etc) assume from K-Mod (non-exhaustive as well anyways etc) (anyways etc)):[\BOLD][NEWLINE]- See Immortal Culture about reverted changes to culture and revolts.[NEWLINE]- Production overflow is never invested into an additional unit as this had lead to balance problems with AI civs training multiple Archers per turn. Instead, excess overflow is converted into gold as in the Unofficial Patch, though with some tweaks to make this conversion more difficult to abuse. 064b[NEWLINE]- Gifting Great People to the AI does not provide a relations bonus. 141[NEWLINE]- No impact of global research on inflation; instead, adjusted tech costs based on difficulty and the years-per-turn progression for a more historically accurate tech pace, and Immortal and Deity games now start on turn 10. 251, 910[NEWLINE]-  Some minor balance changes undone that weren't pulling their weight in terms of added complexity (change 200) (non-exhaustive (AdvCiv-SAS maintainer/develoepr note anyways etc)): All corporations have the same maintenance multiplier (i.e. mostly as in BtS)[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][BOLD]Important miscellaneous changes in AdvCiv (non-exhaustive as well anyways etc)[\BOLD][NEWLINE]- Workers and settlers only have a 50% chance of being captured and 0% if attacked on the same turn as declaring war. 010[NEWLINE]- When a tile with unfinished worker builds is left alone for more than 7 turns, the invested worker turns begin to decay. This is mainly to disincentivize pre-chopping. 011[NEWLINE]- Forest and Jungle provide only 25% defense, and none if the tile is owned by the attacker. 012[NEWLINE]- Unowned Forests and Jungles can't be chopped down. 119[NEWLINE]- The AI evacuates land units that can't defend well from cities that are about to be attacked and untenable. 139[NEWLINE]- When the AI has more happiness or health than it needs, it may refuse to accept resources in trade or may trade away its only copy of a resource. 036[NEWLINE]- Undefended cities stop "fearing for their safety" once Nationalism is discovered. 500c[NEWLINE]- Slavery base yield reduced to 24 production (from 30). 912d [NEWLINE]- The Spy unit can investigate rival cities, but (unlike in Warlords) with a mission cost. 103[NEWLINE]- Research progress toward a tech makes that tech cheaper to steal. 120i[NEWLINE]- When a citizen starves, the Granary is emptied to delay further starvation. 160[NEWLINE]- The Apostolic Palace can propose war against (non-full) voting members, but only full members are compelled to declare war. kekm.25[NEWLINE]- Can no longer bypass the Theocracy restriction by gifting missionaries. 123a/ kekm.4[NEWLINE]- Damage from nuclear weapons to units made less predictable; SDI interception chance reduced from 75% to 60% and cost increased from 1000 to 1500 production. 650[NEWLINE]- Wonders that have been manually removed from the production queue generate no "fail gold." Also no gold from national units. 123f[NEWLINE]- Trade routes can only come from revealed cities, and the paths to those cities need to be revealed as well. Cities are temporarily unavailable for trade when in disorder. Trade along rivers doesn't require any tech (as in Warlords; BtS demands Sailing). When borders of a war enemy block trade, a naval blockade can override this. Connecting a resource on an island workable by a mainland city requires only a road, not a fort. 124[NEWLINE]- When mountain peaks block off part of a landmass, the parts are treated as separate continents. This is relevant for the placement of Barbarians, colony maintenance and wonders that affect only one continent - though the main point is to make things easier for the AI. 030[NEWLINE]- Land threshold for Domination victory reduced, especially in large games. 254[NEWLINE]- On Emperor difficulty and above, some of the AI discounts have been reduced, but human civs face increased production costs, research costs, city growth thresholds and Great Person thresholds. The AI also starts with fewer freebies, in particular, without Agriculture on Immortal and Deity and without a second free Settler on Deity. Progressive AI bonuses are now based on the game turn instead of the AI era. 251/ 250e[NEWLINE]- Marathon speed is only 2.5 times slower than Normal speed, not 3 times. 252[NEWLINE]- The default player count is 8 for the Standard map size. 137[NEWLINE]- Map generation: Clusters of Gold, Gems made less common. Silver may occur on Grassland Forest. No Flood Plains on river corners. Jungle may occur on Plains. 129[NEWLINE]- New algorithm for assigning starting locations. Should partition the available land more evenly than in BtS. Not enabled for all map scripts (list). 027, 108[NEWLINE]- Switched the no-war-probability of Roosevelt and Darius, meaning that Darius can start wars when pleased, and Roosevelt - normally - cannot. 005a[NEWLINE]- Suryavarman's favorite religion is Hinduism and his favorite civic Caste System. 005a[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][BOLD]Other information i scraped/found (long ago (relatively) (at the start of this mod) and can finally add in AdvCiv-SAS but anyways etc...):[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:2]About the below info in this section, it comes from/in anyways etc code comments from base AdvCiv or similar that i have removed our mod (mostly from the old strategy history panel fields we don't use anymore as they are/can be inaccurate/hard to update as well but anyways etc) (non-exhaustive as well anyways etc) ; note that these below are not from base AdvCiv's manual so they may be inaccurate even more or not than manual doc added in this page (Mods Info/ Changes from K-Mod to AdvCiv) (anyways etc), anyways etc ; please also note that we don't update the [LINK=CONCEPT_ADVANCED_START]concepts pages (now in "Outdated" category in AdvCiv-SAS's sevopedia anyways etc)[\LINK] so part of the info below (at least the one related to concepts, may not apply anymore to our mod at all and is just base AdvCiv info for exhaustiveness anyways etc, as for all other info we altered some changes made by AdvCiv while we kept many or some, please view docs or/and [LINK=CONCEPT_ADVCIV_SAS_CORE_CHANGES]CONCEPT_ADVCIV_SAS_CORE_CHANGES[\LINK] for details)[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]- (AdvCiv): Defense from Walls is not cumulative with defense from city culture. The higher of the two values counts.[NEWLINE]- (AdvCiv): The defense modifier from Castle replaces the one from Wall and is not cumulative with defense from city culture[NEWLINE]- units in friendly cities and forts are safe from Flank Attacks.[NEWLINE]- SISTINE_CHAPEL unlike other building [ICON_CULTURE] rates, the added [ICON_CULTURE] rate doesn't double after 1000 years.[NEWLINE]- CONCEPT_ESPIONAGE Addition: advc.132 allows switching to civics not run by the Spy owner.[NEWLINE]- CONCEPT_CITIES advc.004f: "We Love the King Day" disabled by AdvCiv.[NEWLINE]- CONCEPT_LATE_START advc.250b: Added mention of the new SPaH option and a clarification that later-era start and advanced start are separate things. Overwrites text in Civ4GameText_BTS.xml.[NEWLINE]- CONCEPT_UNITS  advc.010: Worker capturing has limitations; advc.005e.[NEWLINE]- CONCEPT_VASSAL_STATES advc.141: Pointed out change in happiness rule. Removed mention of vassal maintenance "dragging the economy to a halt"; it's not so dramatic. Vassal maint. is still mentioned.[NEWLINE]- CONCEPT_COMBAT and added info that feature defense depends on tile ownership.[NEWLINE]- CONCEPT_TRANSPORT Added mention of Executives as special cargo.[NEWLINE]- CONCEPT_TRANSPORT advc.123c: Rule change for loading units into cargo mentioned.[NEWLINE]- CONCEPT_DIPLOMACY Referring reader to the manual about AI refusal to talk (advc.104i) and tribute demands (advc.130o); clarified that the manner of declaring war doesn't make a difference, that tribute can't be demanded from pleased AI leaders, and that the AI doesn't normally declare war when the player declines an offer. Removed mention of "disband[ing] buildings" as this is not possible.[NEWLINE]- TXT_KEY_TRAIT_CREATIVE_PEDIA (note: advc.908b if i am not mistaken from my notes of these? Anyways etc) Since K-Mod and AdvCiv make [ICON_CULTURE] points more worthwhile in several ways, AdvCiv reduces the [ICON_CULTURE] rate (was 2 in BtS) and adds some free initial [ICON_CULTURE] instead. AdvCiv has also removed the faster [ICON_PRODUCTION] of Colosseum - which doesn't seem to fit the culture theme well. (note: advc.908b if i am not mistaken from my notes of these? Anyways etc) [NEWLINE]- _CIVIC_STATE_PROPERTY_ K-Mod treats colony maintenance as separate from distance maintenance, so this civic no longer affects colony maintenance.[NEWLINE]- CONCEPT_PROMOTIONS Overwrites CIV4GameText_Civilopedia_Concepts. Just correcting a bit of misinformation: When it comes to combat XP, it does matter who attacked.[NEWLINE]- CONCEPT_RESOURCES Overwrites CIV4GameText_Civilopedia_Concepts. Correction: Duplicate resources do have uses with BtS.[NEWLINE]- CONCEPT_COMBAT advc.012: Corrected two examples that say that Forest grants 50% def, Weirdly, an example in TXT_KEY_CONCEPT_TERRAIN_PEDIA already said that Forest defense is 25%. Perhaps it was changed to 50% late in development.[NEWLINE]- CONCEPT_ESPIONAGE [advc.103] Added note about Spies being able to investigate cities.[NEWLINE]- CONCEPT_FOOD [advc.160] Replaced "half" of the food with "a portion". Added mention of the Granary under "Insufficient Food".[NEWLINE]- CONCEPT_TRANSPORT advc.906: Submarine becomes Attack Submarine (note: i also added this note if i am mistaken and does not come from base AdvCiv, adding it for exhaustiveness and just in case as well, anyways etc..., anyways etc...:  advc.005e (but did not check 005e though))[NEWLINE]- CONCEPT_UNITED_NATIONS advc.148: Overwriting the key in CIV4GameText_Civilopedia_Concepts.xml. AI voting behavior outlined. Victory vote was missing entirely in German.[NEWLINE]- CIV_INCA advc.004g: Dropped mention of Quechua</English>
	</TEXT>



	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_ADVCIV_SAS_CORE_CHANGES_PEDIA_SR</Tag>
		<English>[H1]AdvCiv to AdvCiv-SAS Core Changes[\H1][PARAGRAPH:2]Non-exhaustive list of changes in AdvCiv-SAS as compared to AdvCiv (excluding most balance changes, for that please refer to the Sevopedia entries of the items you want to see, for example "Units", "Technologies", or "Traits" to have the latest updated version of their effects.)[PARAGRAPH:1]For more details, in particular about the changes, please also visit:[NEWLINE]- if online, https://github.com/wonderingabout/AdvCiv-SAS/, in particular the "Quick Start Guide" there (also appended/included as a text .md file in AdvCiv-SAS). If you want to see the full very exhaustive code changes between AdvCiv current latest stable, for example 1.12 here, and AdvCiv-SAS, please visit this pull request compare: https://github.com/wonderingabout/AdvCiv-SAS/pull/13 . Be warned though it can be very lengthy, so read rather the quick start guide mentionned above preferably for the shorter and less exhaustive version if you'd prefer.[NEWLINE]- if offline: you can also view most (almost all) of the information above by navigating the docs in your AdvCiv-SAS folder (for example if you have the Steam version of the game,it would be here (else adapt to where your civ4 and advciv-sas install paths are): "C:\Program Files (x86)\Steam\steamapps\common\Sid Meier's Civilization IV Beyond the Sword\Beyond the Sword\Mods\AdvCiv-SAS\"), and opening them with a text editor (i recommend Notepad++ (or (even) better depending on the need (but anyways etc) VS Code .md preview for example anyways etc), but the default Windows Notepad.exe can also open .txt and .md files too just with less display features (but still all info unless i'm mistaken anyways)).[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][BOLD]General Information[\BOLD][NEWLINE]- To follow/understand smoother difficulties (called handicap in civ4 if i am not mistaken but anyways etc), i have also added a table view of the differences between difficulties/handicap settings, please see as explained before the README.md at paragraph csv-and-md-view-of-the-handicap-difficulties-info-in-a-table-for-all-difficulties (or whichever paragraph name it may have been renamed to in the future or not but anyways etc) for details (anyways etc)[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][BOLD]Translations[\BOLD][NEWLINE]- For the new content or modified one in this mod (AdvCiv-SAS), only English translations are provided. If your game is in another language, you will still see some text, but in English. For modders, see the detailed explanation (code comment), mostly provided by ChatGPT and which was very helpful (to me at least, anyways, ) on how this is implemented at TXT_KEY_ADVCIV_SAS_CORE_CHANGES_PEDIA_SR 's entry in Mods\AdvCiv-SAS\Assets\XML\Text\CIV4GameText_advc_pedia_Lengthy_Custom.xml[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][BOLD]Sevopedia[\BOLD][NEWLINE]- New feature in sevopedia leader: AI Personality Panels, that aim to represent each Leader's behavorial tendencies and preferences quite exhaustively, and their ranking of such tendencies vs what other leaders ((would) tend to do) anyways, as represented in their XML data, see for example [LINK=LEADER_GANDHI]Gandhi's leader page for example[\LINK]. Extensive documentation has been written as well to help you navigate these and understand how they work. Please read for more details the general introduction to such documents(ation(s?)) in Mods Info [LINK=CONCEPT_ADVCIV_SAS_CORE_AI_PERSONALITY_PANEL_INTRO].4_ADVCIV_SAS_CORE_AI_PERSONALITY_PANEL_INTRO[\LINK][NEWLINE]- Cleanup or adding more features in other Sevopedia categories, such as SevopediaReligion (add Leaders panel (based on History Rewritten's code (modified for AdvCiv-SAS)) and Buildings panel too (based on RFC DOC's code modified for AdvCiv-SAS too anyways etc)), or the SevopediaLeader in general (reordered the size and position of the other panels in SevopediaLeader with or not with other mods's code, or/and other Sevopedia Categories too).[NEWLINE]- Expanded Sevopedia so it uses all screen space available (no margins anymore), now more space to display info if want/need or visual clarity, as some also do for example or/and comparison anyways/etc[NEWLINE]- Reduced main categories width from approxiamtely 200px to 124px approximately, this quite greatly increases the space of the Sevopedia for the content or items category(?)/column (the one that lists for example for the leaders category "Alexander[...]", "Ashoka", etc.. until the end of alphabet and for all other main categories too that have a listing of items (which is almost all if i'm not mistaken anyways)). Hopefully clearer now for this non critical info, while still preserving the 2nd category's width, using shortened names when possible or necessary in 1st/main categories's 1st column.[NEWLINE]- Added a few or many or at least some wikipedia real entries or from some other source (see code comments or/and docs for the info if it is, but as a general rule unless specified otherwise most if not all but at least most pedia type of content comes from wikipedia and generally in english (version of it(i.e. of wikipedia)), thanks wikipedia, anyways etc, for example the [LINK=RELIGION_BUDDHISM]Buddhism[\LINK][NEWLINE][NEWLINE][BOLD]Renaming[\BOLD][NEWLINE]- "We fear you are becoming too advanced" (WFYABTA) has been renamed to "We fear you are trading more than us" (WFYATMTU), as WFYABTA is misleading, and not related at all to your tech progress but to how much you trade if i'm not mistaken, and you can get WFYABTA even if you are lagging behind in tech progress, hopefully clearer now.[NEWLINE]- (Air) interception chance for nukes is now named "Adjusted Air Interception Chance", as it also accounts for Nuke's Air evasion chance if i am not mistaken, see also this for details: https://forums.civfanatics.com/threads/sdi-icbm-and-tactical-nukes.239415/ [NEWLINE]- Renamed [LINK=TERRAIN_SNOW]"Ice" (Terrain) to "Ice Sheet"[\LINK], and [LINK=FEATURE_ICE]"Ice" (Feature) to "Ice Cap"[\LINK], hopefully clearer and more accurate, see their Sevopedia entries for details.[NEWLINE]- Renamed "Ressource" to "Bonus" for shorter Sevopedia category width, but also perhaps a good opportunity to match code name and game name maybe at least is how i would want to do it an AdvCiv-SAS if hopefully fine as in functionning well anyways etc.[NEWLINE]- Renamed [LINK=BONUS_GRAPES]"Wine" (Bonus) to "Grapes"[\LINK], see below at "Rules/Balance" changes in AdvCiv-SAS for details.[NEWLINE]- Renamed [LINK=BONUS_CATTLE]"Cow" (Ressource/Bonus) to "Cattle"[\LINK], and renamed [LINK=BONUS_ELEPHANTS]"Ivory" (Ressource) to "Elephants"[\LINK], hopefully clearer and more accurate (and immersive maybe), see the Sevopedia entry for details.[NEWLINE]- Renamed Religion "Taoism" to "Daoism" and all related entires (units, buildings, descriptions/history, etc), see the Sevopedia page for details or example(s) [LINK=RELIGION_DAOISM]"Daoism"[\LINK] or project/mod docs for more details[NEWLINE]- Renamed "great wonders" to "world wonders", but functionally the exact same if i am not mistaken, i hope it is clearer, more intutiive, and in line with "world project", hinting more strongly at the fact that only one is possible in the entire world if i am not mistaken, anyways etc.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][BOLD]Rules/Balance (non-exhaustive)[\BOLD]reduce TECH_COST_NOTRADE_MODIFIER from -23 to -20 (see docs and or latest updated value in GlobalDefines_advc.xml for details anyways etc), which as reminder according to the base advciv code comment if i am not mistaken anyways etc: "	advc.550d: This modifier is applied to tech costs when playing with the "No Tech Trading" option. The effect of the modifier is reduced in the early and late game. Recommended: -23, meaning that tech costs are taken times 100% - 23% = 77%. This multiplier gets further adjusted to the tech era and map size. Use 0 for BtS behavior (tech costs unaffected by the "No Tech Trading" option)."[NEWLINE]- Game starts at -50 000 BC but it increments very fast (5 000 per turn then gradually less, so after a few dozen turns approximately at normal speed you should already be at the bronze age ; view docs or ingame for latest updated info anyways etc), see also for more details (adjust to your mod path) /_1_AdvCiv-SAS/Docs_And_Appendixes/README_Tech_Tree.md. Then the year number and gameplay pace does not slow as much (at least i tried to make it so, that each end game turn doesn't take ages)[NEWLINE]- Slavery iProductionPerPopulation increased (currently from 24 to 26, see xml for latest updated value as it was too weak and also (it was) (anyways etc) too advantageous in base advciv at least in my experience anyways etc at emperor/monarch to not slave at all, so making slavery more of a risk worthy strategy, considering its cost of immediate population loss and anger, detailed reasoning in HURRY_POPULATION of  ((from) in your mod path (anyways etc)) /Assets/XML/GameInfo/CIV4HurryInfo.xml for details anyways etc), the [LINK=BUILDING_GRANARY]granary[\LINK]] building is also nerfed or/and reworked a bit rather, as a cheaper and (quite) slightly (anyways etc) less (anyways etc) food generating building, see sevopedia building ingame for details or/and docs or/and code comments for details. civ-specific versions of the granary unaffected at least not all, so the civs with a civ-specific granary gain more advantages of having one as their civ-specific building, anyways etc. Reworked in particular the [LINK=BUILDING_INCAN_TERRACE]incan granary (terrace)[\LINK] to be a production/growth building now not a culture one anymore, see also docs or/and xml code comments for details[NEWLINE]- Also replaced some civ-specific buildings, especially late game ones or/and (those i deemed but anyways etc) (too but anyways etc) inefficient, such as/like but anyways etc the russian research institute (now removed) (is (but anyways etc)) now replaced with the new [LINK=BUILDING_RUSSIAN_GORD]building gord[\LINK] for a more/stronger early game impact (based on the castle), see xml or ingame sevopedia or and docs or and other or and not for details, anyways etc[NEWLINE]- All units now are affected by city defenses (walls, castles, etc if any more/other), even gunpowder and later on units, seems more realistic to me this way, as walls can help against guns and against all (almost?) units, actually even if not having the tech for guns itself. See also for details: bIgnoreBuildingDefense in CIV4UnitInfos.xml or/and (tranlslate to english ((following) web page (anyways etc)) using web browser or such) https://gforestshade.github.io/kujira/post/civ4unitinfos/#bignorebuildingdefense for details (too anyways etc(.)) anyways etc... .[NEWLINE]- Air explore units (for example the [LINK=UNIT_AIRSHIP]Dirigible[\LINK] (old airship)) can move through all terrains, including peaks and water tiles.[NEWLINE]- Not tested if i may say but anyways etc, in theory AIs should value Iron bonus/ressource especially more, and horse more too, as an objective, using iAIObjective 10 (was 0), (ideally not restricting trade if uneeded extra in possession but not tested nor do i know too much about it anyways etc but hopefully maybe would work as intended maybe not guaranteed though anyways etc may or not anyways etc) if they don't have it, was 0.[NEWLINE]- As part of renaming wine to grapes, additionally reworked grapes: now improved by [LINK=IMPROVEMENT_FARM]IMPROVEMENT_FARM[\LINK], not anymore by the old improvement_winery now removed. This matches historicality better if i may say and if it's a word anyways etc, as wine was consumed much before 4000 BC. Also, some wines are not made from grapes at all if i am not mistaken, and grapes can be eaten out of the wine usage. Updated bonus's description with a wikipedia based one as often if not always done when updating pedia entries of/in advciv-sas or and other mods using this mod's (i.e. this advciv-sas's code anyways etc). Also, the winery/happiness part of wine is transferred to the grocer building instead, now grapes gives happiness not health anymore. Similarly although not directly related, sugar now also gives happiness not health anymore through grocer. Hopefully buffes these mid game bonus effects while making these ressources more relevant as they were (a) bit (anyways etc) weak compared to say wheat or corn. See code comments for details or the [LINK=BONUS_GRAPES]ingame sevopedia entry of the grapes[\LINK] with also maybe or not or yes anyways etc latest updated info if anything changed since i wrote (am writing currently but anyways etc also wrote when viewing from later the new now maybe or not or yes anyways etc) but this should be the bulk of it and hopefully makes gameplay more accurate or/and interesting perhaps or/and enjoyable or not anyways etc.[NEWLINE]- Adjusted the name and repartition and spawn chance as well as yields of many ressources, please view sevopedia bonus for latest info and this commit (see README_Quick_Get_Started_Guide.md that also has the commit link in the docs of this mod, at bullet point mentioning content similar to this one you are reading here and now i mean if still updated or/and accurate here or there or/and other or and not anyways etc) for details. In general, to get the main idea of it, some ressources that were weak are now stronger (for example silver, [LINK=BONUS_DEER]deer[\LINK], etc.), some are a bit weaker (for example gold, but it could barely be considered a nerf anyways etc), ressources/bonuses overall give less gpt to make game more gradual. Food land ressources spawn significantly less but after various testing increased it to values where they still spawn enough for game not to be boring or tedious, the idea is there will be more compeititon around them, as a result they also generally have a bit stronger bonuses, as well as reworked ones (for example sugar gives base hammer (productivity, horse gives base food but then improved gives only hammer, etc, see sevopedia bonus for details)), and deer in particular spawns much more as it is the only representative of snow or rather tundra ressources, its bonuses are strongest which seems accurate as it is both a very healthy and rich food. As a result, tundra cities if they have deer near them should be a lot more viable, example that may not be accurate in the future of me writing this, but for example as of now these screenshots from the drive for example show how it looks (view around screenshot 5235 to 5249 of the google drive for other samples of that time of this rework now finalized as of me writing this anyways etc): view for example screenshots 5238 of the drive (see/view anyways etc docs of the mod (README.md and such for the link anyways etc) and 5241 of the drive as well for example (same) anyways etc). Also, water ressources spawn more, especially for the now renamed clam into [LINK=BONUS_MOLLUSCS]the more general molluscs[\LINK] and fish as they are general ressources. Similarly, i have run a few tests to make sure (or at least try to (as best as i could or and wanted anyways etc hopefully accurate enough or not or yes or and other or and not anyways etc)) they don't spawn too much, so these are quite conservative tweaks but significant. With also buildings like the [LINK=BUILDING_HARBOR]harbor[\LINK] quite strongly buffed (view sevopedia for details) now, water planting should be a strong alternative to purely land ones, especially to complete an otherwise nice land location but poorer in ressources. I tried to make sure naval planting doesn't become too op or the opposite for land, i hope more versatility and strategy(ies? Anyways etc) can be used now as part of this rework, as well as more accurate gameplay. On that note, some pedia entries have been updated, [LINK=BONUS_WHALE]whales[\LINK] have been buffed too, etc, please view for details sevopedia bonus or/and docs or/and other pages anyways etc (or don't blame me if not accurate info you have hehe if i may say but do as you prefer here is all the info i have or most that was not too tedious or forgetted or rather forgotten xd if i may say but anyways etc of me to say but anyways etc... I hope gameplay will or and can be more interesting now with these balance changes without skewing too much at one side or the other, and that now there are more possibilities to play civ4 in a balanced perhaps competitive way, at least in theory and to best i could do at least of now, hopefully enjoyable or and helpful or not at least to me, may be tweaked in the future or and not, anyways etc.[NEWLINE]- Made ressources/bonuses generally spawn more towards the edges of the map, it was a bit too skewed towards central spawning for most bonuses, giving central start too big of an advantage over edge start, hopefully and with other bonuses and changes to spawn rate and such a bit closer now or/and balanced anyways etc[NEWLINE]- Shrines now require to also have the corresponding religion as a prequirement to build them (and not only just the holy city as before, which is still required now), this means for example that if you conquer a holy city that doesn't have a shrine, you can't build the shrine until/unless you have the matching religion if i am not mistaken (for example to build the [LINK=BUILDING_DAOIST_SHRINE]Daoist Shrine (Currently named "The Dai Miao" as of now (i.e. (as of?) me writing this (sevopedia) doc) anyways etc)[\LINK] you need to have the [LINK=RELIGION_DAOISM]"Daoism"[\LINK] religion too. This allows to display shrines in sevopedia and perhaps also makes more sense in terms of gameplay if it doesn't create issues hopefully, trying it to see anyways etc, see sevopedia entries or/and project/mod docs for details[NEWLINE]- Shrines now also require a tech to be built, which is their religion's tech requirement. This allows to make shrines to also appear in tech tree, plus now shrines cannot be built without also having the religion's tech matching (for example during conquest or such, anyways etc), since shrines are not special buildings unlike temple, monastery, cathedral, maybe this is a fine even desirable way to handle it (in tech tree display, also about the conquest thing or similar or other issues or examples of what may happen but anyways etc as these are world wonders unlike the temple, the monastery, and the cathedral), tech prerequirement for shrines was NONE. See also docs for details or related issues/fixes/reworks ('s) info anyways etc.[NEWLINE]- Removed religion "confucianism", added [LINK=RELIGION_PAGANISM]religion "paganism"[\LINK], more popular and relevant for civ4 maybe as many leaders were religious if i am not mistaken but with no religion, see notes_about_religious_design.txt for details in the docs online on github or(/and(anyways etc)) offline in this project files too for details[NEWLINE]- Fixed and ajusted many religious inaccuracies of favourite religions, at least those i spotted with (being) certainty (certain enough) maybe anwyas etc (or not or/and other or/and not anways etc), for example frederick the great was agnostic not christian, brennus more leaning non religous than pagan (not inaccurate since paganism didn't exist but may fix other xml related fields or maybe not such as religion preference or not anwyays etc), and genghis khan, while tengrist something and not strictly daoist, expressed or/and showed(?) a strong respect(/liking?) for (a(/the?)) daoist leader, so his favourite religion can be assessed to be daoism, especially if he had to choose between civ4 only religions, here being none or daoism, he leans more strongly -much mroe if i am not mistake but anyways etc) towrds daoism), so a leader can have a favourite religion without it being their religion of themselves, see notes mentionned above for details, and this is all if i am not mistaken, but (i thnk)(and hope but anyways etc) if this is (and i was) accurate enouh (but anyways etc) hopefuly accurate enough and (much maybe(?) maybe or not or/and other or not anyways etc) accurate now hopefully maybe or not or/and other or/and not (but) anwyays etc[NEWLINE]- Handicap (i.e. difficulty) settings are now gradually harder, lower/lowest handicap being harder, and highest difficulties being less of a grind and hard in their own ways at least in theory, see docs for details and status update on these or/and xml for details.[NEWLINE]- Other handicap settings changed in other ways, for example unit hammer costs and tech (todo) beaker/gold cost the same at all difficulties for the human player for easier calculations and strategy, please view docs or/and xml or/and handicap data tables for updated status and info if any more than this line, thanks[NEWLINE]- Barbarians are now much stronger in the early game economically, they should now grow at a similar pace than human and other players too until the middle game where they will gradually fade. They should also spawn cities more often and be relevant longer in the game, even though for now at least if not always or not they have trouble to grow past a certain size, and are still not a real player (no diplomacy and scattered cities that are independent, but that contribute together to the "barbarian(s?)((,)'s) civilization"), and become a key part in politics or invasion decisions, maybe i mean or not or/and other or not anyways etc. Their (now new)(anyways etc) overall strength increase (for example they are also harder to kill at all difficulties (less to no combat bonus against them, but never reverse bonus to them to make the game fair and balanced and fun as much as possible at least to me or and maybe (to) others ideally or maybe not (and or maybe not ideally or not or other or and not anyways etc) but anwyays etc) is gradual with difficulties), and they should not be (too) op though so hopefully not overbearing either but demanding more strategy or/and attention to hopefully make the game interesting, while filling some unsettled areas if not claimed fast enough in a quite realistic way too maybe anyways etc. They are also more calculating in who they attack, may raze cities much more than in base AdvCiv/Civ4 if am not mistaken anyways, and are more calculating in who they attack target the weak not the strong, anyways etc, or/and other changes or and not anyways etc. See [LINK=CIVILIZATION_BARBARIAN]Barbarians (Civilization)[\LINK] for details ingame or/and the XML for example for the Steam version of the game (adjust to where your AdvCiv-SAS mod is if path is different or/and you don't use the Steam version of the game) C:\Program Files (x86)\Steam\steamapps\common\Sid Meier's Civilization IV Beyond the Sword\Beyond the Sword\Mods\AdvCiv-SAS\Assets\XML\Civilizations\CIV4CivilizationInfos.xml and related files like CIV4BuildingInfos.xml and CIV4HandicapInfo.xml or/and such.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][BOLD]Fixes[\BOLD][NEWLINE]- Fixed a seemingly AdvCiv/Civ 4 bug where Gandhi's nowar attitude prob were pleased(110) / pleased(115) instead of (seemingly how should be if i am not mistaken anyways etc) pleased(110) / friendly(115)[NEWLINE]- (Seemingly now) Fixed a seemingly bug in base AdvCiv/Civ4 where barbarians could build shwedagon paya or mausolleum of mausollos for example (maybe other wonders too, and national wonders too like moai and hermitage etc) as happened in auto play, sometimes even completing them, by using iBuildUnitProb 100 or a similar high value (was 0 in base AdvCiv code or/and civ4 code anyways etc but anyways etc), seems to be extremely effective, testing more to be sure. Note: I had(have? Anyways etc) tried other approaches like iWonderConstructRand -9999 on LEADER_BARBARIAN in leader head infos xml file, or FLAVOR_MILITARY 10 but did not work at all it seems. I also removed all old logic of buildingclass NONE that seemed to not have any effect on wonder building whether it was here (national wonders) or not (removed it for world wonders, but sitll exact same results it seems of wonders being built, sometimes completed even anyways etc), maybe such barbarian wonder building behaviour/tendency/possibility was just suppressed because barbarians did not grow fast enough to support as in encourage as in do wonder building (activites) anyways etc, but now that they grow fast enough at human and other player's pace, they can make wonders or attempt to, which "derails" from their original warmongering goal and intent in AdvCiv-SAS but anyways, so refraining them from doing it, anyways etc anyways etc...[NEWLINE]- Fixed a seemingly AdvCiv/Civ 4 bug of Sevopedia Unit's placeRequires's Religion button (for example any religious missionary unit) not redirecting to sevopedia religion (nothing happens on click anyways etc), by replacing, in sevopediaunit py file, in placeRequires function/method (of this file anyways etc), WidgetTypes.WIDGET_HELP_RELIGION with WidgetTypes.WIDGET_PEDIA_JUMP_TO_RELIGION(,) as is done already by base advciv and successfully in sevopedia building, anyways etc anyways etc anyways etc[NEWLINE]- Rebalanced great artist: nerf/reduce early bomb culture instant culture gain from 700 to 500 per era, and increase culture per turn for long term victory culture path or and other uses from 12 to 20 per turn, see sevopedia ingame or xml for latest values if they changed in the meantime and i didn't (re)update them here anyways etc (anyways etc), anyways etc</English>
	</TEXT>



	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_ADVCIV_SAS_CORE_AI_PERSONALITY_PANEL_INTRO_PEDIA_SR</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]An exhaustive/extensive documentation has been written about the AI Personality Panel feature (that is) in AdvCiv-SAS (in the SevopediaLeader category), explaining, in broad, general ways how it works and how to read the data from a new player's perspective.[PARAGRAPH:2]It is recommended to read it to understand better how it works.[PARAGRAPH:2]You can view it:[NEWLINE]- online on github (todo add link),[NEWLINE]- or even if you are offline, you can read the .md files as any text file, for example with Notepad++ (or the default Notepad.exe of windows too if you prefer but Notepad.exe has less advanced features, still more than good enough for reading a doc especially if you prefer and should display all info as well if i'm not mistaken, anyways etc anyways). The file path is, for example if you have the Steam version of Civ4 (adapt to where your game and mod is if you use a non-Steam (or other than Steam) version (maybe rather anyways): "C:\Program Files (x86)\Steam\steamapps\common\Sid Meier's Civilization IV Beyond the Sword\Beyond the Sword\Mods\AdvCiv-SAS\README_AI_Personality_Panel.md")[PARAGRAPH:2]You'll get most info from there hopefully rather than me copy pasting the same doc (painfully hehe but that i would gladly do (maybe or not or other etc anyways) but better avoid if possible anyways) in sevopedia ingame and it being potentially outdated after not long, etc anyways, thanks.</English>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
