<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<Civ4GameText>
	<!-- custom: moved the lengthy part of the Sevopedia changes
	to this file, but only for AdvCiv-SAS specific changes (for example
	a new civ, a new leader, etc) that are lengthy.
	Hopefully more readable now, and perhaps exportable if some wish,
	AdvCiv or/and other mods, at least it's cleanly separated -->

	<!-- advc.008: Since the Civilopedia changes are so wordy (not the
     changes, but the copied text), I've moved them out of
     CIV4GameText_advc.xml, where the rest of the Advanced Civ game text
	 is located.
	 Starting with the two text keys changed by K-Mod
	 (one of them commented out, already in K-Mod) cut from
	 Civ4GameText_K-Mod.xml. The comments above those keys
	 are also from K-Mod. -->



	<!-- custom: more accurate and detailed entry, less western-centric -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CROSSBOWMAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A crossbow is a ranged weapon using an elastic launching device consisting of a bow-like assembly called a prod, mounted horizontally on a main frame called a tiller, which is hand-held in a similar fashion to the stock of a long gun. Crossbows shoot arrow-like projectiles called bolts or quarrels. A person who shoots crossbow is called a crossbowman, an arbalister or an arbalist (after the arbalest, a European crossbow variant used during the 12th century).[PARAGRAPH:1][TAB]Crossbows and bows use the same elastic launch principles, but differ in that an archer using a bow must draw-and-shoot in a quick and smooth motion with limited or no time for aiming, while a crossbow's design allows it to be spanned and cocked ready for use at a later time and thus affording them unlimited time to aim. When shooting bows, the archer must fully perform the draw, holding the string and arrow using various techniques while pulling it back with arm and back muscles, and then either immediately shooting instinctively without a period of aiming, or holding that form while aiming. Both demand some physical strength to do so using bows suitable for warfare, though this is easier using lighter draw-weight hunting bows. As such, their accurate and sustained use in warfare takes much practice.[PARAGRAPH:1][TAB]Crossbows avoid these potential problems by having trigger-released cocking mechanisms to maintain the tension on the string once it has been spanned - drawn - into its ready-to-shoot position, allowing these weapons to be carried cocked and ready and affording their users time to aim them. This also allows them to be readied by someone assisting their users, so multiple crossbows can be used one after the other while others reload and ready them. Crossbows are spanned into their cocked positions using a number of techniques and devices, some of which are mechanical and employ gear and pulley arrangements - levers, belt hooks, pulleys, windlasses and cranequins - to overcome very high draw weight. These potentially achieve better precision and enable their effective use by less familiarised and trained personnel, whereas the simple and composite warbows of, for example, the English and the steppe nomads require years of training, practice and familiarisation.[PARAGRAPH:1][TAB]These advantages for the crossbow are somewhat offset by the longer time needed to reload a crossbow for further shots, with the crossbows with high draw weights requiring sophisticated systems of gears and pulleys to overcome their huge draw weights that are very slow and rather awkward to employ on the battlefield. Medieval crossbows were also very inefficient, with short shot stroke lengths from the string lock to the release point of their bolts, along with the slower speeds of their steel prods and heavy strings, despite their massive draw weights compared to bows, though modern materials and crossbow designs overcome these shortcomings.[PARAGRAPH:1][TAB]The earliest known crossbows were invented in ancient China in the first millennium BC and brought about a major shift in the role of projectile weaponry in wars, especially during Qin's unification wars and later the Han campaigns (206 BC - 220 AD) against northern nomads and western states. The medieval European crossbow was called by many names, including "crossbow" itself; most of these names derived from the word ballista, an ancient Greek torsion siege engine similar in appearance but different in design principle.[[PARAGRAPH:1][TAB]In modern times, firearms have largely supplanted bows and crossbows as weapons of war, but crossbows remain widely used for competitive shooting sports and hunting, and for relatively silent shooting.</English>
	</TEXT>


	<!-- custom: based on the disciplined crossbow (kingdom of benin)'s entry (to match the format of this other civ unit (than the chinese civ unit)) and adjusted from there to fit the Chinese civ unit. -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CHINA_CHOKONU_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A crossbow is a ranged weapon using an elastic launching device consisting of a bow-like assembly called a prod, mounted horizontally on a main frame called a tiller, which is hand-held in a similar fashion to the stock of a long gun. Crossbows shoot arrow-like projectiles called bolts or quarrels. A person who shoots crossbow is called a crossbowman, an arbalister or an arbalist (after the arbalest, a European crossbow variant used during the 12th century).[PARAGRAPH:1][TAB]On top of the usual info that can be found on the [LINK=UNIT_CROSSBOWMAN]Crossbowman's page[\LINK], the repeating crossbow, also known as the repeater crossbow, and the Zhuge crossbow, also romanized Chu-ko-nu, due to its association with the Three Kingdoms-era strategist Zhuge Liang (181-234 AD), is a crossbow invented during the Warring States period in China that combined the bow spanning, bolt placing, and shooting actions into one motion.[PARAGRAPH:1][TAB]The earliest archaeological evidence of the repeating crossbow is found in the state of Chu, but it uses a pistol grip that is different from the later and more commonly known Ming dynasty (1368-1644) design.[PARAGRAPH:1][TAB]Although the repeating crossbow was in use throughout most of Chinese history until the late Qing dynasty (1644-1911), it was generally regarded as a non-military weapon suited for women, defending households against robbers.</English>
	</TEXT>



	<!-- custom: taken from C:\Program Files (x86)\Steam\steamapps\common\Sid Meier's Civilization IV Beyond the Sword\Beyond the Sword\Assets\XML\Text\CIV4GameText_Civilopedia_BTS.xml and then modified for AdvCiv-SAS -->
	<!-- custom: description from: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paganism and https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polytheism -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RELIGION_PAGANISM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Paganism (from Latin paganus 'rural, rustic', later 'civilian') is a term first used in the fourth century by early Christians for people in the Roman Empire who practiced polytheism, or ethnic religions other than Christianity, Judaism, and Samaritanism. In the time of the Roman Empire, individuals fell into the pagan class either because they were increasingly rural and provincial relative to the Christian population, or because they were not milites Christi (soldiers of Christ). Alternative terms used in Christian texts were hellene, gentile, and heathen. Ritual sacrifice was an integral part of ancient Greco-Roman religion and was regarded as an indication of whether a person was pagan or Christian. Paganism has broadly connoted the "religion of the peasantry". [PARAGRAPH:2]During and after the Middle Ages, the term paganism was applied to any non-Christian religion, and the term presumed a belief in false gods. The origin of the application of the term "pagan" to polytheism is debated. In the 19th century, paganism was adopted as a self-descriptor by members of various artistic groups inspired by the ancient world. In the 20th century, it came to be applied as a self-descriptor by practitioners of modern paganism, modern pagan movements and polytheistic reconstructionists. Modern pagan traditions often incorporate beliefs or practices, such as nature worship, that are different from those of the largest world religions. [PARAGRAPH:2]Contemporary knowledge of old pagan religions and beliefs comes from several sources, including anthropological field research records, the evidence of archaeological artifacts, and the historical accounts of ancient writers regarding cultures known to Classical antiquity. Most modern pagan religions existing today express a worldview that is pantheistic, panentheistic, polytheistic, or animistic, but some are monotheistic.[PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Prehistoric and/or Paleolithic religion[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Prehistoric religion is the religious practice of prehistoric cultures. Prehistory, the period before written records, makes up the bulk of human experience; over 99% of human experience occurred during the Paleolithic period alone. Prehistoric cultures spanned the globe and existed for over two and a half million years; their religious practices were many and varied, and the study of them is difficult due to the lack of written records describing the details of their faiths.[PARAGRAPH:1]The cognitive capacity for religion likely first emerged in Homo sapiens sapiens, or anatomically modern humans, although some scholars posit the existence of Neanderthal religion and sparse evidence exists for earlier ritual practice. Excluding sparse and controversial evidence in the Middle Paleolithic (300,000-50,000 years ago), religion emerged with certainty in the Upper Paleolithic around 50,000 years ago. Upper Paleolithic religion was possibly shamanic, oriented around the phenomenon of special spiritual leaders entering trance states to receive esoteric spiritual knowledge. These practices are extrapolated based on the rich and complex body of art left behind by Paleolithic artists, particularly the elaborate cave art and enigmatic Venus figurines they produced.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Neolithic Revolution, which established agriculture as the dominant lifestyle, occurred around 12,000 BC and ushered in the Neolithic. Neolithic society grew hierarchical and inegalitarian compared to its Paleolithic forebears, and their religious practices likely changed to suit. Neolithic religion may have become more structural and centralised than in the Paleolithic, and possibly engaged in ancestor worship both of one's individual ancestors and of the ancestors of entire groups, tribes, and settlements. One famous feature of Neolithic religion were the stone circles of the British Isles, of which the best known today is Stonehenge. A particularly well-known area of late Neolithic through Chalcolithic religion is Proto-Indo-European mythology, the religion of the people who first spoke the Proto-Indo-European language, which has been partially reconstructed through shared religious elements between early Indo-European language speakers.[PARAGRAPH:1]Bronze Age and Iron Age religions are understood in part through archaeological records, but also, more so than Paleolithic and Neolithic, through written records; some societies had writing in these ages, and were able to describe those which did not. These eras of prehistoric religion see particular cultural focus today by modern reconstructionists, with many pagan faiths today based on the pre-Christian practices of protohistoric Bronze and Iron Age societies.[PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Bronze Age to Early Iron Age[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Well-known historical polytheistic pantheons include the Sumerian gods, the Egyptian gods, the pantheon attested in Classical Antiquity (in ancient Greek and Roman religion), the Norse Æsir and Vanir, the Yoruba Orisha, and the Aztec gods.[PARAGRAPH:1]In many civilizations, pantheons tended to grow over time. Deities first worshipped as the patrons of cities or other places came to be collected together as empires extended over larger territories. Conquests could lead to the subordination of a culture's pantheon to that of the invaders, as in the Greek Titanomachia, and possibly also the Æsir-Vanir war in the Norse mythos. Cultural exchange could lead to "the same" deity being revered in two places under different names, as seen with the Greeks, Etruscans, and Romans, and also to the cultural transmission of elements of an extraneous religion, as with the ancient Egyptian deity Osiris, who was later worshipped in ancient Greece.[PARAGRAPH:1]Most ancient belief systems held that gods influenced human lives. However, the Greek philosopher Epicurus held that the gods were incorruptible but material, blissful beings who inhabited the empty spaces between worlds and did not trouble themselves with the affairs of mortals, but could be perceived by the mind, especially during sleep.[PARAGRAPH:1]The religions of the ancient Near East were mostly polytheistic, with some examples of monolatry (for example, Yahwism and Atenism). Some scholars believe that the similarities between these religions indicate that the religions are related, a belief known as patternism.[PARAGRAPH:1]Many religions of the ancient near East and their offshoots can be traced to Proto-Semitic religion. Other religions in the ancient Near East include the ancient Egyptian religion, the Luwian and Hittite religions of Asia Minor and the Sumerian religion of ancient Mesopotamia. Offshoots of Proto-Semitic religion include Canaanite religion and Arabian religion. Judaism is a development of Canaanite religion, both Indo-European and Semitic religions influenced the ancient Greek religion, and Zoroastrianism was a product of ancient Indo-Iranian religion primarily the ancient Iranian religion. In turn these religious traditions strongly influenced the later monotheistic religions of Christianity, Mandaeism, Gnosticism, Islam, and Manicheanism, which inherited their monotheism from Judaism and Zoroastrianism.[PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Folk religions[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]The majority of so-called "folk religions" in the world today (distinguished from traditional ethnic religions) are found in the Asia-Pacific region. This fact conforms to the trend of the majority of polytheist religions being found outside the western world.[PARAGRAPH:1]Folk religions are often closely tied to animism. Animistic beliefs are found in historical and modern cultures. Folk beliefs are often labeled superstitions when they are present in monotheistic societies. Folk religions often do not have organized authorities, also known as priesthoods, or any formal sacred texts. They often coincide with other religions as well. Abrahamic monotheistic religions, which dominate the western world, typically do not approve of practicing parts of multiple religions, but folk religions often overlap with others. Followers of polytheistic religions do not often problematize following practices and beliefs from multiple religions.[PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Ancient history: Classical antiquity and Late Antiquity and Christianization[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Ludwig Feuerbach defined the paganism of classical antiquity, which he termed Heidentum ('heathenry') as "the unity of religion and politics, of spirit and nature, of god and man", qualified by the observation that man in the pagan view is always defined by ethnicity, i.e., As a result, every pagan tradition is also a national tradition. Modern historians define paganism instead as the aggregate of cult acts, set within a civic rather than a national context, without a written creed or sense of orthodoxy.[PARAGRAPH:1]The developments in the religious thought of the far-flung Roman Empire during Late Antiquity need to be addressed separately, because this is the context in which Early Christianity itself developed as one of several monotheistic cults, and it was in this period that the concept of pagan developed in the first place. As Christianity emerged from Second Temple Judaism and Hellenistic Judaism, it stood in competition with other religions advocating pagan monotheism, including the cults of Dionysus, Neoplatonism, Mithraism, Gnosticism, and Manichaeanism. Dionysus in particular exhibits significant parallels with Christ, so that numerous scholars have concluded that the recasting of Jesus the wandering rabbi into the image of Christ the Logos, the divine saviour, reflects the cult of Dionysus directly. They point to the symbolism of wine and the importance it held in the mythology surrounding both Dionysus and Jesus Christ; Wick argues that the use of wine symbolism in the Gospel of John, including the story of the Marriage at Cana at which Jesus turns water into wine, was intended to show Jesus as superior to Dionysus. The scene in The Bacchae wherein Dionysus appears before King Pentheus on charges of claiming divinity is compared to the New Testament scene of Jesus being interrogated by Pontius Pilate.[PARAGRAPH:1]Proto-Albanian speakers were Christianized under the Latin sphere of influence, specifically in the 4th century CE, as shown by the basic Christian terms in Albanian, which are of Latin origin and entered Proto-Albanian before the Gheg-Tosk dialectal diversification. Regardless of the Christianization, ancient paganism persisted among Albanians, and especially within the inaccessible and deep interior - where Albanian folklore evolved over the centuries in a relatively isolated tribal culture and society - it has continued to persist, or at most it was partially transformed by the Christian, and later Muslim and Marxist beliefs, that were either to be introduced by choice or imposed by force. The Albanian traditional customary law (Kanun) has held a sacred - although secular - longstanding, unwavering and unchallenged authority with a cross-religious effectiveness over the Albanians, which is attributed to an earlier pagan code common to all the Albanian tribes. Historically, the Christian clergy has vigorously fought, but without success, the pagan rituals practiced by Albanians for traditional feasts and particular events, especially the fire rituals (Zjarri).[PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Postclassical history[\BOLD]Pagan Continuity in Mani and Mistra (800-1100) Christianity was introduced late in Mani, with the first Greek temples converted into churches during the 11th century. Byzantine monk Nikon "the Metanoite" was sent in the 10th century to convert the predominantly pagan Maniots. Although his preaching began the conversion process, it took over 200 years for the majority to accept Christianity fully by the 11th and 12th centuries. Patrick Leigh Fermor noted that the Maniots, isolated by mountains, were among the last Greeks to abandon the old religion, doing so towards the end of the 9th century:Sealed off from outside influences by their mountains, the semi-troglodytic Maniots themselves were the last of the Greeks to be converted. They only abandoned the old religion of Greece towards the end of the ninth century. It is surprising to remember that this peninsula of rock, so near the heart of the Levant from which Christianity springs, should have been baptised three whole centuries after the arrival of St. Augustine in far-away Kent.[PARAGRAPH:1]According to Constantine VII in De Administrando Imperio, the Maniots were referred to as 'Hellenes' and only fully Christianized in the 9th century, despite some church ruins from the 4th century indicating early Christian presence. The region's mountainous terrain allowed the Maniots to evade the Eastern Roman Empire's Christianization efforts, thus preserving pagan traditions, which coincided with significant years in the life of Gemistos Plethon.[PARAGRAPH:1]Another safe area for the pagans was the city of Harran which, Despite the persecution of its pagan inhabitants by Byzantine Emperor Maurice, remained a largely pagan city well into the early Islamic period. When the city was besieged by the armies of the Rashidun Caliphate in 639-640, it was the pagan community that negotiated its peaceful surrender. Under the subsequent rule of the caliphates, Harran became a major settlement within the Diyar Mudar region and retained a significant degree of autonomy. During the First Fitna, the people of Harran sided with Mu'awiya I over Ali at the Battle of Siffin in 657, which allegedly resulted in a brutal retaliation by Ali, who massacred much of the population.[PARAGRAPH:1]Under the Umayyad Caliphate (661-750), Harran prospered and was selected as the capital by the last Umayyad caliph, Marwan II, from 744 to 750. This move may have been influenced by the city's pagan sympathies and its strategic position near the empire's eastern provinces. The city's prominence under Umayyad rule saw it grow as a cultural and scholarly center, with the establishment of the first Muslim university in 717 under Umar II, attracting scholars from across the Islamic world.[PARAGRAPH:1]Although Harran lost its capital status under the Abbasid Caliphate, it continued to flourish, particularly during the reign of Harun al-Rashid (786-809), when its university became a key center for translation and intellectual activity. The local religion, blending elements of Mesopotamian paganism and Neoplatonism, persisted into the 10th century, though periodic decrees enforced conversions to Islam, especially under Al-Ma'mun in 830. Nonetheless, Harran retained its heterogeneity, with a population that included Muslims, Christians, Jews, and a variety of other religious groups.[PARAGRAPH:1]The medieval church accused sects deemed heretical such as the Waldensians and Cathars of participating in pagan fertility rites.[PARAGRAPH:1]Arab paganism gradually disappeared during Muhammad's era through Islamization. The sacred months of the Arab pagans were the 1st, 7th, 11th, and 12th months of the Islamic calendar. After Muhammad had conquered Mecca he set out to convert the pagans. One of the last military campaigns that Muhammad ordered against the Arab pagans was the Demolition of Dhul Khalasa. It occurred in April and May 632 AD, in 10AH of the Islamic Calendar. Dhul Khalasa is referred to as both an idol and a temple, and it was known by some as the Ka'ba of Yemen, built and worshipped by polytheist tribes.[PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Early Modern Renaissance[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Interest in reviving ancient Roman religious traditions can be traced to the Renaissance, with figures such as Gemistus Pletho and Julius Pomponius Laetus advocating for a revival, when Renaissance magic was practiced as a revival of Greco-Roman magic. Gemistus Plethon, who was from Mistras (near the Mani Peninsula-where paganism had endured until the 12th century) encouraged the Medici, descendants of the Maniot Latriani dynasty, to found the Neoplatonic Academy in Florence, helping to spark the Renaissance. In addition Julius Pomponius Laetus (student of Pletho) established the Roman academy which secretly celebrated the Natale di Roma, a festival linked to the foundation of Rome, and the birthday of Romulus. The Academy was dissolved in 1468 when Pope Paul II ordered the arrest and execution of some of the members, Pope Sixtus IV allowed Laetus to open the academy again until the Sack of Rome in 1527.[PARAGRAPH:1]After the French Revolution, the French lawyer Gabriel André Aucler (mid 1700s-1815) adopted the name Quintus Nautius and sought to revive paganism, styling himself as its leader. He designed religious clothing and performed pagan rites at his home. In 1799, he published La Thréicie, presenting his religious views. His teachings were later analyzed by Gérard de Nerval in Les Illuminés (1852). Admiring ancient Greece and ancient Rome, Aucler supported the French Revolution and saw it as a path to restoring an ancient republic. He took the name Quintus Nautius, claimed Roman priestly lineage, and performed Orphic rites at his home. His followers were mainly his household. In 1799, he published La Thréicie, advocating a revival of paganism in France, condemning Christianity, and promoting universal animation.[PARAGRAPH:1]In the 17th century, the description of paganism turned from a theological aspect to an ethnological one, and religions began to be understood as part of the ethnic identities of peoples, and the study of the religions of so-called primitive peoples triggered questions as to the ultimate historical origin of religion. Jean Bodin viewed pagan mythology as a distorted version of Christian truths. Nicolas Fabri de Peiresc saw the pagan religions of Africa of his day as relics that were in principle capable of shedding light on the historical paganism of Classical Antiquity.[PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Late Modern Romanticism[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]The 19th century also saw much scholarly interest in the reconstruction of pagan mythology from folklore or fairy tales. This was notably attempted by the Brothers Grimm, especially Jacob Grimm in his Teutonic Mythology, and Elias Lönnrot with the compilation of the Kalevala. The work of the Brothers Grimm influenced other collectors, both inspiring them to collect tales and leading them to similarly believe that the fairy tales of a country were particularly representative of it, to the neglect of cross-cultural influence. Among those influenced were the Russian Alexander Afanasyev, the Norwegians Peter Christen Asbjørnsen and Jørgen Moe, and the Englishman Joseph Jacobs.[PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Late 20th century[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]The 1960s and 1970s saw a resurgence in neo-Druidism as well as the rise of modern Germanic paganism in the United States and in Iceland. In the 1970s, Wicca was notably influenced by feminism, leading to the creation of an eclectic, Goddess-worshipping movement known as Dianic Wicca. The 1979 publication of Margot Adler's Drawing Down the Moon and Starhawk's The Spiral Dance opened a new chapter in public awareness of paganism. With the growth and spread of large, pagan gatherings and festivals in the 1980s, public varieties of Wicca continued to further diversify into additional, eclectic sub-denominations, often heavily influenced by the New Age and counter-culture movements. These open, unstructured or loosely structured traditions contrast with British Traditional Wicca, which emphasizes secrecy and initiatory lineage.[PARAGRAPH:1]By the time of the collapse of the former Soviet Union in 1991, freedom of religion was legally established across Russia and a number of other newly independent states, allowing for the growth in both Christian and non-Christian religions.[PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]21st century[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]In the 2000s, Associazione Tradizionale Pietas began reconstructing temples across Italy and sought legal recognition from the state, drawing inspiration from similar groups like YSEE in Greece. In 2023, Pietas participated in the ECER meeting, resulting in the signing of the Riga Declaration, which calls for the recognition of European ethnic religions. Public rituals, such as those celebrating the ancient festival of the Natale di Roma, have also resumed in recent years.[PARAGRAPH:1]The idea of practicing Roman religion in the modern era has spread beyond Italy, with practitioners found in countries across Europe and the Americas. The most prominent international organization is Nova Roma, founded in 1998, with active groups worldwide.[PARAGRAPH:1]Modern paganism, or Neopaganism, includes reconstructed practice such as Roman Polytheistic Reconstructionism, Hellenism, Slavic Native Faith, Celtic Reconstructionist Paganism, or heathenry, as well as modern eclectic traditions such as Wicca and its many offshoots, Neo-Druidism, and Discordianism.[PARAGRAPH:1]However, there often exists a distinction or separation between some polytheistic reconstructionists such as Hellenism and revivalist neopagans like Wiccans. The divide is over numerous issues such as the importance of accurate orthopraxy according to ancient sources available, the use and concept of magic, which calendar to use and which holidays to observe, as well as the use of the term pagan itself.[PARAGRAPH:1]In modern times, Heathen and Heathenry are increasingly used to refer to those branches of modern paganism inspired by the pre-Christian religions of the Germanic, Scandinavian and Anglo-Saxon peoples.[PARAGRAPH:1]In Iceland, the members of Ásatrúarfélagið account for nearly 2% of the total population, therefore being nearly six thousand people. In Lithuania, many people practice Romuva, a revived version of the pre-Christian religion of that country. Lithuania was among the last areas of Europe to be Christianized. Heathenry has been established on a formal basis in Australia since at least the 1930s.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<!-- custom: from https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Temple and https://pickvocab.com/dictionary/en/pagan ,(;?(anyways etc)) (and) adjusted or not for AdvCiv-SAS anyways etc -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_PAGAN_TEMPLE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A temple (from the Latin templum) is a place of worship, a building used for spiritual rituals and activities such as prayer and sacrifice. By convention, the specially built places of worship of some religions are commonly called "temples" in English, while those of other religions are not, even though they fulfill very similar functions.[PARAGRAPH:1]The form and function of temples are thus very variable, though they are often considered by believers to be, in some sense, the "house" of one or more deities. Typically, offerings of some sort are made to the deity, and other rituals are enacted, and a special group of clergy maintain and operate the temple. The degree to which the whole population of believers can access the building varies significantly; often parts, or even the whole main building, can only be accessed by the clergy. Temples typically have a main building and a larger precinct, which may contain many other buildings or may be a dome-shaped structure, much like an igloo.[PARAGRAPH:1]The word comes from Ancient Rome, where a templum constituted a sacred precinct as defined by a priest, or augur. It has the same root as the word "template", a plan in preparation for the building that was marked out on the ground by the augur.[PARAGRAPH:1]The pagan temple was dedicated to the worship of ancient gods.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<!-- custom: from https://www.paganbookofhours.org/horae/monasticfaq.html#:~:text=The%20Order%20of%20the%20Horae,meditative%20work%2C%20ritual%20and%20prayer. ,(;?(anyways etc)) (and) adjusted or not for AdvCiv-SAS anyways etc -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_PAGAN_MONASTERY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A monastery is a building where monks can retreat from the world and concentrate upon the divine. Usually a monastery will have strict rules of conduct to protect its unworldly members from temptation. In some monasteries, the monks are totally silent; in others no visitors are allowed inside. Monasteries usually have many daily rituals and religious services. [PARAGRAPH:1]Following description from the Order of the Horae Pagan Monasticism:[PARAGRAPH:1]Modern neo-paganism, based loosely as it is on ancient traditions, has many different sects and forms....just like the religions of our ancestors. Some sects, like Gardnerianism, are more formal and structured; others are looser and more hedonistic. There's no one structure that works for all pagan sects, just as there is no one structure that works for all people. Similarly, ancient traditions varied widely in their level of structure and formality. The experience of a Bacchic Maenad and a Vestal Virgin are radically different, even though they theoretically believed in and honored the same set of gods, and came from similar cultural worldviews. There's room for all sorts of orders, sects, and structures in modern neo-paganism as well. Because it draws from so many traditions, neo-paganism can fit just about any structure. There are a few things that we believe are inherent to neo-pagan belief; one of those is polytheism and/or pantheism, and another is reverence for the Earth and Nature as sacred. With those as givens, there are a wide variety of possible group structures - and that's a good thing. If there's one thing that Nature has to teach us, it's that Variety Is Good.[PARAGRAPH:1]The reason why most modern neo-pagan groups are so unstructured, nonhierarchical, and hedonistic is that statistically, most pagans today were not born and raised pagans. The majority of them came to paganism out of another faith, and many left that faith out of distaste for its outdated and unquestioned rules. Many pagans carry unhealed religious wounds from their early life that make them shun any structure that even vaguely resembles what they grew up with, even if the underlying assumptions are radically different. We tend to think that this is throwing out the baby with the bath water. That's why Asphodel is about reclaiming.....taking the useful parts and clearing out what's not useful to us. Almost every world religion has some sort of monastic tradition - Christian, Buddhist, Hindu, Shinto, etc. - and some have several. In each of these religions, monasticism is seen as a special calling for a very few people. These individuals are drawn to a life of structure, discipline, contemplation, service to others, immersion in spirituality, and the oneness of religious community. It's not for everyone, or even for every monastic's whole life - for example, in Buddhist countries, young people are often encouraged to spend a month or a year as a monk or nun, then go back to the outside world. A few stay; most leave. Monasteries and abbeys are places of sanctuary, retreats where one can go for the religious equivalent of a full-body immersion in the waters of the spirit. They are often a source of inspiration and service to the larger community.[PARAGRAPH:1]The definition of Paganism is not "whatever is the polar opposite of the faith of my childhood", or "whatever is in opposition to the dominant cultural model" or "whatever best supports my radical politics". We believe that neo-paganism needs to grow beyond its youthful rebellion and embrace real diversity, including the more "conservative" or structured elements.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_PAGAN_CATHEDRAL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]In Civilization IV, a cathedral is defined as an especially large and ornate religious building where the faithful worship. Only the most prosperous cities can afford to create cathedrals, as they require huge amounts of raw material and years of dedicated labor by skilled craftsmen. For example, the Notre Dame Cathedral in Paris, France, took over two centuries to complete. [PARAGRAPH:1]. </English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_PAGAN_SHRINE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB].</English>
	</TEXT>



	<!-- custom: from https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taoism and adjusted or not for AdvCiv-SAS anyways etc, renamed in particular "Tao Te Ching" to "Dao de jing" (https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dao_de_jing) or/and other changes or and not, which generally consist of naming "Tao" to "Dao" when relevant or simply maybe possible (almost always and everytime i could or/and wanted or and other or and not anyways etc as said after in this code comment anyways etc(anyways etc anyways etc...)) too i.e. not always but whenever i could or/and wanted or/and other or/and not, and possibly other changes i did or maybe not or yes or not or etc or and other or and not anyways etc -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RELIGION_DAOISM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Daoism or Taoism is a diverse philosophical and religious tradition indigenous to China, emphasizing harmony with the Dao _ (pinyin: dào; Wade-Giles: tao). With a range of meaning in Chinese philosophy, translations of Dao include 'way', 'road', 'path', or 'technique', generally understood in the Daoist sense as an enigmatic process of transformation ultimately underlying reality. Daoist thought has informed the development of various practices within the Daoist tradition and beyond, including forms of meditation, astrology, qigong, feng shui, and internal alchemy. A common goal of Daoist practice is self-cultivation, a deeper appreciation of the Dao, and more harmonious existence. Daoist ethics vary, but generally emphasize such virtues as effortless action, naturalness, simplicity, and the three treasures of compassion, frugality, and humility.[PARAGRAPH:1]The core of Daoist thought crystallized during the early Warring States period (c. 450 - c. 300 BCE), during which the epigrammatic Dao de jing and the anecdotal Zhuangzi-widely regarded as the fundamental texts of Daoist philosophy-were largely composed. They form the core of a body of Daoist writings accrued over the following centuries, which was assembled by monks into the Daozang canon starting in the 5th century CE. Early Daoism drew upon diverse influences, including the Shang and Zhou state religions, Naturalism, Mohism, Confucianism, various Legalist theories, as well as the I Ching and Spring and Autumn Annals.[PARAGRAPH:1]Although Daoism and Confucianism developed significant differences, they are not seen as mutually incompatible or exclusive. The relationship between Daoism and Buddhism upon the latter's introduction to China is characterized as one of mutual influence, with long-running discourses shared between Daoists and Buddhists; the distinct Mahayana tradition of Zen that emerged during the Tang dynasty (607-917) incorporates many ideas from Daoism.[PARAGRAPH:1]Many Daoist denominations recognize deities, often ones shared with other traditions, which are venerated as superhuman figures exemplifying Daoist virtues. They can be roughly divided into two categories of "gods" and xian (or "immortals"). Xian were immortal beings with vast supernatural powers, also describing a principled, moral person. Since Daoist thought is syncretic and deeply rooted in Chinese culture for millennia, it is often unclear which denominations should be considered "Daoist".[PARAGRAPH:1]The status of daoshi, or 'Daoist master', is traditionally attributed only to clergy in Daoist organizations, who distinguish between their traditions and others in Chinese folk religion. Though generally lacking motivation for strong hierarchies, Daoist philosophy has often served as a theoretical foundation for politics, warfare, and Daoist organizations. Daoist secret societies precipitated the Yellow Turban Rebellion during the late Han dynasty, attempting to create what has been characterized as a Daoist theocracy.[PARAGRAPH:1]Today, Daoism is one of five religious doctrines officially recognized by the Chinese government, also having official status in Hong Kong and Macau. It is considered a major religion in Taiwan, and also has significant populations of adherents throughout the Sinosphere and Southeast Asia. In the West, Daoism has taken on various forms, both those hewing to historical practice, as well as highly synthesized practices variously characterized as new religious movements.[PARAGRAPH:2]"Dao" and "Tao" are different romanized spellings of the same Chinese word: _.[NEWLINE]-"Dao" is the romanized spelling in the Hanyu Pinyin system, officially adopted in China in the 1950s, which has largely replaced Wade-Giles romanization.[NEWLINE]-"Tao" is the romanized spelling in the Wade-Giles system, which was predominant in English-speaking countries until the late 20th century, and remains in use for certain terms with strongly established spellings.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Standard Chinese pronunciation of _ is /tau_/.[NEWLINE]-In Standard Chinese, the initial consonant, /t/, is not voiced like the /d/ in the English word "do".[NEWLINE]-In Standard Chinese, the initial consonant, /t/, is not aspirated like the /t_/ in the English word "to".[PARAGRAPH:1]Neither an English pronunciation like /da_/ (an English pronunciation of "Dao") nor an English pronunciation like /t_a_/ (an English pronunciation of "Tao") is the same as the Standard Chinese pronunciation of _.[PARAGRAPH:1]These differences in the initial consonants used in English and Standard Chinese may contribute to there being different methods of romanizing Chinese, which consequently may confuse English speakers when encountering both "Dao" and "Tao" spellings for the same Chinese term.[PARAGRAPH:1]One authority calls the pronunciation with a _t_ as in "tie" (with a /t_/) to be a "mispronunciation" originally caused by the "clumsy Wade-Giles system", which misled most readers. Standard Chinese phonology does not have the same sound inventory as English phonology; the Wade-Giles romanization system provides spellings in the Latin alphabet, but they are not meant to indicate an exact English pronunciation in the same way as though they were English words.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DAOIST_TEMPLE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]In Civilization IV, a temple is defined as a building where the faithful come to worship. Christians call their temples "churches," while Muslims call theirs "mosques," and Jews call theirs, simply, "temples." Temples are far more common than cathedrals, but much less large and ornate. Even the smallest village can possess a temple. [PARAGRAPH:1]Daoist temples are often attractive, brightly-colored buildings, filled with statues of divine beings. Priests may or may not be in attendance. Daoism is a ritualistic religion, and the temple is often used for ceremonies ranging from parades to exorcisms. The ceremonies themselves tend to be loud and colorful, full of chanting, singing, clashing symbols, and firecrackers.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DAOIST_MONASTERY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A monastery is a building where monks can retreat from the world and concentrate upon the divine. Usually a monastery will have strict rules of conduct to protect its unworldly members from temptation. In some monasteries, the monks are totally silent; in others no visitors are allowed inside. Monasteries usually have many daily rituals and religious services. [PARAGRAPH:1] Throughout the ages monasteries have often been centers of learning. In remote areas the monks may be the only literate people for miles around. Monks have often been employed as scribes, copying out the words of their religion's sacred scripture. Monasteries frequently have extensive libraries, holding religious, scientific, medical and philosophical texts. [PARAGRAPH:1]Daoists began constructing monasteries during the Tang period, from 600 - 900 BC. They learned the concept of monasticism from the Buddhists, who greatly influenced Daoism during this period.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DAOIST_CATHEDRAL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]In Civilization IV, a cathedral is defined as an especially large and ornate religious building where the faithful worship. Only the most prosperous cities can afford to create cathedrals, as they require huge amounts of raw material and years of dedicated labor by skilled craftsmen. For example, the Notre Dame Cathedral in Paris, France, took over two centuries to complete. [PARAGRAPH:1]Many of the most elaborate and extensive Daoist religious buildings are pagodas - tiered towers with multiple eaves. This building style originated in Nepal and has since spread across much of Asia. Unfortunately, many great Daoist pagodas were constructed of wood - wood holds special religious significance for Daoists - and have not withstood the onslaught of time. [PARAGRAPH:1]Daoist pagodas tend to be bright and colorful structures, with broad curving roofs that are adorned with divine figures and traditional symbols of luck such as dragons and carp. Daoism is not a selfish faith, and the pagodas may have rooms or shrines dedicated to Buddhist meditation and/or Hindu deities. </English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DAOIST_SHRINE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Daoist Dai Miao, or "Temple of the God of Mount Tai," is located on Mount Tai in Shandong Province, China. One of the "five sacred mountains of China," Mount Tai has been of great religious importance throughout Chinese history, and evidence suggests that pilgrims have been climbing the mountain for at least 3000 years. There are 22 temples, 97 ruins, and several thousand stone tablets and inscriptions scattered across the its rugged shoulders.[PARAGRAPH:2]The Dai Miao is the largest temple complex on the mountain, covering an area of about a million square feet. The buildings within the temple have been built and rebuilt a number of times, the most recent major overhaul occurring about 2000 years ago during the Han Dynasty. [PARAGRAPH:2]In its latest incarnation, the temple is a replica of the Imperial Palace. The complex has five major halls and many small buildings. The most important building is the Palace of Heavenly Blessings, constructed in 1008. The building contains a mural titled, "The God of Mount Tai Making a Journey." The mural is 10 feet in height by about 200 feet long. It was painted in 1009, making it 1004 years old. [PARAGRAPH:2]Next to the Palace of Heavenly Blessings stand the Yaocan Pavilion and the entrance archway, as well as the Bronze Pavilion in the northeast corner. The Dai Temple is surrounded by the 2,100 year-old Han Dynasty cypresses. Beloved as much for its rugged beauty as for its religious significance, the Dai Miao remains one of the most important religious structures in the world.</English>
	</TEXT>



	<!-- custom: from https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hinduism and adjusted or not for AdvCiv-SAS anyways etc -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RELIGION_HINDUISM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Hinduism is an umbrella term for a range of Indian religious and spiritual traditions (sampradayas) that are unified by adherence to the Vedas, the oldest collection of Sanskrit texts, as well as to the concept of dharma, a cosmic order maintained by its followers through rituals and righteous living. The word Hindu is an exonym, and while Hinduism has been called the oldest religion in the world, it has also been described by the modern term Sanatana Dharma (lit. 'eternal dharma') emphasizing its eternal nature. Another endonym for Hinduism is Vaidika Dharma (lit. 'Vedic dharma').[PARAGRAPH:1]Hinduism entails diverse systems of thought, marked by a range of shared concepts that discuss theology, mythology, among other topics in textual sources. Hindu texts have been classified into Sruti (lit. 'heard') and Smrti (lit. 'remembered'). The major Hindu scriptures are the Vedas, the Upanishads, the Puranas, the Mahabharata (including the Bhagavad Gita), the Ramayana, and the Agamas. Prominent themes in Hindu beliefs include the karma (action, intent and consequences), the samsara (the cycle of death and rebirth) and the four Purusarthas, proper goals or aims of human life, namely: dharma (ethics/duties), artha (prosperity/work), kama (desires/passions) and moksha (liberation/freedom from passions and ultimately samsara). Hindu religious practices include devotion (bhakti), worship (puja), sacrificial rites (yajna), and meditation (dhyana) and yoga. Hinduism has no central doctrinal authority and many Hindus do not claim to belong to any denomination. However, scholarly studies notify four major denominations: Shaivism, Shaktism, Smartism, and Vaishnavism. The six astika schools of Hindu philosophy that recognise the authority of the Vedas are: Samkhya, Yoga, Nyaya, Vaisheshika, Mimamsa, and Vedanta.[PARAGRAPH:1]While the traditional Itihasa-Purana and its derived Epic-Puranic chronology present Hinduism as a tradition existing for thousands of years, scholars regard Hinduism as a fusion or synthesis of Brahmanical orthopraxy with various Indian cultures, having diverse roots and no specific founder. This Hindu synthesis emerged after the Vedic period, between c. 500 to 200 BCE, and c. 300 CE, in the period of the second urbanisation and the early classical period of Hinduism when the epics and the first Puranas were composed. It flourished in the medieval period, with the decline of Buddhism in India. Since the 19th century, modern Hinduism, influenced by western culture, has acquired a great appeal in the West, most notably reflected in the popularisation of yoga and various sects such as Transcendental Meditation and the Hare Krishna movement.[PARAGRAPH:1]Hinduism is the world's third-largest religion, with approximately 1.20 billion followers, or around 15% of the global population, known as Hindus. It is the most widely professed faith in India, Nepal, Mauritius, and in Bali, Indonesia. Significant numbers of Hindu communities are found in the countries of South Asia, in Southeast Asia, in the Caribbean, Middle East, North America, Europe, Oceania, Africa, and other regions.[PARAGRAPH:2]The word Hindu is an exonym, derived from Sanskrit Sindhu, the name of the Indus River as well as the country of the lower Indus basin (Sindh). The Proto-Iranian sound change *s > h occurred between 850 and 600 BCE. "Hindu" occurs in Avesta as heptahindu, equivalent to Rigvedic sapta sindhu. The 6th-century BCE inscription of Darius I mentions Hindush (referring to Sindh) among his provinces. Hindustan (spelt "hndstn") is found in a Sasanian inscription from the 3rd century CE. The term Hindu in these ancient records is a geographical term and did not refer to a religion. In Arabic texts, "Hind", a derivative of Persian "Hindu", was used to refer to the land beyond the Indus and therefore, all the people in that land were "Hindus", according to historian Romila Thapar. By the 13th century, Hindustan emerged as a popular alternative name of India.[PARAGRAPH:1]Among the earliest known records of 'Hindu' with connotations of religion may be in the 7th-century CE Chinese text Record of the Western Regions by Xuanzang. In the 14th century, 'Hindu' appeared in several texts in Persian, Sanskrit and Prakrit within India, and subsequently in vernacular languages, often in comparative contexts to contrast them with Muslims or "Turks". Examples include the 14th-century Persian text Futuhu's-salatin by 'Abd al-Malik Isami, Jain texts such as Vividha Tirtha Kalpa and Vidyatilaka, circa 1400 Apabhramsa text Kirttilata by Vidyapati, 16-18th century Bengali Gaudiya Vaishnava texts, etc. These native usages of "Hindu" were borrowed from Persian, and they did not always have a religious connotation, but they often did. In Indian texts, Hindu dharma ("Hindu religion") was often used to refer to Hinduism.[PARAGRAPH:1]Starting in the 17th century, European merchants and colonists adopted "Hindu" (often with the English spelling "Hindoo") to refer to residents of India as a religious community. The term got increasingly associated with the practices of Brahmins, who were also referred to as "Gentiles" and "Gentoos". Terms such as "Hindoo faith" and "Hindoo religion" were often used, eventually leading to the appearance of "Hindooism" in a letter of Charles Grant in 1787, who used it along with "Hindu religion". The first Indian to use "Hinduism" may have been Raja Ram Mohan Roy in 1816-17. By the 1840s, the term "Hinduism" was used by those Indians who opposed British colonialism, and who wanted to distinguish themselves from Muslims and Christians. Before the British began to categorise communities strictly by religion, Indians generally did not define themselves exclusively through their religious beliefs; instead identities were largely segmented on the basis of locality, language, varna, jati, occupation, and sect.</English>
	</TEXT>



	<!-- custom: from https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Judaism and adjusted or not for AdvCiv-SAS anyways etc -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RELIGION_JUDAISM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Judaism is an Abrahamic, monotheistic, ethnic religion that comprises the collective spiritual, cultural, and legal traditions of the Jewish people. Religious Jews regard Judaism as their means of observing the Mosaic covenant, which was established between God and the Israelites, their ancestors. The religion is considered one of the earliest monotheistic religions.[PARAGRAPH:1]Jewish religious doctrine encompasses a wide body of texts, practices, theological positions, and forms of organization. Among Judaism's core texts is the Torah-the first five books of the Hebrew Bible-and a collection of ancient Hebrew scriptures. The Tanakh, known in English as the Hebrew Bible, has the same books as Protestant Christianity's Old Testament, with some differences in order and content. In addition to the original written scripture, the supplemental Oral Torah is represented by later texts, such as the Midrash and the Talmud. The Hebrew-language word torah can mean "teaching", "law", or "instruction", although "Torah" can also be used as a general term that refers to any Jewish text or teaching that expands or elaborates on the original Five Books of Moses. Representing the core of the Jewish spiritual and religious tradition, the Torah is a term and a set of teachings that are explicitly self-positioned as encompassing at least seventy, and potentially infinite, facets and interpretations. Judaism's texts, traditions, and values strongly influenced later Abrahamic religions, including Christianity and Islam. Hebraism, like Hellenism, played a seminal role in the formation of Western civilization through its impact as a core background element of early Christianity.[PARAGRAPH:1]Within Judaism, there are a variety of religious movements, most of which emerged from Rabbinic Judaism, which holds that God revealed his laws and commandments to Moses on Mount Sinai in the form of both the Written and Oral Torah. Historically, all or part of this assertion was challenged by various groups, such as the Sadducees and Hellenistic Judaism during the Second Temple period; the Karaites during the early and later medieval period; and among segments of the modern non-Orthodox denominations. Some modern branches of Judaism, such as Humanistic Judaism, may be considered secular or nontheistic. Today, the largest Jewish religious movements are Orthodox Judaism (Haredi and Modern Orthodox), Conservative Judaism, and Reform Judaism. Major sources of difference between these groups are their approaches to halakha (Jewish law), rabbinic authority and tradition, and the significance of the State of Israel. Orthodox Judaism maintains that the Torah and Halakha are explicitly divine in origin, eternal and unalterable, and that they should be strictly followed. Conservative and Reform Judaism are more liberal, with Conservative Judaism generally promoting a more traditionalist interpretation of Judaism's requirements than Reform Judaism. A typical Reform position is that Halakha should be viewed as a set of general guidelines rather than as a set of restrictions and obligations whose observance is required of all Jews. Historically, special courts enforced Halakha; today, these courts still exist but the practice of Judaism is mostly voluntary. Authority on theological and legal matters is not vested in any one person or organization, but in the Jewish sacred texts and the rabbis and scholars who interpret them.[PARAGRAPH:1]Jews are an ethnoreligious group including those born Jewish, in addition to converts to Judaism. In 2021, the world Jewish population was estimated at 15.2 million, or roughly 0.195% of the world population, although religious observance varies from strict to nonexistent.[PARAGRAPH:2]The term Judaism derives from Iudaismus, a Latinized form of the Ancient Greek Ioudaismos (_ Greek: _, from the verb _, "to side with or imitate the [Judeans]"). Its ultimate source was Hebrew: _, romanized: Yehudah Judah", which is also the source of the Hebrew term for Judaism, _ Yahadut. The term _ first appears in the Koine Greek book of 2 Maccabees in the 2nd century BCE (i.e. 2 Maccabees 2:21, 8:1 and 14:38) . In the context of the age and period it meant "seeking or forming part of a cultural entity". It resembled its antonym Hellenismos, a word signifying people's submission to Hellenistic cultural norms. The conflict between Ioudaismos and Hellenismos lay behind the Maccabean Revolt and hence the invention of the term Ioudaismos.[PARAGRAPH:1]Shaye J. D. Cohen writes in his book The Beginnings of Jewishness:[PARAGRAPH:1]"We are tempted, of course, to translate [Ioudaïsmós] as "Judaism," but this translation is too narrow, because in this first occurrence of the term, Ioudaïsmós has not yet been reduced to the designation of a religion. It means rather "the aggregate of all those characteristics that makes Judaeans Judaean (or Jews Jewish)." Among these characteristics, to be sure, are practices and beliefs that we would today call "religious," but these practices and beliefs are not the sole content of the term. Thus Ioudaïsmós should be translated not as "Judaism" but as Judaeanness."[PARAGRAPH:1]Daniel R. Schwartz, however, argues that "Judaism", especially in the context of the Book of Maccabees, refers to the religion, as opposed to the culture and politics of the Judean state. He believes it reflected the ideological divide between the Pharisees and Sadducees and, implicitly, anti-Hasmonean and pro-Hasmonean factions in Judean society.[PARAGRAPH:1]According to the Oxford English Dictionary the earliest citation in English where the term was used to mean "the profession or practice of the Jewish religion; the religious system or polity of the Jews" is Robert Fabyan's The newe cronycles of Englande and of Fraunce (1516). "Judaism" as a direct translation of the Latin Iudaismus first occurred in a 1611 English translation of the Biblical apocrypha (the Deuterocanonical books in the Catholic Church and Eastern Orthodoxy), 2 Macc. ii. 21: "Those that behaved themselves manfully to their honour for Iudaisme."</English>
	</TEXT>



	<!-- custom: from https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buddhism and adjusted or not for AdvCiv-SAS anyways etc -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RELIGION_BUDDHISM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Buddhism, also known as Buddhadharma and Dharmavinaya, is an Indian religion based on teachings attributed to the Buddha, a wandering teacher who lived in the 6th or 5th century BCE. It is the world's fourth-largest religion, with almost 500 million followers, known as Buddhists, who comprise seven percent of the global population. It arose in the eastern Gangetic plain as a Sramana movement in the 5th century BCE, and gradually spread throughout much of Asia. Buddhism has subsequently played a major role in Asian culture and spirituality, eventually spreading to the West in the 20th century.[PARAGRAPH:1]According to tradition, the Buddha instructed his followers in a path of development which leads to awakening and full liberation from dukkha (lit. 'suffering, unease'). He regarded this path as a Middle Way between extremes such as asceticism or sensual indulgence. Teaching that dukkha arises alongside attachment or clinging, the Buddha advised meditation practices and ethical precepts rooted in non-harming. Widely observed teachings include the Four Noble Truths, the Noble Eightfold Path, and the doctrines of dependent origination, karma, and the three marks of existence. Other commonly observed elements include the Triple Gem, the taking of monastic vows, and the cultivation of perfections (paramita).[PARAGRAPH:1]The Buddhist canon is vast, with philosophical traditions and many different textual collections in different languages (such as Sanskrit, Pali, Tibetan, and Chinese). Buddhist schools vary in their interpretation of the paths to liberation (marga) as well as the relative importance and "canonicity" assigned to various Buddhist texts, and their specific teachings and practices. Two major extant branches of Buddhism are generally recognized by scholars: Theravada (lit. 'School of the Elders') and Mahayana (lit. 'Great Vehicle'). The Theravada tradition emphasizes the attainment of nirvana (lit. 'extinguishing') as a means of transcending the individual self and ending the cycle of death and rebirth (samsara), while the Mahayana tradition emphasizes the Bodhisattva ideal, in which one works for the liberation of all sentient beings. Additionally, Vajrayana (lit. 'Indestructible Vehicle'), a body of teachings incorporating esoteric tantric techniques, may be viewed as a separate branch or tradition within Mahayana.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Theravada branch has a widespread following in Sri Lanka as well as in Southeast Asia, namely Myanmar, Thailand, Laos, and Cambodia. The Mahayana branch-which includes the East Asian traditions of Tiantai, Chan, Pure Land, Zen, Nichiren, and Tendai is predominantly practised in Nepal, Bhutan, China, Malaysia, Vietnam, Taiwan, Korea, and Japan. Tibetan Buddhism, a form of Vajrayana, is practised in the Himalayan states as well as in Mongolia and Russian Kalmykia and Tuva. Japanese Shingon also preserves the Vajrayana tradition as transmitted to China. Historically, until the early 2nd millennium, Buddhism was widely practiced in the Indian subcontinent before declining there; it also had a foothold to some extent elsewhere in Asia, namely Afghanistan, Turkmenistan, Uzbekistan, and Tajikistan.[PARAGRAPH:2]The names Buddha Dharma and Bauddha Dharma come from Sanskrit: _ _ and _ _ respectively ("doctrine of the Enlightened One" and "doctrine of Buddhists"). The term Dharmavinaya comes from Sanskrit: _, literally meaning "doctrines [and] disciplines".[PARAGRAPH:1]The Buddha ("the Awakened One") was a Sramana who lived in South Asia c. 6th or 5th century BCE. Followers of Buddhism, called Buddhists in English, referred to themselves as Sakyan-s or Sakyabhiksu in ancient India. Buddhist scholar Donald S. Lopez asserts they also used the term Bauddha, although scholar Richard Cohen asserts that that term was used only by outsiders to describe Buddhists.</English>
	</TEXT>



	<!-- custom: from https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christianity and adjusted or not for AdvCiv-SAS anyways etc -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RELIGION_CHRISTIANITY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Christianity is an Abrahamic monotheistic religion, professing that Jesus is the Son of God and was raised from the dead after his crucifixion, whose coming as the messiah (Christ) was prophesied in the Old Testament and chronicled in the New Testament. It is the world's largest and most widespread religion with over 2.4 billion followers, comprising around 31.2% of the world population. Its adherents, known as Christians, are estimated to make up a majority of the population in 157 countries and territories.[PARAGRAPH:1]Christianity remains culturally diverse in its Western and Eastern branches, and doctrinally diverse concerning justification and the nature of salvation, ecclesiology, ordination, and Christology. The creeds of various Christian denominations generally hold in common Jesus as the God the Son-the Logos incarnated-who ministered, suffered, and died on a cross, but rose from the dead for the salvation of humankind; and referred to as the gospel, meaning the "good news". The four canonical gospels of Matthew, Mark, Luke and John describe Jesus' life and teachings as preserved in the early Christian tradition, with the Old Testament as the gospels' respected background.[PARAGRAPH:1]Christianity began in the 1st century, after the death of Jesus, as a Judaic sect with Hellenistic influence in the Roman province of Judaea. The disciples of Jesus spread their faith around the Eastern Mediterranean area, despite significant persecution. The inclusion of Gentiles led Christianity to slowly separate from Judaism (2nd century). Emperor Constantine I decriminalized Christianity in the Roman Empire by the Edict of Milan (313), later convening the Council of Nicaea (325) where Early Christianity was consolidated into what would become the state religion of the Roman Empire (380). The Church of the East and Oriental Orthodoxy both split over differences in Christology (5th century), while the Eastern Orthodox Church and the Catholic Church separated in the East-West Schism (1054). Protestantism split into numerous denominations from the Catholic Church in the Reformation era (16th century). Following the Age of Discovery (15th-17th century), Christianity expanded throughout the world via missionary work, evangelism, immigration, and extensive trade. Christianity played a prominent role in the development of Western civilization, particularly in Europe from late antiquity and the Middle Ages.[PARAGRAPH:1]The three main branches of Christianity are Roman Catholicism (1.3 billion people), Protestantism (625 million-900 million), and Eastern Orthodoxy (230 million), while other prominent branches include Oriental Orthodoxy (60 million), Restorationism (35 million), and the Church of the East (600,000). Smaller church communities number in the thousands despite efforts toward unity (ecumenism). In the West, Christianity remains the dominant religion even with a decline in adherence, with about 70% of that population identifying as Christian. Christianity is growing in Africa and Asia, the world's most populous continents. Christians are persecuted in some regions of the world, particularly where they are in the minority in the Middle East, North Africa, East Asia, and South Asia.[PARAGRAPH:2]Early Jewish Christians referred to themselves as being of 'The Way' (Koine Greek: _ _, romanized: tês hodoû), an expression possibly coming from Isaiah 40:3, "prepare the way of the Lord". According to Acts 11:26, the term "Christian" (_, Khristianós), meaning "followers of Christ" and referring to Jesus' disciples, was first used in the city of Antioch by the non-Jewish inhabitants there. The earliest recorded use of the term "Christianity/Christianism" (_, Khristianismós) was by Ignatius of Antioch around 100 AD. The name Jesus comes from Ancient Greek: _ Iesous, probably from Hebrew/Aramaic: _ Yesua'.</English>
	</TEXT>



	<!-- custom: from https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Islam and adjusted or not for AdvCiv-SAS anyways etc -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_RELIGION_ISLAM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Islam is an Abrahamic monotheistic religion based on the Quran, and the teachings of Muhammad. Adherents of Islam are called Muslims, who are estimated to number 1.9 billion worldwide and are the world's second-largest religious population after Christians.[PARAGRAPH:1]Muslims believe that Islam is the complete and universal version of a primordial faith that was revealed many times through earlier prophets and messengers, including Adam, Noah, Abraham, Moses, and Jesus. Muslims consider the Quran to be the verbatim word of God and the unaltered, final revelation. Alongside the Quran, Muslims also believe in previous revelations, such as the Tawrat (the Torah), the Zabur (Psalms), and the Injil (Gospel). They believe that Muhammad is the main and final of God's prophets, through whom the religion was completed. The teachings and normative examples of Muhammad, called the Sunnah, documented in accounts called the hadith, provide a constitutional model for Muslims. Islam is based on the belief in the oneness and uniqueness of God (tawhid), and belief in an afterlife (akhirah) with the Last Judgment-wherein the righteous will be rewarded in paradise (jannah) and the unrighteous will be punished in hell (jahannam). The Five Pillars, considered obligatory acts of worship, are the Islamic oath and creed (shahada), daily prayers (salah), almsgiving (zakat), fasting (sawm) in the month of Ramadan, and a pilgrimage (hajj) to Mecca. Islamic law, sharia, touches on virtually every aspect of life, from banking and finance and welfare to men's and women's roles and the environment. The two main religious festivals are Eid al-Fitr and Eid al-Adha. The three holiest sites in Islam are Masjid al-Haram in Mecca, Prophet's Mosque in Medina, and al-Aqsa Mosque in Jerusalem.[PARAGRAPH:1]The religion of Islam originated in Mecca in 610 CE. Muslims believe this is when Muhammad received his first revelation. By the time of his death, most of the Arabian Peninsula had converted to Islam. Muslim rule expanded outside Arabia under the Rashidun Caliphate and the subsequent Umayyad Caliphate ruled from the Iberian Peninsula to the Indus Valley. In the Islamic Golden Age, specifically during the reign of the Abbasid Caliphate, most of the Muslim world experienced a scientific, economic and cultural flourishing. The expansion of the Muslim world involved various states and caliphates as well as extensive trade and religious conversion as a result of Islamic missionary activities (dawah), as well as through conquests, imperialism, and colonialism.[PARAGRAPH:1]The two main Islamic branches are Sunni Islam (87-90%) and Shia Islam (10-13%). While the Shia-Sunni divide initially arose from disagreements over the succession to Muhammad, they grew to cover a broader dimension, both theologically and juridically. The Sunni canonical hadith collection consists of six books, while the Shia canonical hadith collection consists of four books. Muslims make up a majority of the population in 49 countries. Approximately 12% of the world's Muslims live in Indonesia, the most populous Muslim-majority country; 31% live in South Asia; 20% live in the Middle East-North Africa; and 15% live in sub-Saharan Africa. Muslim communities are also present in the Americas, China, and Europe. Muslims are the world's fastest-growing major religious group, according to Pew Research. This is primarily due to a higher fertility rate and younger age structure compared to other major religions.[PARAGRAPH:2]In Arabic, Islam (Arabic: _, lit. 'submission [to God]') is the verbal noun of Form IV originating from the verb _ (salama), from the triliteral root _-_-_ (S-L-M), which forms a large class of words mostly relating to concepts of submission, safeness, and peace. In a religious context, it refers to the total surrender to the will of God. A Muslim (_), the word for a follower of Islam, is the active participle of the same verb form, and means "submitter (to God)" or "one who surrenders (to God)". However, Quranic studies scholar Mohsen Goudarzi has argued that in the Quran the word din means "worship", the islam means "monotheism" and the muslim means "monotheist". In the Hadith of Gabriel, Islam is presented as one part of a triad that also includes iman (faith), and ihsan (excellence).[PARAGRAPH:1]Islam itself was historically called Mohammedanism in the English-speaking world. This term has fallen out of use and is sometimes said to be offensive, as it suggests that a human being, rather than God, is central to Muslims' religion.</English>
	</TEXT>



	<!-- custom: from https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prehistoric_religion and adjusted or not for AdvCiv-SAS anyways etc -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIVIC_PREHISTORIC_RELIGION_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The question of when religion emerged in the evolving psyche has sparked the curiosity of paleontologists for decades. On the whole, neither the archaeological record nor the current understanding of how human intelligence evolved suggests early hominins had the cognitive capacity for spiritual belief. Religion was certainly present during the Upper Paleolithic period, dating to about 50,000 through 12,000 years ago, while religion in the Lower and Middle Paleolithic "belongs to the realm of legend".[PARAGRAPH:2]In early research, Australopithecus, the first hominins to emerge in the fossil record, were thought to have sophisticated hunting patterns. These hunting patterns were extrapolated from those of modern hunter-gatherers, and in turn anthropologists and archaeologists pattern-matched Australopithecus and peers to the complex ritual surrounding such hunts. These assumptions were later disproved, and evidence suggesting Australopithecus and peers were capable of using tools such as fire was deemed coincidental. For several decades, prehistoricist consensus has opposed the idea of an Australopithecus faith. The first evidence of ritual emerges in the hominin genus Homo, which emerged between 2-3 million years ago and includes modern humans, their ancestors and closest relatives.[PARAGRAPH:2]The exact question of when ritual shaded into religious faith evades simple answer. The Lower and Middle Paleolithic periods, dominated by early Homo hominins, were an extraordinarily long period (from the emergence of Homo until 50,000 years before the present) of apparent cultural stability. No serious evidence for religious practice exists amongst Homo habilis, the first hominin to use tools. The picture complicates as Homo erectus emerges. H. erectus was the point where hominins seem to have developed an appreciation for ritual, the intellectual ability to stem aggression of the kind seen in modern chimpanzees, and a sense of moral responsibility. Though the emergence of ritual in H. erectus "should not be understood as the full flowering of religious capacity", it marked a qualitative and quantitative change to its forebears. An area of particular scholarly interest is the evidence base for cannibalism and ritual mutilation amongst H. erectus. Skulls found in Java and at the Chinese Zhoukoudian archaeological site bear evidence of tampering with the brain case of the skull in ways thought to correspond to removing the brain for cannibalistic purposes, as observed in hunter-gatherers. Perhaps more tellingly, in those sites and others a number of H. erectus skulls show signs suggesting that the skin and flesh was cut away from the skull in predetermined patterns. These patterns, unlikely to occur by coincidence, are associated in turn with ritual.[PARAGRAPH:2]The lineage leading to anatomically modern humans originated around 500,000 years before the present day. Modern humans are classified taxonomically as Homo sapiens sapiens. This classification is controversial, as it goes against traditional subspecies classifications; no other hominins have been treated as uncontroversial members of H. sapiens. The 2003 description of Homo sapiens idaltu drew attention as a relatively clear case of a H. sapiens subspecies, but was disputed by authors such as Chris Stringer. Neanderthals in particular pose a taxonomic problem. The classification of Neanderthals, a close relative of anatomically modern humans, as Homo neanderthalensis or Homo sapiens neanderthalensis is a decades-long matter of dispute. Neanderthals and H. s. sapiens were able to interbreed, a trait associated with membership in the same species, and around 2% of the modern human genome is composed of Neanderthal DNA. However, strong negative selection existed against the direct offspring of Neanderthals and H. s. sapiens, consistent with the reduced fertility seen in hybrid species such as mules; this has been used as recent argument against the classification of Neanderthals as a H. sapiens subspecies.[PARAGRAPH:2]The study of Neanderthal ritual, as proxy and preface for religion, revolves around death and burial rites. The first undisputed burials, approximately 150,000 years ago, were performed by Neanderthals. The limits of the archaeological record stymie extrapolation from burial to funeral rites, though evidence of grave goods and unusual markings on bones suggest funerary practices. In addition to funerals, a growing evidence base suggests Neanderthals made use of bodily ornamentation through pigments, feathers, and even claws. As such ornamentation is not preserved in the archaeological record, it is understood only by comparison to modern hunter-gatherers, where it often corresponds to rituals of spiritual significance. Unlike H. s. sapiens over equivalent periods, Neanderthal society as preserved in the archaeological record is one of remarkable stability, with little change in tool design over hundreds of thousands of years; Neanderthal cognition, as backfilled from genetic and skeletal evidence, is thought rigid and simplistic compared to that of contemporary, let alone modern, H. s. sapiens. By extension, Neanderthal ritual is speculated to have been a teaching mechanism that resulted in an unchanging culture, by embedding a learning style where orthopraxy dominated in thought, life, and culture. This is contrasted with prehistoric H. s. sapiens religious ritual, which is understood as an extension of art, culture, and intellectual curiosity.[PARAGRAPH:2]Archaeologists such as Brian Hayden interpret Neanderthal burial as suggestive of both belief in an afterlife and of ancestor worship. Hayden also interprets Neanderthals as engaging in bear worship, a hypothesis driven by the common finding of cave bear remains around Neanderthal habitats and by the frequency of such worship amongst cold-dwelling hunter-gatherer societies. Cave excavations throughout the twentieth century found copious bear remains in and around Neanderthal habitats, including stacked skulls, bear bones around human graves, and patterns of skeletal remains consistent with animal skin displays. Other archaeologists, such as Ina Wunn, find the evidence for the "bear cult" unconvincing. Wunn interprets Neanderthals as a pre-religious people, and the presence of bear remains around Neanderthal habitats as a coincidental association; as cave bears by their nature dwell in caves, their bones should be expected to be found there. The broader archaeological evidence overall suggests that bear worship was not a major factor of Paleolithic religion.[PARAGRAPH:2]In recent years, genetic and neurological research has expanded the study of the emergence of religion. In 2018, the cultural anthropologist Margaret Boone Rappaport published her analysis of the sensory, neurological, and genetic differences between the great apes, Neanderthals, H. s. sapiens, and H. s. idaltu. She interprets the H. s. sapiens brain and genome as having a unique capacity for religion through characteristics such as expanded parietal lobes, greater cognitive flexibility, and an unusually broad capacity for both altruism and aggression. In Rappaport's framework, only H. s. sapiens of the hominins is capable of religion for much the same reason as the tools and artworks of prehistoric H. s. sapiens are finer and more detailed than those of their Neanderthal contemporaries; all are products of a unique cognition.</English>
	</TEXT>



	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_BARBARIAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The term "barbarian" was created by the Greeks; it was originally used to denote any foreigner. Since then it has gained a more negative connotation, and it is commonly applied to civilizations deemed "inferior" to one's own. The Chinese, for instance, thought of all foreign cultures - everybody from the Manchus to the Turks to the Europeans - as barbarians. Rome applied it to the Huns and the Germanic tribes, as well as to the more advanced Gauls.[PARAGRAPH:2]In Civilization IV, the term denotes people that are not part of any organized civilization appearing in the game, but are instead old-style hunter-gatherers who prey on the "weak" civilized world. Though some barbarians may have acquired fairly advanced weaponry - swords and axes, for example - and though they may occasionally capture or even build their own cities, they remain at heart brigandic nomads, destroying everything that comes in their path. Barbarians cannot be bargained with or appeased: they must be destroyed - before they destroy you![PARAGRAPH:2]In AdvCiv-SAS, due to their (originally) later start (in turn number since/until they have their first city), and some other restrictions they originally have as part of Civilization IV and/or base AdvCiv or/and other preexisting mods, they are given some boosts to help them catch up a bit faster this delay and compensate even if a bit the penalties they have. Please see the CIVILIZATION_BARBARIAN in the XML of CIV4CivilizationInfos.xml for details. These include (may not be accurate or updated with latest XML): a few free buildings, and all military units being allowed now (think of it as mercenaries, bandits, pirates, terrorists, or/and others maybe or not, anyways etc)</English>
	</TEXT>



	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_FORBIDDEN_PALACE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A collection of imperial structures in Beijing, the Forbidden Palace stands as a testament to the Chinese architectural ingenuity and aesthetic. Ornamental gardens, terraces and fountains surround the magnificent structure, which became the capital of China in 1421. It was the residence of 24 emperors of the Ming and Qing Dynasties until the last emperor abdicated in 1911. Although the correct title for the building is the Imperial Palace, it is more widely known as the "Forbidden" Palace because ordinary people were barred from entering its grounds. With a 160-foot moat and walls 30 feet tall, there was little chance that they would get inside unwanted. The Forbidden Palace is enormous; it occupies 170 acres and contains 8,706 rooms. An estimated eight to ten thousand people lived inside the palace to serve the needs of the emperor. Today, the Forbidden Palace is a major tourist attraction, and it is still used as a symbol of Chinese sovereignty.</English>
	</TEXT>



	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_SECURITY_BUREAU_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]As long as there has been espionage, there has been a need for counter-espionage. This is the realm of the Security Bureau. Bureaus like the American FBI or the British MI5 make sure that sensitive intelligence is protected from outside sources. While espionage is an ancient practice, most Security Bureaus are less than one hundred years old. MI5 has only been in existence since 1909, organized originally to fight against German spies before World War I. The FBI began its expansion in the 1930s thanks to J. Edgar Hoover, the Bureau's first director.</English>
	</TEXT>



	<!-- custom: seeing how they are reluctant to call/name Mao Zedong by his real name in code and inconsistently, and insisting he is a "Dictator of China" but also yet somehow if i am not mistaken about this (strange as in inaccurate and weird maybe or not or yes but anyways etc) that  (somehow anyways etc) "Mao died in 1976, beloved by his people", i don't trust much of their bio, and despite not knowing much aobut mao himself (maybe is good opportunity to learn even if just peak a bit but anyways etc and maybe interesting too but anyways etc...), i'd rather pick a more accurate source (or/and at least a more reliable one or and not or yes or and other or and not anyways etc...), also fixing description and enhancing it while doing so, assuming we don't remove mao later, but even then (if we deprecate him i.e. i mean anyways etc, we could still move him (his code rather not actually him as a person/body but anyways etc anyways etc...)) we could still move him cleanly to a deprecated file or files without the weird naming or/and maybe inaccurate or/and inconcstency or/and other things or/and not or yes or not or and othe ror and not etc anwyys etc..., so hopefully good in all regard, but if not, in all cases etc and gogogo maybe or not or yes or and other or and not but anyways etc anyways etc
	from:
	https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mao_Zedong
	and modified/adjusted or maybe not for AdvCiv-SAS anyways etc...
	-->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_MAO_ZEDONG_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Mao Zedong [\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Chairman of the Chinese Communist Party[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD] 1893-1976[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Mao Zedong (26 December 1893 - 9 September 1976) was a Chinese politician, revolutionary, and political theorist who founded the People's Republic of China (PRC) in 1949 and led the country from its establishment until his death in 1976. Mao served as chairman of the Chinese Communist Party (CCP) from 1943 until his death, and as the party's de facto leader from 1935. His theories, which he advocated as a Chinese adaptation of Marxism-Leninism, are known as Maoism.[PARAGRAPH:1]Born to a peasant family in Shaoshan, Hunan, Mao studied in Changsha and was influenced by the 1911 Revolution and ideas of Chinese nationalism and anti-imperialism. He was introduced to Marxism while working as a librarian at Peking University, and later participated in the May Fourth Movement of 1919. In 1921, Mao became a founding member of the CCP. After the start of the Chinese Civil War between the Kuomintang (KMT) and CCP, Mao led the failed Autumn Harvest Uprising in Hunan in 1927, and in 1931 founded the Jiangxi Soviet. He helped build the Chinese Red Army, and developed a strategy of guerilla warfare. In 1935, Mao became leader of the CCP during the Long March, a military retreat to the Yan'an Soviet in Shaanxi, where the party began rebuilding its forces. The CCP allied with the KMT in the Second United Front at the start of the Second Sino-Japanese War in 1937, but the civil war resumed after Japan's surrender in 1945. In 1949, Mao's forces defeated the Nationalist government, which withdrew to Taiwan.[PARAGRAPH:1]On 1 October 1949, Mao proclaimed the foundation of the PRC, a one-party state controlled by the CCP. He initiated land redistribution and industrialisation campaigns, suppressed political opponents, intervened in the Korean War, and oversaw the ideological Hundred Flowers and Anti-Rightist Campaigns. From 1958 to 1962, Mao oversaw the Great Leap Forward, a campaign which aimed to rapidly collectivise agriculture and industrialise the country. It failed, and resulted in the Great Chinese Famine. In 1966, Mao launched the Cultural Revolution, which was marked by violent class struggle, destruction of historical artifacts, and Mao's cult of personality. From the late 1950s, Mao's foreign policy was dominated by a political split with the Soviet Union, and in the 1970s he began establishing relations with the United States. In 1976, Mao died of a heart attack. He was initially succeeded by Hua Guofeng, then in 1978 by Deng Xiaoping. The CCP's official evaluation of Mao's legacy both praises him and acknowledges mistakes in his later years.[PARAGRAPH:1]Mao's policies resulted in a vast number of deaths, with tens of millions of victims of famine, political persecution, prison labour and executions, and his regime has been described as totalitarian. Mao has also been credited with transforming China from a semi-colony to a major world power and advancing literacy, women's rights, basic healthcare, education, and life expectancy. In modern China, he is widely regarded as a national hero who liberated the country from imperialism. He became an ideological leader within the international communist movement, inspiring various Maoist organisations.[PARAGRAPH:1]English romanisation of name: During Mao's lifetime, the English-language media universally rendered his name as Mao Tse-tung, using the Wade-Giles system of transliteration though with the circumflex accent in the syllable Tsê dropped. Due to its recognizability, the spelling was used widely, even by the PRC's foreign ministry after Hanyu Pinyin became the PRC's official romanisation system for Mandarin Chinese in 1958; the well-known booklet of Mao's political statements was officially entitled Quotations from Chairman Mao Tse-tung in English translations. While the pinyin-derived spelling Mao Zedong is increasingly common, the Wade-Giles-derived spelling Mao Tse-tung continues to be used in modern publications to some extent.</English>
	</TEXT>



	<!-- custom: add Ogiso Igodo, leader of the Kingdom Of Benin, copy pasted from:
	C:\Program Files (x86)\Steam\steamapps\common\Sid Meier's Civilization IV Beyond the Sword\Beyond the Sword\Assets\XML\Text\CIV4GameText_Civilopedia_BTS.xml then modified to fit this leader
	Mention of Ogiso Igodo also here:
	https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ogiso_monarchy#Origin_and_establishment
	Here too (found link on the page linked just above)
	https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Igodo
	some info here too:
	https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Igodomigodo
	note:putting everything in English in all languages is so much more convenient
	and faster, maybe not best and ideal but many paragraphs and such even with
	translator, i hope i can invest my efforts elsewhere.
	I don't mind translating it once in English though is quite cool and
	interesting, but many times is a chore, i also think (and hope) that lost
	players	would play in English, else maybe they would not mind too much about
	this, but is bit too long to do, as in tedious, not lengthy, not impossible
	to do but i hope i can code other things
	-->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_OGISO_IGODO_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Ogiso Igodo[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of The Kingdom of Benin[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] c.900s AD[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Igodo (Obagodo) was the first King of Igodomigodo (Which would then become the Kingdom Of Benin, and much later modern Nigeria (historically unrelated to modern Benin (see the pedia page of Kingdom of Benin for details))).[PARAGRAPH:1]According to Ife and early Benin tradition, he was one of the sons of Oduduwa who dispersed from Ife to found various kingdoms. Some Edo traditions say Igodo descended from heaven, others claim he came from the sky due to his great wisdom, hence his title Ogiso, meaning "King from the sky".[PARAGRAPH:1]During his reign, he organized the kingdom's administration, introduced new political structures, and reinforced the connection between Igodomigodo and the broader Yoruba civilization. There are also stories that describe the Ogiso traveling to Ife for festivals, further strengthening the ties between the two regions.[PARAGRAPH:1]His leadership laid the foundation for the later transformation of Igodomigodo into the Benin Kingdom, which grew into one of the most powerful kingdoms in West Africa. Igodo's legacy is preserved in the historical narratives of both the Edo and Yoruba people. His rule signified the early formation of the Benin monarchy, which would later be formally restructured under Eweka I, a direct descendant of Oduduwa, who officially established the Oba of Benin dynasty after Oranmiyan's campaign. The Benin royal family, which traces its lineage to Oduduwa through Oranmiyan, continues to be a major institution in Nigeria today.</English>
	</TEXT>



	<!-- custom: rename "Montezuma" to "Moctezuma II" (more accurate) and fix birth date from "c.1480" to "1466"
	source for the corrections (mentionned)(anyways etc) above: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moctezuma_II
	text otherwise kept same at leats for now if not always or maybe not (too) or maybe yes or not or/and other(s?) or/and not anyways etc anyways etc
	-->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_MOCTEZUMA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Moctezuma II [\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Aztec Emperor [\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD] c.1466 - 1520[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Moctezuma II was Emperor of the Aztec nation from approximately 1502 until its dissolution in 1520. At the start of his reign he was considered a god and was absolute monarch of the entire known world; at the end of his reign he watched a small group of foreigners destroy his empire with ease. [PARAGRAPH:1]Moctezuma II ruled the Aztecs at the height of their power. His empire controlled a large portion of what is now modern Mexico. They had conquered virtually all other people around them, except for a few other nations, which they deliberately left free (so that they would have somebody left to make war against and to use as sacrifices). [PARAGRAPH:1]Though extremely rich and powerful, Moctezuma II's nation shamelessly squandered a great portion of its wealth and might. Much like the Egyptians, the Aztecs built huge monuments to their gods and held ever-increasing numbers of expensive religious festivals in which they slaughtered tens of thousands of prisoners and their own people. Moctezuma II himself lived in great splendor, his clothing made of silver, gold, and brightly-colored feathers. His court was brilliant, though much riddled with corruption and intrigue. [PARAGRAPH:1]In 1519, Hernando Cortes led 600 Spanish adventurers with 20 horses and 10 cannon to the shores of Mexico on a mission of exploration. Hearing of the great wealth of the Aztecs, he took his tiny force west, determined to conquer this massive nation of five million. At the start of the march Cortes burned his ships to ensure that his men would not desert him. [PARAGRAPH:1]The natives that first faced Cortes were primitive and divided. They were terrified of the Spanish "demonic" horses and cannon and broke before their accurate musket-fire. Cleverly exploiting their political divisions, Cortes then enlisted the defeated peoples' aid by promising them revenge against the hated Aztecs. [PARAGRAPH:1]Moctezuma II watched Cortes' approach with fear and bewilderment. His religion told him that one day the god Quetzalcoatl would return in the guise of a light-skinned bearded man, and when that day occurred, the Aztecs were to welcome him with open arms. Surely Cortes was Quetzalcoatl, else how could he command an army of demons? On the other hand, Cortes was clearly bent on the conquest of the empire - should Moctezuma II not oppose him? Perhaps the sinful Aztecs needed to be punished! [PARAGRAPH:1]Eventually, at the desperate urging of his advisors, Moctezuma II sent an army into the field against the invaders. But they were unable to offer effective resistance and Cortes' forces quickly overwhelmed them. The invaders then marched into the capital city Tenochtitlan virtually unopposed and took Moctezuma II prisoner. He was eventually killed during an uprising that pushed the invaders out of the city for more than a year. [PARAGRAPH:1]One has to wonder what would have happened if Moctezuma II had shown Cortes' courage and resolve and mobilized his people when the invaders first arrived. Could the Spanish have conquered Mexico against determined and organized resistance? Perhaps, but perhaps the natives would have held on long enough to learn to master the horse and gun - or at least their fear of them. If so, they would have become a formidable foe indeed.</English>
	</TEXT>



	<!-- custom: clean import from:
	C:\Program Files (x86)\Steam\steamapps\common\Sid Meier's Civilization IV Beyond the Sword\Beyond the Sword\Assets\XML\Text\CIV4GameText_Civilopedia_BTS.xml
	And then editing it
	See:
	https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Benin
	As for the leader entry (Ogiso Igodo), and most likely similarly
	to next cases, i would not translate the full version/thing
	in other languages, i have Quillbot though or/and other bots.
	Hopefully the English version in all languages is good enough. -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_KINGDOM_OF_BENIN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Kingdom of Benin, also known as Great Benin or Benin Kingdom was a kingdom within what is now considered southern Nigeria. It has no historical relation to the modern republic of Benin, which was known as Dahomey from the 17th century until 1975. The Kingdom of Benin's capital was Edo, now known as Benin City in Edo State, Nigeria.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Benin Kingdom was one of the oldest and most developed states in the coastal hinterland of West Africa. It grew out of the previous Edo Kingdom of Igodomigodo around the 11th century AD; it was annexed by the British Empire in 1897.[PARAGRAPH:1]In the 15th and 16th centuries, the kingdom reached the height of its prosperity, expanding its territory, trading with European powers, and creating a remarkable artistic legacy in cast bronze, iron, brass, carved ivory, and other materials.[PARAGRAPH:2]Rituals and laws[PARAGRAPH:1]Human sacrifices[PARAGRAPH:1]Humans were sacrificed in an annual ritual in honour of the god of iron, where warriors from Benin City would perform an acrobatic dance while suspended from the trees. The ritual recalled a mythical war against the sky. Sacrifices of a man, a woman, a goat, a cow and a ram were also made to a god called "the king of death". The god, named Ogiuwu, was worshipped at a special altar in the centre of Benin City. There were two separate annual series of rites that honored past Obas. Sacrifices were performed every fifth day. At the end of each series of rites, the current Oba's deceased father was honored with a public festival. During the festival, twelve criminals, chosen from a prison where the worst criminals were held, were sacrificed. By the end of the eighteenth century, three to four people were sacrificed at the mouth of the Benin River annually, to attract European trade, according to one source.[PARAGRAPH:1]Burials[PARAGRAPH:1]The monarchy of Benin was hereditary; the eldest son was to become the new Oba. In order to validate the succession of the kingship, the eldest son had to bury his father and perform elaborate rituals. If the eldest son failed to complete these tasks, he might be disqualified from becoming king.[PARAGRAPH:1]Separation of son and mother[PARAGRAPH:1]After the son was installed as king, his mother - after having been invested with the title of Iyoba - was transferred to a palace just outside Benin City, in a place called Uselu. The mother held a considerable amount of power; she was, however, never allowed to meet her son - who was now a divine ruler - again.[PARAGRAPH:1]Divinity of the Oba[PARAGRAPH:1]In Benin, the Oba was seen as divine. The Oba's divinity and sacredness was the focal point of the kingship. The Oba was shrouded in mystery; he only left his palace on ceremonial occasions. It was previously punishable by death to assert that the Oba performed human acts, such as eating, sleeping, dying or washing. The Oba was also credited with having magical powers. He also controlled a powerful bureaucratic apparatus whose decrees were obeyed to the letter.[PARAGRAPH:2]Architecture[PARAGRAPH:1]Impluvium[PARAGRAPH:1]The Impluvium was used in Benin architecture to store rainwater (see the building entry of the Impluvium in the pedia for details).[PARAGRAPH:1]City walls[PARAGRAPH:1]The Benin City walls have been known to Westerners since around 1500. Around 1500, the Portuguese explorer Duarte Pacheco Pereira, briefly described the walls during his travels. In Pereira's Esmeraldo de Situ Orbis, 1505, we read:[PARAGRAPH:1]"The houses are built of sun-dried bricks covered with palm leaves. Benin, which is 80 leagues long by 40 leagues broad, is always at war with its neighbours from whom it obtains captives, whom we buy at from 12 to 15 brass or copper manillas".[PARAGRAPH:1]Another description given around 1600, one hundred years after Pereira's description, is by the Dutch explorer Dierick Ruiters. Pereira's account of the walls is as follows:[PARAGRAPH:1]"This city is about a league long from gate to gate; it has no wall but is surrounded by a large moat, very wide and deep, which suffices for its defence". For more details, see the entry in the pedia: "The Ancient Walls of Benin" (Wonder).[PARAGRAPH:2]Military[PARAGRAPH:1]Operations[PARAGRAPH:1]Military operations relied on a well trained disciplined force. At the head of the host stood the Oba of Benin. The monarch of the realm served as supreme military commander. Beneath him were subordinate generalissimos, the Ezomo, the Iyase, and others who supervised a Metropolitan Regiment based in the capital, and a Royal Regiment made up of hand-picked warriors that also served as bodyguards. Benin's queen mother, the Iyoba, also retained her own regiment - the "Queen's Own". The Metropolitan and Royal regiments were relatively stable semi-permanent or permanent formations. The Village Regiments provided the bulk of the fighting force and were mobilized as needed, sending contingents of warriors upon the command of the king and his generals. Formations were broken down into sub-units under designated commanders. Foreign observers often commented favorably on Benin's discipline and organization as "better disciplined than any other Guinea nation", contrasting them with the slacker troops from the Gold Coast.[PARAGRAPH:1]Tactics[PARAGRAPH:1]Benin's tactics were well organized, with preliminary plans weighed by the Oba and his sub-commanders. Logistics were organized to support missions from the usual porter forces, water transport via canoe, and requisitioning from localities the army passed through. Movement of troops via canoes was critically important in the lagoons, creeks and rivers of the Niger Delta, a key area of Benin's domination. Tactics in the field seem to have evolved over time. While the head-on clash was well known, documentation from the 18th century shows greater emphasis on avoiding continuous battle lines, and more effort to encircle an enemy (ifianyako).Fortifications were important in the region and numerous military campaigns fought by Benin's soldiers revolved around sieges. Benin's military earthworks are the largest of such structures in the world, and Benin's rivals also built extensively. Barring a successful assault, most sieges were resolved by a strategy of attrition, slowly cutting off and starving out the enemy fortification until it capitulated. On occasion, however, European mercenaries were called on to aid with these sieges. In 1603-04 for example, European cannon helped batter and destroy the gates of a town near present-day Lagos, allowing 10,000 warriors of Benin to enter and conquer it. As payment, the Europeans received items, such as palm oil and bundles of pepper. The example of Benin shows the power of indigenous military systems, but also the role outside influences and new technologies brought to bear. This is a normal pattern among many nations.[PARAGRAPH:2]European contact[PARAGRAPH:1]Portugal[PARAGRAPH:1]The first European travelers to reach Benin were Portuguese explorers under João Afonso de Aveiro in about 1485. A strong mercantile relationship developed, with the Edo trading slaves and tropical products such as ivory, pepper and palm oil for European goods such as manillas and guns. In the early 16th century, the Oba sent an ambassador to Lisbon, and the king of Portugal sent Christian missionaries to Benin City. Some residents of Benin City could still speak a pidgin Portuguese in the late 19th century.[PARAGRAPH:1]England[PARAGRAPH:1]The first English expedition to Benin was in 1553, and significant trading developed between Europe and Benin based on the export of ivory, palm oil, pepper, and later slaves. Visitors in the 16th and 19th centuries brought back to Europe tales of "Great Benin", a fabulous city of noble buildings, ruled over by a powerful king. A fanciful engraving of the settlement was made by a Dutch illustrator (from descriptions alone) and was shown in Olfert Dapper's Naukeurige Beschrijvinge der Afrikaensche Gewesten, published in Amsterdam in 1668.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Netherlands[PARAGRAPH:1]Another Dutch traveler, David van Nyendael, visited Benin in 1699 and also wrote an account of the kingdom. Nyendael's description was published in 1704 as an appendix to Willem Bosman's Nauwkeurige Beschryving van de Guinese Goud-, tand- en Slave-kust. In his description, Nyendael states the following about the character of the Benin people:[PARAGRAPH:1]"The inhabitants of the Benin are in general a kind and polite people, of whom one with kindness might get everything he desires. Whatever might be offered to them out of politeness, will always be doubled in return. However, they want their politeness to be returned with likewise courtesy as well, without the appearance of any disappointment or rudeness, and rightly so. To be sure, trying to take anything from them with force or violence, would be as if one tries to reach out to the Moon and will never be left unreckoned. When it comes to trade, they are very strict and will not suffer the slightest infringement of their customs, not even a iota can be changed. Though, when one is willing to accept these customs, they are very easy-going and will cooperate in every way possible to reach an agreement".[PARAGRAPH:2]Art and cultural trade[PARAGRAPH:1]Scientific analysis of the brass (or "bronze") used to make the famous Benin plaques and other sculptures found that, beginning in the late 15th century, the metal (previously thought to have come from the Netherlands) began to derive from the Rhineland region of Germany. At that time, the brass was exported from Germany in the form of ring-shaped ingots which were used as currency in the trans-Atlantic slave trade (bought from the Portuguese and incorporated by the people in Benin as a metal source in sculpture), and subsequently melted down in Benin to produce Benin Bronzes.[PARAGRAPH:2]Notable figures (main points, details in the leader specific pages of the leaders from this implemented in this game/mod)[PARAGRAPH:1]Queen Idia[PARAGRAPH:1]Queen Idia was the wife of Oba Ozolua, the Oba who reigned in about 1481 AD. She was a famous warrior who received much of the credit for the victories of her son as his political counsel, together with her mystical powers and medicinal knowledge, were viewed as critical elements of Esigie's success on the battlefield. Queen Idia became more popular when an ivory carving of her face was adopted as the symbol of FESTAC in 1977.[PARAGRAPH:1]Emotan[PARAGRAPH:1]Emotan was a trader who sold her wares at the exact point where her statue now stands. She was historically credited with setting up the first primary school in the kingdom and saving the monarchy during one of its lowest moments. She helped the Oba Ewuare in reclaiming the throne from his usurper brother, Oba Uwaifiokun who reigned about 1432 AD.[PARAGRAPH:1]Queen Iden[PARAGRAPH:1]Queen Iden is yet another heroine whose sacrifice helped shape Benin Kingdom. She was the queen during the reign of Oba Ewuape in about 1700 AD. She is known to have volunteered herself as a sacrificial lamb for the welfare of her husband and that of the entire kingdom after she consulted the oracle and was informed that human sacrifice would be needed to appease the gods and restore peace and unity in the kingdom.[PARAGRAPH:1]General Asoro[PARAGRAPH:1]General Asoro the Warrior was the sword bearer to King Ovonramwen (the Oba of Benin) in 1897. He participated in the defence of Benin during the 1897 expedition, engaging the British expeditionary force sent to capture the Oba. A quote uttered by the general that "no other person [should] dare pass this road except the Oba" (So kpon Oba) was later translated to "SAKPONBA", which a well known road in Benin was named after.[PARAGRAPH:1]Chief Obasogie[PARAGRAPH:1]Chief Obasogie was not just an outstanding Benin warrior of old who defended the kingdom against external invasion but also a talented blacksmith and sculptor.</English>
	</TEXT>



	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_KINGDOM_OF_BENIN_DISCIPLINED_CROSSBOWMAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A crossbow is a ranged weapon using an elastic launching device consisting of a bow-like assembly called a prod, mounted horizontally on a main frame called a tiller, which is hand-held in a similar fashion to the stock of a long gun. Crossbows shoot arrow-like projectiles called bolts or quarrels. A person who shoots crossbow is called a crossbowman, an arbalister or an arbalist (after the arbalest, a European crossbow variant used during the 12th century).[PARAGRAPH:1][TAB]On top of the usual info that can be found on the [LINK=UNIT_CROSSBOWMAN]Crossbowman's page[\LINK], military operations in the Kingdom Of Benin relied on a well trained disciplined force. Formations were broken down into sub-units under designated commanders. Foreign observers often commented favorably on Benin's discipline and organization as "better disciplined than any other Guinea nation", contrasting them with the slacker troops from the Gold Coast.[PARAGRAPH:1][TAB]Before the coming of the gun, guilds of blacksmiths were charged with war production-particularly swords and iron spearheads. In addition, crossbowmen formed a specialized unit of the Benin army. Archers and crossbowmen were trained in target and field archery.Benin's tactics were well organized, with preliminary plans weighed by the Oba and his sub-commanders. Logistics were organized to support missions from the usual porter forces, water transport via canoe, and requisitioning from localities the army passed through. Movement of troops via canoes was critically important in the lagoons, creeks and rivers of the Niger Delta, a key area of Benin's domination.</English>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
