<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<Civ4GameText>


	<!-- custom: 

	Before starting, a note about translations:

	If we define only the <English>My translation example</Example> tag without
	putting the other language tags, then (according to ChatGPT), the other languages will
	see the English version, no need to copy paste the same version many times, thanks ChatGPT
	etc too maybe anyways.
	Detailed explanations of ChatGPT below (i modified the formatting of it a bit but same content (i may have added Upper cases instead or Change a bit some sentences to connect them, should be mostly the same)).

	1) For new content we add (for example if we were to add a new sniper unit (great memory ChatGPT thanks a lot, anyways, )):
	:
	Quote:
	"
	What happens if you only define an XML entry in English?

	If you only define one language (like English) in your XML (e.g., CIV4GameText.xml), and leave out translations for other languages, then:
	Yes  other languages will see the English version.

	Why?
	Because Civ4's text system falls back to English if:
	- A translation is missing for the current language.
	- The player's selected language is not found in the XML at all.

	So for example:
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SNIPER</Tag>
		<English>Sniper</English>
	</TEXT>

	If the player has their game language set to French, Spanish, or anything else  they'll still see "Sniper" in English, because:
	- The game didnt find <French>, <German>, etc., for that tag.
	- So it shows <English> as a fallback.

	Exceptions / Notes:
	- If the <English> field is missing entirely, the game will show the tag name (like TXT_KEY_UNIT_SNIPER) instead.
	- If you include a <French> tag but leave it empty, it may show nothing or just whitespace  so it's better to leave other languages out entirely unless you have a proper translation.
	"


	2) For content already existing in the game (for example FEATURE_ICE):
	Quoting ChatGPT again, thanks ChatGPT and etc thanks all too or not too etc, anyways:

	Quote:
	"
	This gets into how overrides work in Civ4's XML system. Here's the breakdown:
	You override an existing in-game text key (e.g. TXT_KEY_FEATURE_ICE) in your mod's XML:

	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_FEATURE_ICE</Tag>
		<English>Frozen Hell</English>
	</TEXT>

	But you do not include <French>, <German>, etc.

	What happens in-game?
	Civ4 will completely override the original text entry, even in non-English languages.

	So:
	- English players will see: "Frozen Hell"
	- French players will not see the original Firaxis French translation  theyll see "Frozen Hell" too.
	- Other languages will also see your new English text, not the base game's translation.
	"

	Important Note:
	Once you override a <Tag> in your mod, the original translations are no longer used, even if you only replace <English>.
	That means:
	- You're responsible for translations if you want to preserve them.
	- If not, it's totally fine  Civ4 will fall back to your <English> string in all languages.

	Pro Tip:
	If you're just changing English and want to keep the original translations, you can rename the tag, like:

	<Tag>TXT_KEY_FEATURE_ICE_ALT</Tag>

	Then use TXT_KEY_FEATURE_ICE_ALT wherever you want (e.g. in your modified CIV4FeatureInfos.xml). That way:
	- The original TXT_KEY_FEATURE_ICE stays untouched.
	- You can localize or not as you like.

	Summary:
	What You Do										What Players See
	Only override <English> of a base tag			All languages will see your English string
	Don't touch a tag								Players see base game translations
	Rename the tag									Original untouched; you're free to localize your version
	"
	-->



	<!-- custom: moved the lengthy part of the Sevopedia changes
	to this file, but only for AdvCiv-SAS specific changes (for example
	a new civ, a new leader, etc) that are lengthy.
	Hopefully more readable now, and perhaps exportable if some wish,
	AdvCiv or/and other mods, at least it's cleanly separated -->

	<!-- advc.008: Since the Civilopedia changes are so wordy (not the
     changes, but the copied text), I've moved them out of
     CIV4GameText_advc.xml, where the rest of the Advanced Civ game text
	 is located.
	 Starting with the two text keys changed by K-Mod
	 (one of them commented out, already in K-Mod) cut from
	 Civ4GameText_K-Mod.xml. The comments above those keys
	 are also from K-Mod. -->



	<!-- custom: AdvCiv-SAS specific tags (if i am not mistaken these are tags,
	not in terms of content added but in terms of the type of content, here is
	mostly but not only documentation pages aobut AdvCiv-SAS itself, hopefully
	easier to manage here, anyways) -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_ADVCIV_SAS_CORE_CHANGES_PEDIA_SR</Tag>
		<English>[H1]AdvCiv to AdvCiv-SAS Core Changes[\H1][PARAGRAPH:2]Non-exhaustive list of changes in AdvCiv-SAS as compared to AdvCiv (excluding balance changes, for that please refer to the Sevopedia entries of the items you want to see, for example "Units", "Technologies", or "Traits" to have the latest updated version of their effects.)[PARAGRAPH:1]For more details, in particular about the changes, https://github.com/wonderingabout/AdvCiv-SAS/, in particular the "Quick Start Guide" there (also appended/included as a text .md file in AdvCiv-SAS) [PARAGRAPH:1]If you want to see the full very exhaustive code changes between AdvCiv current latest stable, for example 1.12 here, and AdvCiv-SAS, please visit this pull request compare: https://github.com/wonderingabout/AdvCiv-SAS/pull/13 . Be warned though it can be very lengthy, so read rather the quick start guide mentionned above preferably for the shorter and less exhaustive version if you'd prefer.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][BOLD]Translations[\BOLD][NEWLINE]- For the new content or modified one in this mod (AdvCiv-SAS), only English translations are provided. Even if your game is in another language, you will still see some text, but in English. For modders, see the detailed explanation (code comment), mostly provided by ChatGPT and which was very helpful (to me at least, anyways, ) on how this is implemented at TXT_KEY_ADVCIV_SAS_CORE_CHANGES_PEDIA_SR 's entry in Mods\AdvCiv-SAS\Assets\XML\Text\CIV4GameText_advc_pedia_Lengthy_Custom.xml[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][BOLD]Sevopedia[\BOLD][NEWLINE]- New category in leader page: AI Personality and AI Agregates, gives you AI preferences as well as normalized (in percentages) aggregates of their tendencies, (mostly all by ChatGPT including the doc, i did contribute quite a bit but for most is really just ChatGPT (and me), anyways) see [LINK=LEADER_GANDHI]Gandhi's leader page for example[\LINK] and the specific doc in mod information [LINK=CONCEPT_ADVCIV_SAS_CORE_AI_PERSONALITY_AGGREGATES]4_ADVCIV_SAS_CORE_AI_PERSONALITY_AGGREGATES[\LINK] [NEWLINE][NEWLINE][BOLD]Renaming[\BOLD][NEWLINE]- "We fear you are becoming too advanced" (WFYABTA) has been renamed to "We fear you are trading more than us" (WFYATMTU), as WFYABTA is misleading, and not related at all to your tech progress but to how much you trade if i'm not mistaken, and you can get WFYABTA even if you are lagging behind in tech progress, hopefully clearer now.[NEWLINE]- (Air) interception chance for nukes is now named "Adjusted Air Interception Chance", as it also accounts for Nuke's Air evasion chance if i am not mistaken, see also this for details: https://forums.civfanatics.com/threads/sdi-icbm-and-tactical-nukes.239415/ [NEWLINE]- Renamed [LINK=TERRAIN_SNOW]"Ice" (Terrain) to "Ice Sheet"[\LINK], and [LINK=FEATURE_ICE]"Ice" (Feature) to "Ice Cap"[\LINK], hopefully clearer and more accurate, see their Sevopedia entries for details.[NEWLINE]- Renamed [LINK=BONUS_COW]"Cow" (Ressource) to "Cattle"[\LINK], and renamed [LINK=BONUS_IVORY]"Ivory" (Ressource) to "Elephants"[\LINK], hopefully clearer and more accurate (and immersive maybe), see the Sevopedia entry for details.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][BOLD]Rules[\BOLD][NEWLINE]- All units now are affected by city defenses, even gunpowder and later on units, seems more realistic to me this way, as walls can help against guns and against all (almost?) units, actually even if not having the tech for guns itself[NEWLINE]- Air explore units (for example the [LINK=UNIT_AIRSHIP]Dirigible[\LINK] (old airship)) can move through all terrains, including peaks and water tiles.</English>
	</TEXT>



	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_ADVCIV_SAS_CORE_AI_PERSONALITY_AGGREGATES_PEDIA_SR</Tag>
		<English>[H1]AI Personality Aggregates (AdvCiv-SAS)[\H1]Note: Doc written by ChatGPT (and full AI Aggregates code also comes from ChatGPT, i only implemented it (copy paste) after prompting it (and did the table and such in python with ChatGPT's help but anyways)). As for an example to see it, see [LINK=LEADER_GANDHI]Gandhi's leader page for example[\LINK].[PARAGRAPH:2]AI Personality Aggregates are a unique feature of AdvCiv-SAS that provide insight into how each leader behaves, beyond visible traits like Aggressive or Creative. They are based on hidden AI values found in CIV4LeaderHeadInfos.xml, such as MaxWarRand, BuildUnitProb, PeaceWeight, and many others. These values are normally invisible during gameplay but strongly influence how each AI leader acts in diplomacy, war, trade, and empire management.[PARAGRAPH:1]Aggregates are computed by combining multiple of these hidden values into a single number between 0-100. This number is normalized relative to all other leaders using a min-max formula. For example, if the lowest value among all leaders is 10 and the highest is 50, then a leader with 30 would score 50 on the normalized scale. The point is to allow you to compare leaders easily on a single axis like "Aggressiveness" or "Builder Tendency".[PARAGRAPH:1]Each behavior group - called an aggregate - consists of a name, a score (0-100), and a visual scale made of symbols such as ### or #####. All aggregates use the same symbol format (#) for readability. The score reflects how strongly a leader expresses the associated behavior, after normalizing relevant AI attributes. In most cases, a higher score means the leader behaves more intensely in that area. However, some attributes are inversed before aggregation, such as when a lower value leads to stronger behavior (e.g. lower WonderConstructRand means more likely to build wonders). These inversions are handled automatically in the calculation. The result is a clean, intuitive display where higher scores always mean more of the defined behavior.[PARAGRAPH:1]Let us walk through one example. The "Sneaky" trait is calculated using three XML values: getDemandRebukedSneakProb, getEspionageWeight, and getDogpileWarRand. For each of these, the AI has a number in the XML - for instance, getEspionageWeight might be 40. We collect the values for all leaders, then normalize the selected leader's value to a number between 0-100. If one of the XML values is inverted (meaning a lower number makes the AI more inclined to do something, like lower WonderConstructRand means more wonder-building), then the normalization is reversed for that value before averaging.[PARAGRAPH:1]Then we average the three normalized values, and the result is the final aggregate score. So if a leader has a sneak prob of 80/100, espionage of 60/100, and dogpile tendency of 40/100, the result would be 60/100 on "Sneaky". That is what gets displayed in the AI Personality panel.[PARAGRAPH:1]These aggregates are shown on the right side of the Sevopedia Leader page. Each entry shows the name of the trait, the computed score, and the visual scale. The traits are grouped into categories like War Strategy, Diplomacy, Economic Preferences, Victory Strategy, Attitude Modifiers, Trade Thresholds, and Aggregates.[PARAGRAPH:1]Aggregates are new, and they are not part of standard Civilization IV or AdvCiv. They were designed fully by ChatGPT, including the Python logic and the display strategy. All the math is done using Python inside SevoPediaLeader.py, and the values are pulled live from the XML data already defined by the game. That means they work for all existing leaders and any custom leaders you add - as long as those leaders have AI values, the system will work for them too.[PARAGRAPH:1]As a modder or player, you can use this information to understand the AI better. If an AI has high "Stubborn", you know that even at Friendly they may refuse your deals. If another has high "Dogpiler", be careful when you are weak in a war - they might declare on you opportunistically. Traits like "Builder", "Flexible", or "Tech Hoarder" give you clues about their priorities.[PARAGRAPH:1]This system does not override anything in the game - it simply makes visible what was already there but hidden. It helps with both immersion and gameplay understanding. The traits are not made up: they are just summaries of existing AI behavior, now available in a readable form.[PARAGRAPH:1]You can edit the behavior formulas directly in Python. Every trait is defined as a list of XML getters, each with an optional inverse flag. Modders can create new traits or adjust the weighting as they see fit. The layout is customizable too, but even without edits, the system is plug-and-play.[PARAGRAPH:1]In conclusion, AI Personality Aggregates are a powerful addition for any player or modder who wants to understand the AI beyond simple trait labels. They show you how an AI is wired, what it values, and how it is likely to behave in a variety of situations. For learning, planning, diplomacy, or modding - they are an invaluable tool.[PARAGRAPH:2]The aggregates listed below are organized by their underlying behavior themes. While the in-game display does not explicitly group them into categories (to conserve space), they are logically grouped in the code and in this documentation for clarity. Each entry includes a definition, the XML values used to compute it, an explanation of how the score is derived, and what it means for gameplay and strategy. This information can help players understand not only how an AI might behave in isolation, but also how its behaviors interact with others on the map.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][H1]Combat and Military Behavior[\H1]- Aggressive: Reflects a leader's general willingness to wage war. High values mean frequent war declarations, stronger offensive priorities, and a tendency to build more military units. Computed using getMaxWarRand, getBuildUnitProb, and getBaseAttackOddsChange. Higher scores indicate a more aggressive leader that poses military threats throughout the game.[NEWLINE]- Dogpiler: Measures how likely a leader is to join existing wars against weakened players. Includes getDogpileWarRand, getDeclareWarTradeRand, and getWarmongerRespect. High values signal a tendency to opportunistically jump into wars, which means players weakened by ongoing wars should be wary of this AI.[NEWLINE]- Reckless: Captures how risky and unpredictable a leader is in war-related decisions. Based on getBaseAttackOddsChange, getLimitedWarRand, and getDeclareWarRefuseAttitudeThreshold (inverted). High values mean the AI may take risky battles, start wars with low justification, and disregard diplomatic warnings.[NEWLINE]- Allied Warmonger: Represents AIs who combine strong military behavior with collaborative war efforts. Uses getWarmongerRespect, getShareWarAttitudeChangeLimit, and getDogpileWarRand. These AIs will team up in wars and are more dangerous in multiplayer AI team-ups.[NEWLINE]- Border Watcher: Focuses on leaders that are sensitive to nearby borders and land ownership. Uses getMaxWarMinAdjacentLandPercent, getCloseBordersAttitudeChange, and getMaxWarNearbyPowerRatio. High scores mean the AI dislikes neighbors and may act to protect or expand its borders aggressively.[NEWLINE]- Power Tracker: Tracks how much the AI pays attention to power ratios before engaging in war. Computed with getMaxWarNearbyPowerRatio, getMaxWarDistantPowerRatio, and getLimitedWarPowerRatio. A high score indicates a calculated war planner that only strikes when strong.[NEWLINE][H1]Diplomatic Behavior[\H1]- Diplomatic: A measure of peaceful, cooperation-prone behavior. Built from getBasePeaceWeight, getNoTechTradeThreshold (inverted), and getOpenBordersRefuseAttitudeThreshold (inverted). High scores mean more open borders, tech trades, and diplomacy.[NEWLINE]- Isolationist: Opposite of Diplomatic. Uses getOpenBordersRefuseAttitudeThreshold, getDeclareWarRefuseAttitudeThreshold, and getStopTradingRefuseAttitudeThreshold. High values mean this leader avoids interaction, is hard to befriend, and rarely opens up diplomatically.[NEWLINE]- Stubborn: Reflects general refusal behavior, especially in diplomacy and trade. Includes getTechRefuseAttitudeThreshold, getCityRefuseAttitudeThreshold, getStopTradingRefuseAttitudeThreshold, getAdoptCivicRefuseAttitudeThreshold, and getConvertReligionRefuseAttitudeThreshold. These AIs are hard to deal with even at Friendly attitudes.[NEWLINE]- Dealbreaker: A more focused variant of "Stubborn,"" covering deal-breaking behaviors. Uses getRefuseToTalkWarThreshold, getTechRefuseAttitudeThreshold, and getStopTradingRefuseAttitudeThreshold. High values mean the AI often refuses negotiations, even when a player expects cooperation.[NEWLINE]- Grudgy: Captures long memory for slights and border tension. Based on getWorseRankDifferenceAttitudeChange, getCloseBordersAttitudeChange, and getDifferentReligionAttitudeChangeLimit. High scores indicate that once annoyed, the leader will stay that way and hold grudges.[NEWLINE]- Collaborative: Measures openness to cooperative diplomatic modifiers. Computed from getShareWarAttitudeChangeLimit, getSameReligionAttitudeChangeLimit, and getFavoriteCivicAttitudeChangeLimit. High scores mean the leader rewards alignment in civics, religions, and shared enemies.[NEWLINE][H1]Economic and Strategic Planning[\H1]- Builder: Measures inclination toward peaceful infrastructure. Based on getWonderConstructRand (inverted), getBuildUnitProb (inverted), and getMaxGoldTradePercent. High values indicate leaders that focus on wonders, economy, and long-term growth.[NEWLINE]- Trader: Focuses on openness to trade and mutual benefit. Uses getTechTradeKnownPercent, getMaxGoldTradePercent, and getMapRefuseAttitudeThreshold (inverted). These leaders frequently trade maps, techs, and gold with others.[NEWLINE]- Gold Hoarder: Tracks leaders who collect and guard gold. Includes getMaxGoldTradePercent, getMaxGoldPerTurnTradePercent, and getCityRefuseAttitudeThreshold. High values mean they build a strong treasury but don't like to share it.[NEWLINE]- Tech Hoarder: Measures reluctance to share technology. Based on getNoTechTradeThreshold, getTechRefuseAttitudeThreshold, and getTechTradeKnownPercent (inverted). High scores mean tech trades are rare and expensive.[NEWLINE]- Micro-manager: Captures small-scale detail preferences. Uses getAttackOddsChangeRand, getMakePeaceRand, and getRefuseToTalkWarThreshold. These AIs make cautious but intricate decisions.[NEWLINE][H1]Behavioral Nuance and Opportunism[\H1]- Sneaky: Represents trickiness and opportunism. Built from getDemandRebukedSneakProb, getDogpileWarRand, and getEspionageWeight. Leaders with high scores are more likely to backstab or conduct covert ops.[NEWLINE]- Opportunistic: Tracks general opportunism in trade and war. Computed from getDeclareWarTradeRand, getTechTradeKnownPercent, and getWarmongerRespect. Leaders with high scores adjust rapidly to power shifts and tech advantages.[NEWLINE]- Flexible: Indicates diplomatic and civic adaptability. Uses getAdoptCivicRefuseAttitudeThreshold (inverted), getConvertReligionRefuseAttitudeThreshold (inverted), and getFavoriteCivicAttitudeChangeLimit (inverted). High scores mean they are more likely to accommodate player demands.[NEWLINE]- Vassalizer: Tracks use of vassal mechanics. Based on getVassalRefuseAttitudeThreshold, getPowerWeightModifier, and getRefuseToTalkWarThreshold (inverted). These AIs seek to dominate and subdue rather than destroy.[NEWLINE]- Culture Pusher: Leaders focused on cultural victories and ideological influence. Computed with getCultureVictoryWeight, getMaxWarMinAdjacentLandPercent (inverted), and getSameReligionAttitudeChangeLimit. High values indicate passive expansion and border pressure.[NEWLINE]- Wonder Chaser: Combines builder logic with prestige focus. Uses getWonderConstructRand (inverted), getBuildUnitProb (inverted), and getBasePeaceWeight. These AIs will prioritize wonders and prestige structures, but may sacrifice military for it.[NEWLINE]- Unpredictable: Captures erratic or random tendencies. Computed with getAttackOddsChangeRand, getLimitedWarRand, and getDeclareWarTradeRand. High scores mean they can surprise players  for better or worse.[PARAGRAPH:2]In addition to aggregated traits, each leader also has individual AI personality attributes. These are hidden XML values that directly control how an AI behaves in war, diplomacy, trade, development, and overall strategy. Each attribute influences one specific behavior. Most values are located in CIV4LeaderHeadInfos.xml. The following list explains each known attribute, how it works, and what it means in terms of gameplay. These values are visible in the AI Personality panel for each leader in Sevopedia.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]- Max War Rand: This value determines how often the AI will consider declaring a full war. A higher value makes the AI less likely to start wars. Lower values indicate a war-prone leader. This is one of the strongest indicators of military aggressiveness.[NEWLINE]- Max War Nearby Power Ratio: This is the power threshold the AI checks before declaring war on a nearby opponent. A lower ratio means the AI is more willing to attack even when the target is strong. A higher ratio means the AI prefers to attack only when it has superior strength.[NEWLINE]- Max War Distant Power Ratio: Similar to the previous attribute, but for distant targets. A high value makes the AI less likely to attack civilizations far away. This controls overseas invasions and distant wars.[NEWLINE]- Max War Min Adjacent Land Percent: This controls whether the AI considers launching a full war based on how much border it shares with a rival. A higher value means the AI needs a large border to consider attacking. A lower value means it is willing to attack with only limited land access.[NEWLINE]- Limited War Rand: Determines how often the AI will consider limited wars (small-scale or opportunistic attacks). Lower values mean the AI will try this more often.[NEWLINE]- Limited War Power Ratio: Similar to the Max War ratio, but for limited wars. A low value makes the AI more likely to attack even if it is weaker.[NEWLINE]- Dogpile War Rand: This determines how likely an AI is to join an existing war against a player or civ who is already under attack. Low values make it more likely to dogpile. AIs with low values here are dangerous during wars where you're already losing.[NEWLINE]- Make Peace Rand: Controls how often the AI will consider making peace. A higher number means peace is less likely. AIs with low numbers here may be more open to ending wars early.[NEWLINE]- Base Attitude: A baseline modifier to the AI's attitude toward other players. This is usually 0, but can be positive or negative. It affects diplomatic relations passively.[NEWLINE]- Peace Weight: Indicates how peaceful the AI is overall. High values mean the AI prefers peace and dislikes warmongers. Low values mean the AI is indifferent to war or may admire aggression. This also influences how it votes in the UN and AP.[NEWLINE]- Warmonger Respect: How much the AI respects or fears warmongers. Higher values mean it will like aggressive leaders more. Low values mean it will dislike or avoid them.[NEWLINE]- Demand Rebuked Sneak Prob: The chance the AI will launch a sneak attack after you refuse a demand. High values mean they may surprise-attack you if you deny them.[NEWLINE]- Demand Rebuked War Prob: Similar to the previous value, but for open war declaration (not sneak attack). Low values mean fewer consequences when denying demands.[NEWLINE]- Refuse to Talk War Threshold: This value controls how long an AI refuses to talk during war. Higher values mean longer periods of isolation. Affects your ability to negotiate peace.[NEWLINE]- No Tech Trade Threshold: Controls how willing the AI is to trade technology. Higher values mean tech hoarding. Lower values mean openness to tech exchange.[NEWLINE]- Tech Trade Known Percent: The minimum percent of civilizations that must know a tech before the AI is willing to trade it. High values mean the AI waits until everyone knows it.[NEWLINE]- Declare War Trade Rand: Determines the AI's willingness to declare war on demand through diplomacy. Lower values mean it's easier to bribe them into attacking others.[NEWLINE]- Espionage Weight: How much focus the AI puts on espionage missions. Higher values mean more spies, sabotage, and counter-intelligence. Affects gameplay especially with espionage-enabled victory conditions or sabotage threats.[NEWLINE]- Build Unit Prob: Probability that the AI will choose to build military units over civilian ones. Higher values mean a stronger military buildup. Affects unit spam and wartime resilience.[NEWLINE]- Base Attack Odds Change: Increases or decreases the AI's estimated odds for attacking. Higher values make them more aggressive. Can lead to reckless combat. Lower values make them more cautious.[NEWLINE]- Attack Odds Change Rand: Adds randomness to the AI's decision to attack. Higher values introduce more variability in combat choices. Can make the AI seem less predictable in battle.[NEWLINE]- Wonder Construct Rand: Affects how likely the AI is to build wonders. Lower values mean more focus on wonder construction. This also affects how competitive the AI is for key buildings like the Great Library or Pyramids.[NEWLINE]- Max Gold Trade Percent: Controls how much gold the AI is willing to trade in a single deal. Higher values mean more generous offers. Affects diplomacy and AI flexibility in trades.[NEWLINE]- Max Gold Per Turn Trade Percent: Same as above, but for GPT (gold per turn) deals. Higher values mean the AI is more willing to commit to long-term trades.[NEWLINE]- Worse Rank Difference Attitude Change: How much the AI's attitude worsens toward civs ranked lower than them. High values indicate arrogance. Leaders with high values may look down on weaker civs.[NEWLINE]- Better Rank Difference Attitude Change: How much the AI dislikes stronger civs. High values indicate envy or fear. These leaders are more suspicious of top players.[NEWLINE]- Close Borders Attitude Change: Penalty applied when borders are too close. Affects peaceful coexistence. Higher values mean the AI dislikes you more for crowding them.[NEWLINE]- Same Religion Attitude Change Limit: Bonus to attitude for sharing religion. Higher values make the AI favor you more if you have the same faith. Useful for diplomacy and alliances.[NEWLINE]- Different Religion Attitude Change Limit: Penalty to attitude when religions differ. Higher values make the AI more intolerant. Can sabotage relations even with friendly leaders.[NEWLINE]- Share War Attitude Change Limit: Bonus to attitude for fighting the same enemy. High values make the AI more appreciative of joint wars. Can lead to long-term allies.[NEWLINE]- Favorite Civic Attitude Change Limit: Bonus to attitude for using their favorite civic. Helps identify what civics to adopt to get in their good graces.[NEWLINE]- Tech Refuse Attitude Threshold: Minimum attitude required for the AI to trade tech. Lower values mean they are more willing to trade even if they dislike you. High values mean they require Friendly or better.[NEWLINE]- City Refuse Attitude Threshold: Same as above, but for city trades. AIs rarely trade cities, but this makes it even harder or easier depending on the number.[NEWLINE]- Strategic Bonus Refuse Attitude Threshold: Minimum attitude required to trade strategic resources (copper, iron, horses). High values mean they are stingy.[NEWLINE]- Health Bonus Refuse Attitude Threshold: Minimum attitude to trade health resources (corn, pigs, etc.).[NEWLINE]- Happiness Bonus Refuse Attitude Threshold: Minimum attitude to trade happiness resources (gems, incense, etc.).[NEWLINE]- Map Refuse Attitude Threshold: Minimum attitude to share maps. Low values mean they are more willing to cooperate with cartography and reveal information.[NEWLINE]- Declare War Refuse Attitude Threshold: Minimum attitude required to agree to declare war on someone. Lower is better if you want to bribe them into war.[NEWLINE]- Declare War Them Refuse Attitude Threshold: Same as above, but for declaring war on someone the AI is currently trading with or has special relations with.[NEWLINE]- Stop Trading Refuse Attitude Threshold: Minimum attitude required to ask the AI to stop trading with a third party. Higher values mean more loyalty to existing partners.[NEWLINE]- Stop Trading Them Refuse Attitude Threshold: Variant of the previous value. Affects refusal when the AI likes the third party.[NEWLINE]- Adopt Civic Refuse Attitude Threshold: Minimum attitude required to ask the AI to switch to your preferred civic. High values mean they rarely switch. Affects diplomatic civics requests.[NEWLINE]- Convert Religion Refuse Attitude Threshold: Same as above but for religion. AIs with high values here are religiously stubborn.[NEWLINE]- Open Borders Refuse Attitude Threshold: Minimum attitude to accept an open borders agreement. High values mean isolationist leaders who refuse trade routes or passage.[NEWLINE]- Vassal Refuse Attitude Threshold: Minimum attitude needed to accept vassalage. Affects capitulation and voluntary vassal offers. High values make diplomacy harder.[NEWLINE]- Power Weight Modifier: A rarely used but powerful modifier that increases or decreases how much military power affects AI evaluations. Higher values make the AI more responsive to power ratios (yours or theirs).[PARAGRAPH:2]In addition to the core AI personality attributes listed above, leaders in Civilization IV also possess a wide array of secondary behavioral modifiers defined in CIV4LeaderHeadInfos.xml. These values do not appear in the AI Personality panel but still influence AI behavior behind the scenes. They include diplomatic contact probabilities, memory-based attitude changes, war aversion levels, unit and improvement preferences, and flavor weights for strategic tendencies. For example, ContactRands like CONTACT_TRADE_TECH or CONTACT_DEMAND_TRIBUTE determine how frequently an AI initiates certain diplomatic actions. MemoryAttitudePercents control how long an AI remembers events like tech trades or betrayals. NoWarAttitudeProbs adjust the AI's likelihood of refusing to declare war based on its attitude (e.g. Cautious or Pleased). UnitAIWeightModifiers and ImprovementWeightModifiers affect the AI's preference for assigning units to roles like UNITAI_RESERVE or building specific improvements like farms. Finally, Flavor values influence strategic priorities such as military, culture, or religion, and shape the AI's behavior in broader gameplay contexts. While these attributes are not visualized in-game, they play a vital role in shaping AI depth and realism. Modders may wish to inspect and adjust these fields to fine-tune personality profiles beyond the visible attributes. A future section may document these values in more detail, including practical examples and modding guidance.[NEWLINE]</English>
	</TEXT>



	<!-- custom: more accurate and detailed entry, less western-centric -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CROSSBOWMAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A crossbow is a ranged weapon using an elastic launching device consisting of a bow-like assembly called a prod, mounted horizontally on a main frame called a tiller, which is hand-held in a similar fashion to the stock of a long gun. Crossbows shoot arrow-like projectiles called bolts or quarrels. A person who shoots crossbow is called a crossbowman, an arbalister or an arbalist (after the arbalest, a European crossbow variant used during the 12th century).[PARAGRAPH:1][TAB]Crossbows and bows use the same elastic launch principles, but differ in that an archer using a bow must draw-and-shoot in a quick and smooth motion with limited or no time for aiming, while a crossbow's design allows it to be spanned and cocked ready for use at a later time and thus affording them unlimited time to aim. When shooting bows, the archer must fully perform the draw, holding the string and arrow using various techniques while pulling it back with arm and back muscles, and then either immediately shooting instinctively without a period of aiming, or holding that form while aiming. Both demand some physical strength to do so using bows suitable for warfare, though this is easier using lighter draw-weight hunting bows. As such, their accurate and sustained use in warfare takes much practice.[PARAGRAPH:1][TAB]Crossbows avoid these potential problems by having trigger-released cocking mechanisms to maintain the tension on the string once it has been spanned - drawn - into its ready-to-shoot position, allowing these weapons to be carried cocked and ready and affording their users time to aim them. This also allows them to be readied by someone assisting their users, so multiple crossbows can be used one after the other while others reload and ready them. Crossbows are spanned into their cocked positions using a number of techniques and devices, some of which are mechanical and employ gear and pulley arrangements - levers, belt hooks, pulleys, windlasses and cranequins - to overcome very high draw weight. These potentially achieve better precision and enable their effective use by less familiarised and trained personnel, whereas the simple and composite warbows of, for example, the English and the steppe nomads require years of training, practice and familiarisation.[PARAGRAPH:1][TAB]These advantages for the crossbow are somewhat offset by the longer time needed to reload a crossbow for further shots, with the crossbows with high draw weights requiring sophisticated systems of gears and pulleys to overcome their huge draw weights that are very slow and rather awkward to employ on the battlefield. Medieval crossbows were also very inefficient, with short shot stroke lengths from the string lock to the release point of their bolts, along with the slower speeds of their steel prods and heavy strings, despite their massive draw weights compared to bows, though modern materials and crossbow designs overcome these shortcomings.[PARAGRAPH:1][TAB]The earliest known crossbows were invented in ancient China in the first millennium BC and brought about a major shift in the role of projectile weaponry in wars, especially during Qin's unification wars and later the Han campaigns (206 BC - 220 AD) against northern nomads and western states. The medieval European crossbow was called by many names, including "crossbow" itself; most of these names derived from the word ballista, an ancient Greek torsion siege engine similar in appearance but different in design principle.[[PARAGRAPH:1][TAB]In modern times, firearms have largely supplanted bows and crossbows as weapons of war, but crossbows remain widely used for competitive shooting sports and hunting, and for relatively silent shooting.</English>
	</TEXT>


	<!-- custom: based on the disciplined crossbow (kingdom of benin)'s entry (to match the format of this other civ unit (than the chinese civ unit)) and adjusted from there to fit the Chinese civ unit. -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CHINA_CHOKONU_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A crossbow is a ranged weapon using an elastic launching device consisting of a bow-like assembly called a prod, mounted horizontally on a main frame called a tiller, which is hand-held in a similar fashion to the stock of a long gun. Crossbows shoot arrow-like projectiles called bolts or quarrels. A person who shoots crossbow is called a crossbowman, an arbalister or an arbalist (after the arbalest, a European crossbow variant used during the 12th century).[PARAGRAPH:1][TAB]On top of the usual info that can be found on the [LINK=UNIT_CROSSBOWMAN]Crossbowman's page[\LINK], the repeating crossbow, also known as the repeater crossbow, and the Zhuge crossbow, also romanized Chu-ko-nu, due to its association with the Three Kingdoms-era strategist Zhuge Liang (181-234 AD), is a crossbow invented during the Warring States period in China that combined the bow spanning, bolt placing, and shooting actions into one motion.[PARAGRAPH:1][TAB]The earliest archaeological evidence of the repeating crossbow is found in the state of Chu, but it uses a pistol grip that is different from the later and more commonly known Ming dynasty (1368-1644) design.[PARAGRAPH:1][TAB]Although the repeating crossbow was in use throughout most of Chinese history until the late Qing dynasty (1644-1911), it was generally regarded as a non-military weapon suited for women, defending households against robbers.</English>
	</TEXT>


	<!-- custom: add Ogiso Igodo, leader of the Kingdom Of Benin, copy pasted from:
	C:\Program Files (x86)\Steam\steamapps\common\Sid Meier's Civilization IV Beyond the Sword\Beyond the Sword\Assets\XML\Text\CIV4GameText_Civilopedia_BTS.xml then modified to fit this leader
	Mention of Ogiso Igodo also here:
	https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ogiso_monarchy#Origin_and_establishment
	Here too (found link on the page linked just above)
	https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Igodo
	some info here too:
	https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Igodomigodo
	note:putting everything in English in all languages is so much more convenient
	and faster, maybe not best and ideal but many paragraphs and such even with
	translator, i hope i can invest my efforts elsewhere.
	I don't mind translating it once in English though is quite cool and
	interesting, but many times is a chore, i also think (and hope) that lost
	players	would play in English, else maybe they would not mind too much about
	this, but is bit too long to do, as in tedious, not lengthy, not impossible
	to do but i hope i can code other things
	-->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_OGISO_IGODO_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Ogiso Igodo[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of The Kingdom of Benin[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] c.900s AD[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Igodo (Obagodo) was the first King of Igodomigodo (Which would then become the Kingdom Of Benin, and much later modern Nigeria (historically unrelated to modern Benin (see the pedia page of Kingdom of Benin for details))).[PARAGRAPH:1]According to Ife and early Benin tradition, he was one of the sons of Oduduwa who dispersed from Ife to found various kingdoms. Some Edo traditions say Igodo descended from heaven, others claim he came from the sky due to his great wisdom, hence his title Ogiso, meaning "King from the sky".[PARAGRAPH:1]During his reign, he organized the kingdom's administration, introduced new political structures, and reinforced the connection between Igodomigodo and the broader Yoruba civilization. There are also stories that describe the Ogiso traveling to Ife for festivals, further strengthening the ties between the two regions.[PARAGRAPH:1]His leadership laid the foundation for the later transformation of Igodomigodo into the Benin Kingdom, which grew into one of the most powerful kingdoms in West Africa. Igodo's legacy is preserved in the historical narratives of both the Edo and Yoruba people. His rule signified the early formation of the Benin monarchy, which would later be formally restructured under Eweka I, a direct descendant of Oduduwa, who officially established the Oba of Benin dynasty after Oranmiyan's campaign. The Benin royal family, which traces its lineage to Oduduwa through Oranmiyan, continues to be a major institution in Nigeria today..</English>
	</TEXT>
	

	<!-- custom: clean import from:
	C:\Program Files (x86)\Steam\steamapps\common\Sid Meier's Civilization IV Beyond the Sword\Beyond the Sword\Assets\XML\Text\CIV4GameText_Civilopedia_BTS.xml
	And then editing it
	See:
	https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Benin
	As for the leader entry (Ogiso Igodo), and most likely similarly
	to next cases, i would not translate the full version/thing
	in other languages, i have Quillbot though or/and other bots.
	Hopefully the English version in all languages is good enough. -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_KINGDOM_OF_BENIN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Kingdom of Benin, also known as Great Benin or Benin Kingdom was a kingdom within what is now considered southern Nigeria. It has no historical relation to the modern republic of Benin, which was known as Dahomey from the 17th century until 1975. The Kingdom of Benin's capital was Edo, now known as Benin City in Edo State, Nigeria.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Benin Kingdom was one of the oldest and most developed states in the coastal hinterland of West Africa. It grew out of the previous Edo Kingdom of Igodomigodo around the 11th century AD; it was annexed by the British Empire in 1897.[PARAGRAPH:1]In the 15th and 16th centuries, the kingdom reached the height of its prosperity, expanding its territory, trading with European powers, and creating a remarkable artistic legacy in cast bronze, iron, brass, carved ivory, and other materials.[PARAGRAPH:2]Rituals and laws[PARAGRAPH:1]Human sacrifices[PARAGRAPH:1]Humans were sacrificed in an annual ritual in honour of the god of iron, where warriors from Benin City would perform an acrobatic dance while suspended from the trees. The ritual recalled a mythical war against the sky. Sacrifices of a man, a woman, a goat, a cow and a ram were also made to a god called "the king of death". The god, named Ogiuwu, was worshipped at a special altar in the centre of Benin City. There were two separate annual series of rites that honored past Obas. Sacrifices were performed every fifth day. At the end of each series of rites, the current Oba's deceased father was honored with a public festival. During the festival, twelve criminals, chosen from a prison where the worst criminals were held, were sacrificed. By the end of the eighteenth century, three to four people were sacrificed at the mouth of the Benin River annually, to attract European trade, according to one source.[PARAGRAPH:1]Burials[PARAGRAPH:1]The monarchy of Benin was hereditary; the eldest son was to become the new Oba. In order to validate the succession of the kingship, the eldest son had to bury his father and perform elaborate rituals. If the eldest son failed to complete these tasks, he might be disqualified from becoming king.[PARAGRAPH:1]Separation of son and mother[PARAGRAPH:1]After the son was installed as king, his mother - after having been invested with the title of Iyoba - was transferred to a palace just outside Benin City, in a place called Uselu. The mother held a considerable amount of power; she was, however, never allowed to meet her son - who was now a divine ruler - again.[PARAGRAPH:1]Divinity of the Oba[PARAGRAPH:1]In Benin, the Oba was seen as divine. The Oba's divinity and sacredness was the focal point of the kingship. The Oba was shrouded in mystery; he only left his palace on ceremonial occasions. It was previously punishable by death to assert that the Oba performed human acts, such as eating, sleeping, dying or washing. The Oba was also credited with having magical powers. He also controlled a powerful bureaucratic apparatus whose decrees were obeyed to the letter.[PARAGRAPH:2]Architecture[PARAGRAPH:1]Impluvium[PARAGRAPH:1]The Impluvium was used in Benin architecture to store rainwater (see the building entry of the Impluvium in the pedia for details).[PARAGRAPH:1]City walls[PARAGRAPH:1]The Benin City walls have been known to Westerners since around 1500. Around 1500, the Portuguese explorer Duarte Pacheco Pereira, briefly described the walls during his travels. In Pereira's Esmeraldo de Situ Orbis, 1505, we read:[PARAGRAPH:1]"The houses are built of sun-dried bricks covered with palm leaves. Benin, which is 80 leagues [sic] long by 40 leagues [sic] broad, is always at war with its neighbours from whom it obtains captives, whom we buy at from 12 to 15 brass or copper manillas".[PARAGRAPH:1]Another description given around 1600, one hundred years after Pereira's description, is by the Dutch explorer Dierick Ruiters. Pereira's account of the walls is as follows:[PARAGRAPH:1]"This city is about a league long from gate to gate; it has no wall but is surrounded by a large moat, very wide and deep, which suffices for its defence". For more details, see the entry in the pedia: "The Ancient Walls of Benin" (Wonder).[PARAGRAPH:2]Military[PARAGRAPH:1]Operations[PARAGRAPH:1]Military operations relied on a well trained disciplined force. At the head of the host stood the Oba of Benin. The monarch of the realm served as supreme military commander. Beneath him were subordinate generalissimos, the Ezomo, the Iyase, and others who supervised a Metropolitan Regiment based in the capital, and a Royal Regiment made up of hand-picked warriors that also served as bodyguards. Benin's queen mother, the Iyoba, also retained her own regiment - the "Queen's Own". The Metropolitan and Royal regiments were relatively stable semi-permanent or permanent formations. The Village Regiments provided the bulk of the fighting force and were mobilized as needed, sending contingents of warriors upon the command of the king and his generals. Formations were broken down into sub-units under designated commanders. Foreign observers often commented favorably on Benin's discipline and organization as "better disciplined than any other Guinea nation", contrasting them with the slacker troops from the Gold Coast.[PARAGRAPH:1]Tactics[PARAGRAPH:1]Benin's tactics were well organized, with preliminary plans weighed by the Oba and his sub-commanders. Logistics were organized to support missions from the usual porter forces, water transport via canoe, and requisitioning from localities the army passed through. Movement of troops via canoes was critically important in the lagoons, creeks and rivers of the Niger Delta, a key area of Benin's domination. Tactics in the field seem to have evolved over time. While the head-on clash was well known, documentation from the 18th century shows greater emphasis on avoiding continuous battle lines, and more effort to encircle an enemy (ifianyako).Fortifications were important in the region and numerous military campaigns fought by Benin's soldiers revolved around sieges. Benin's military earthworks are the largest of such structures in the world, and Benin's rivals also built extensively. Barring a successful assault, most sieges were resolved by a strategy of attrition, slowly cutting off and starving out the enemy fortification until it capitulated. On occasion, however, European mercenaries were called on to aid with these sieges. In 1603-04 for example, European cannon helped batter and destroy the gates of a town near present-day Lagos, allowing 10,000 warriors of Benin to enter and conquer it. As payment, the Europeans received items, such as palm oil and bundles of pepper. The example of Benin shows the power of indigenous military systems, but also the role outside influences and new technologies brought to bear. This is a normal pattern among many nations.[PARAGRAPH:2]European contact[PARAGRAPH:1]Portugal[PARAGRAPH:1]The first European travelers to reach Benin were Portuguese explorers under João Afonso de Aveiro in about 1485. A strong mercantile relationship developed, with the Edo trading slaves and tropical products such as ivory, pepper and palm oil for European goods such as manillas and guns. In the early 16th century, the Oba sent an ambassador to Lisbon, and the king of Portugal sent Christian missionaries to Benin City. Some residents of Benin City could still speak a pidgin Portuguese in the late 19th century.[PARAGRAPH:1]England[PARAGRAPH:1]The first English expedition to Benin was in 1553, and significant trading developed between Europe and Benin based on the export of ivory, palm oil, pepper, and later slaves. Visitors in the 16th and 19th centuries brought back to Europe tales of "Great Benin", a fabulous city of noble buildings, ruled over by a powerful king. A fanciful engraving of the settlement was made by a Dutch illustrator (from descriptions alone) and was shown in Olfert Dapper's Naukeurige Beschrijvinge der Afrikaensche Gewesten, published in Amsterdam in 1668.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Netherlands[PARAGRAPH:1]Another Dutch traveler, David van Nyendael, visited Benin in 1699 and also wrote an account of the kingdom. Nyendael's description was published in 1704 as an appendix to Willem Bosman's Nauwkeurige Beschryving van de Guinese Goud-, tand- en Slave-kust. In his description, Nyendael states the following about the character of the Benin people:[PARAGRAPH:1]"The inhabitants of the Benin are in general a kind and polite people, of whom one with kindness might get everything he desires. Whatever might be offered to them out of politeness, will always be doubled in return. However, they want their politeness to be returned with likewise courtesy as well, without the appearance of any disappointment or rudeness, and rightly so. To be sure, trying to take anything from them with force or violence, would be as if one tries to reach out to the Moon and will never be left unreckoned. When it comes to trade, they are very strict and will not suffer the slightest infringement of their customs, not even a iota can be changed. Though, when one is willing to accept these customs, they are very easy-going and will cooperate in every way possible to reach an agreement".[PARAGRAPH:2]Art and cultural trade[PARAGRAPH:1]Scientific analysis of the brass (or "bronze") used to make the famous Benin plaques and other sculptures found that, beginning in the late 15th century, the metal (previously thought to have come from the Netherlands) began to derive from the Rhineland region of Germany. At that time, the brass was exported from Germany in the form of ring-shaped ingots which were used as currency in the trans-Atlantic slave trade (bought from the Portuguese and incorporated by the people in Benin as a metal source in sculpture), and subsequently melted down in Benin to produce Benin Bronzes.[PARAGRAPH:2]Notable figures (main points, details in the leader specific pages of the leaders from this implemented in this game/mod)[PARAGRAPH:1]Queen Idia[PARAGRAPH:1]Queen Idia was the wife of Oba Ozolua, the Oba who reigned in about 1481 AD. She was a famous warrior who received much of the credit for the victories of her son as his political counsel, together with her mystical powers and medicinal knowledge, were viewed as critical elements of Esigie's success on the battlefield. Queen Idia became more popular when an ivory carving of her face was adopted as the symbol of FESTAC in 1977.[PARAGRAPH:1]Emotan[PARAGRAPH:1]Emotan was a trader who sold her wares at the exact point where her statue now stands. She was historically credited with setting up the first primary school in the kingdom and saving the monarchy during one of its lowest moments. She helped the Oba Ewuare in reclaiming the throne from his usurper brother, Oba Uwaifiokun who reigned about 1432 AD.[PARAGRAPH:1]Queen Iden[PARAGRAPH:1]Queen Iden is yet another heroine whose sacrifice helped shape Benin Kingdom. She was the queen during the reign of Oba Ewuape in about 1700 AD. She is known to have volunteered herself as a sacrificial lamb for the welfare of her husband and that of the entire kingdom after she consulted the oracle and was informed that human sacrifice would be needed to appease the gods and restore peace and unity in the kingdom.[PARAGRAPH:1]General Asoro[PARAGRAPH:1]General Asoro the Warrior was the sword bearer to King Ovonramwen (the Oba of Benin) in 1897. He participated in the defence of Benin during the 1897 expedition, engaging the British expeditionary force sent to capture the Oba. A quote uttered by the general that "no other person [should] dare pass this road except the Oba" (So kpon Oba) was later translated to "SAKPONBA", which a well known road in Benin was named after.[PARAGRAPH:1]Chief Obasogie[PARAGRAPH:1]Chief Obasogie was not just an outstanding Benin warrior of old who defended the kingdom against external invasion but also a talented blacksmith and sculptor.</English>
	</TEXT>


	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_KINGDOM_OF_BENIN_DISCIPLINED_CROSSBOWMAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A crossbow is a ranged weapon using an elastic launching device consisting of a bow-like assembly called a prod, mounted horizontally on a main frame called a tiller, which is hand-held in a similar fashion to the stock of a long gun. Crossbows shoot arrow-like projectiles called bolts or quarrels. A person who shoots crossbow is called a crossbowman, an arbalister or an arbalist (after the arbalest, a European crossbow variant used during the 12th century).[PARAGRAPH:1][TAB]On top of the usual info that can be found on the [LINK=UNIT_CROSSBOWMAN]Crossbowman's page[\LINK], military operations in the Kingdom Of Benin relied on a well trained disciplined force. Formations were broken down into sub-units under designated commanders. Foreign observers often commented favorably on Benin's discipline and organization as "better disciplined than any other Guinea nation", contrasting them with the slacker troops from the Gold Coast.[PARAGRAPH:1][TAB]Before the coming of the gun, guilds of blacksmiths were charged with war production-particularly swords and iron spearheads. In addition, crossbowmen formed a specialized unit of the Benin army. Archers and crossbowmen were trained in target and field archery.Benin's tactics were well organized, with preliminary plans weighed by the Oba and his sub-commanders. Logistics were organized to support missions from the usual porter forces, water transport via canoe, and requisitioning from localities the army passed through. Movement of troops via canoes was critically important in the lagoons, creeks and rivers of the Niger Delta, a key area of Benin's domination.</English>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
