<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!-- custom: moved the lengthy part of the Sevopedia changes
to this file, but only for my mod specific changes (for example
a new civ, a new leader, etc) that are lengthy.
Hopefully more readable now, and perhaps exportable if some wish,
AdvCiv or/and other mods maybe i mean anyways about this,
at least about this i mean anyways, at least it's cleanly
separated at least about this i mean, anyways, i mean anyways -->

<!-- advc.008: Since the Civilopedia changes are so wordy (not the
     changes, but the copied text), I've moved them out of
     CIV4GameText_advc.xml, where the rest of the Advanced Civ game text
	 is located.
	 Starting with the two text keys changed by K-Mod
	 (one of them commented out, already in K-Mod) cut from
	 Civ4GameText_K-Mod.xml. The comments above those keys
	 are also from K-Mod. -->

<Civ4GameText>
	<!-- custom: add Ogiso Igodo, leader of the Kingdom Of Benin, copy pasted from:
	C:\Program Files (x86)\Steam\steamapps\common\Sid Meier's Civilization IV Beyond the Sword\Beyond the Sword\Assets\XML\Text\CIV4GameText_Civilopedia_BTS.xml then modified to fit this leader in this and
	about this case at least i mean anyways
	Mention of Ogiso Igodo also here:
	https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ogiso_monarchy#Origin_and_establishment
	Here too (found link on the page linked just above in this case i mean
	anyways at least maybe i mean anyways)
	https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Igodo
	some info here too i mean anyways:
	https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Igodomigodo
	note: i mean anyways, that put everything in English in all languages is
	so much more convenient and faster, maybe not best and ideal but many
	paragraphs and such even with translator, i hope i can invest my efforts
	elsewhere about this at least i mean anyways.
	I don't mind translating it once in English though is quite cool and
	interesting i mean anyways, but many times, about this i mean anyways
	at least maybe, is a chore if i may say i mean anywyas, i also think
	(and hope about this case maybe at least i mean anyways) that lost players
	would play in English, else maybe they would not mind too much about this,
	but is bit too long to do i mean anyways, as in tedious, not lengthy, i mean
	anyways, not impossible to do but i hope i can code other things aobut this
	i mean at least maybe i mean anyways, thanks,
	-->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_OGISO_IGODO_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Ogiso Igodo[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of The Kingdom of Benin[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] c.900s AD[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Igodo (Obagodo) was the first King of Igodomigodo (Which would then become the Kingdom Of Benin, and much later modern Nigeria (historically unrelated to modern Benin (see the pedia page of Kingdom of Benin for details))).[PARAGRAPH:1]According to Ife and early Benin tradition, he was one of the sons of Oduduwa who dispersed from Ife to found various kingdoms. Some Edo traditions say Igodo descended from heaven, others claim he came from the sky due to his great wisdom, hence his title Ogiso, meaning "King from the sky".[PARAGRAPH:1]During his reign, he organized the kingdoms administration, introduced new political structures, and reinforced the connection between Igodomigodo and the broader Yoruba civilization. There are also stories that describe the Ogiso traveling to Ife for festivals, further strengthening the ties between the two regions.[PARAGRAPH:1]His leadership laid the foundation for the later transformation of Igodomigodo into the Benin Kingdom, which grew into one of the most powerful kingdoms in West Africa. Igodos legacy is preserved in the historical narratives of both the Edo and Yoruba people. His rule signified the early formation of the Benin monarchy, which would later be formally restructured under Eweka I, a direct descendant of Oduduwa, who officially established the Oba of Benin dynasty after Oranmiyan's campaign. The Benin royal family, which traces its lineage to Oduduwa through Oranmiyan, continues to be a major institution in Nigeria today.[PARAGRAPH:1]Source:[PARAGRAPH:1]Wikipedia (several pages: Ogiso_monarchy#Origin_and_establishment, Igodo, Igodomigodo).</English>
		<French>[H1]Ogiso Igodo[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of The Kingdom of Benin[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] c.900s AD[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Igodo (Obagodo) was the first King of Igodomigodo (Which would then become the Kingdom Of Benin, and much later modern Nigeria (historically unrelated to modern Benin (see the pedia page of Kingdom of Benin for details))).[PARAGRAPH:1]According to Ife and early Benin tradition, he was one of the sons of Oduduwa who dispersed from Ife to found various kingdoms. Some Edo traditions say Igodo descended from heaven, others claim he came from the sky due to his great wisdom, hence his title Ogiso, meaning "King from the sky".[PARAGRAPH:1]During his reign, he organized the kingdoms administration, introduced new political structures, and reinforced the connection between Igodomigodo and the broader Yoruba civilization. There are also stories that describe the Ogiso traveling to Ife for festivals, further strengthening the ties between the two regions.[PARAGRAPH:1]His leadership laid the foundation for the later transformation of Igodomigodo into the Benin Kingdom, which grew into one of the most powerful kingdoms in West Africa. Igodos legacy is preserved in the historical narratives of both the Edo and Yoruba people. His rule signified the early formation of the Benin monarchy, which would later be formally restructured under Eweka I, a direct descendant of Oduduwa, who officially established the Oba of Benin dynasty after Oranmiyan's campaign. The Benin royal family, which traces its lineage to Oduduwa through Oranmiyan, continues to be a major institution in Nigeria today.[PARAGRAPH:1]Source:[PARAGRAPH:1]Wikipedia (several pages: Ogiso_monarchy#Origin_and_establishment, Igodo, Igodomigodo).</French>
		<German>[H1]Ogiso Igodo[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of The Kingdom of Benin[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] c.900s AD[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Igodo (Obagodo) was the first King of Igodomigodo (Which would then become the Kingdom Of Benin, and much later modern Nigeria (historically unrelated to modern Benin (see the pedia page of Kingdom of Benin for details))).[PARAGRAPH:1]According to Ife and early Benin tradition, he was one of the sons of Oduduwa who dispersed from Ife to found various kingdoms. Some Edo traditions say Igodo descended from heaven, others claim he came from the sky due to his great wisdom, hence his title Ogiso, meaning "King from the sky".[PARAGRAPH:1]During his reign, he organized the kingdoms administration, introduced new political structures, and reinforced the connection between Igodomigodo and the broader Yoruba civilization. There are also stories that describe the Ogiso traveling to Ife for festivals, further strengthening the ties between the two regions.[PARAGRAPH:1]His leadership laid the foundation for the later transformation of Igodomigodo into the Benin Kingdom, which grew into one of the most powerful kingdoms in West Africa. Igodos legacy is preserved in the historical narratives of both the Edo and Yoruba people. His rule signified the early formation of the Benin monarchy, which would later be formally restructured under Eweka I, a direct descendant of Oduduwa, who officially established the Oba of Benin dynasty after Oranmiyan's campaign. The Benin royal family, which traces its lineage to Oduduwa through Oranmiyan, continues to be a major institution in Nigeria today.[PARAGRAPH:1]Source:[PARAGRAPH:1]Wikipedia (several pages: Ogiso_monarchy#Origin_and_establishment, Igodo, Igodomigodo).</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Ogiso Igodo[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of The Kingdom of Benin[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] c.900s AD[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Igodo (Obagodo) was the first King of Igodomigodo (Which would then become the Kingdom Of Benin, and much later modern Nigeria (historically unrelated to modern Benin (see the pedia page of Kingdom of Benin for details))).[PARAGRAPH:1]According to Ife and early Benin tradition, he was one of the sons of Oduduwa who dispersed from Ife to found various kingdoms. Some Edo traditions say Igodo descended from heaven, others claim he came from the sky due to his great wisdom, hence his title Ogiso, meaning "King from the sky".[PARAGRAPH:1]During his reign, he organized the kingdoms administration, introduced new political structures, and reinforced the connection between Igodomigodo and the broader Yoruba civilization. There are also stories that describe the Ogiso traveling to Ife for festivals, further strengthening the ties between the two regions.[PARAGRAPH:1]His leadership laid the foundation for the later transformation of Igodomigodo into the Benin Kingdom, which grew into one of the most powerful kingdoms in West Africa. Igodos legacy is preserved in the historical narratives of both the Edo and Yoruba people. His rule signified the early formation of the Benin monarchy, which would later be formally restructured under Eweka I, a direct descendant of Oduduwa, who officially established the Oba of Benin dynasty after Oranmiyan's campaign. The Benin royal family, which traces its lineage to Oduduwa through Oranmiyan, continues to be a major institution in Nigeria today.[PARAGRAPH:1]Source:[PARAGRAPH:1]Wikipedia (several pages: Ogiso_monarchy#Origin_and_establishment, Igodo, Igodomigodo).</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]Ogiso Igodo[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of The Kingdom of Benin[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] c.900s AD[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Igodo (Obagodo) was the first King of Igodomigodo (Which would then become the Kingdom Of Benin, and much later modern Nigeria (historically unrelated to modern Benin (see the pedia page of Kingdom of Benin for details))).[PARAGRAPH:1]According to Ife and early Benin tradition, he was one of the sons of Oduduwa who dispersed from Ife to found various kingdoms. Some Edo traditions say Igodo descended from heaven, others claim he came from the sky due to his great wisdom, hence his title Ogiso, meaning "King from the sky".[PARAGRAPH:1]During his reign, he organized the kingdoms administration, introduced new political structures, and reinforced the connection between Igodomigodo and the broader Yoruba civilization. There are also stories that describe the Ogiso traveling to Ife for festivals, further strengthening the ties between the two regions.[PARAGRAPH:1]His leadership laid the foundation for the later transformation of Igodomigodo into the Benin Kingdom, which grew into one of the most powerful kingdoms in West Africa. Igodos legacy is preserved in the historical narratives of both the Edo and Yoruba people. His rule signified the early formation of the Benin monarchy, which would later be formally restructured under Eweka I, a direct descendant of Oduduwa, who officially established the Oba of Benin dynasty after Oranmiyan's campaign. The Benin royal family, which traces its lineage to Oduduwa through Oranmiyan, continues to be a major institution in Nigeria today.[PARAGRAPH:1]Source:[PARAGRAPH:1]Wikipedia (several pages: Ogiso_monarchy#Origin_and_establishment, Igodo, Igodomigodo).</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	

	<!-- custom: clean import from:
	C:\Program Files (x86)\Steam\steamapps\common\Sid Meier's Civilization IV Beyond the Sword\Beyond the Sword\Assets\XML\Text\CIV4GameText_Civilopedia_BTS.xml
	And then editing it i mean anyways
	See (also i mean anyways about this (case) i mean anyways) :
	https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Benin
	As for the leader entry (Ogiso Igodo), and most likely similarly
	to next cases about	this at least maybe i mean anyways, i would not
	translate the full version/thing about this i mean anywyas at least
	in other languages, i have Quillbot though or/and other bots about
	this i mean anyways, i mean anyways as is i mean anyways.
	Hopefully the English version in all languages is good enough for
	about this i mean anyways. -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_KINGDOM_OF_BENIN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Kingdom of Benin, also known as Great Benin or Benin Kingdom was a kingdom within what is now considered southern Nigeria. It has no historical relation to the modern republic of Benin, which was known as Dahomey from the 17th century until 1975. The Kingdom of Benin's capital was Edo, now known as Benin City in Edo State, Nigeria.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Benin Kingdom was one of the oldest and most developed states in the coastal hinterland of West Africa. It grew out of the previous Edo Kingdom of Igodomigodo around the 11th century AD; it was annexed by the British Empire in 1897.[PARAGRAPH:1]In the 15th and 16th centuries, the kingdom reached the height of its prosperity, expanding its territory, trading with European powers, and creating a remarkable artistic legacy in cast bronze, iron, brass, carved ivory, and other materials.[PARAGRAPH:2]Rituals and laws[PARAGRAPH:1]Human sacrifices[PARAGRAPH:1]Humans were sacrificed in an annual ritual in honour of the god of iron, where warriors from Benin City would perform an acrobatic dance while suspended from the trees. The ritual recalled a mythical war against the sky. Sacrifices of a man, a woman, a goat, a cow and a ram were also made to a god called "the king of death". The god, named Ogiuwu, was worshipped at a special altar in the centre of Benin City. There were two separate annual series of rites that honored past Obas. Sacrifices were performed every fifth day. At the end of each series of rites, the current Oba's deceased father was honored with a public festival. During the festival, twelve criminals, chosen from a prison where the worst criminals were held, were sacrificed. By the end of the eighteenth century, three to four people were sacrificed at the mouth of the Benin River annually, to attract European trade, according to one source.[PARAGRAPH:1]Burials[PARAGRAPH:1]The monarchy of Benin was hereditary; the eldest son was to become the new Oba. In order to validate the succession of the kingship, the eldest son had to bury his father and perform elaborate rituals. If the eldest son failed to complete these tasks, he might be disqualified from becoming king.[PARAGRAPH:1]Separation of son and mother[PARAGRAPH:1]After the son was installed as king, his mother - after having been invested with the title of Iyoba - was transferred to a palace just outside Benin City, in a place called Uselu. The mother held a considerable amount of power; she was, however, never allowed to meet her son - who was now a divine ruler - again.[PARAGRAPH:1]Divinity of the Oba[PARAGRAPH:1]In Benin, the Oba was seen as divine. The Oba's divinity and sacredness was the focal point of the kingship. The Oba was shrouded in mystery; he only left his palace on ceremonial occasions. It was previously punishable by death to assert that the Oba performed human acts, such as eating, sleeping, dying or washing. The Oba was also credited with having magical powers. He also controlled a powerful bureaucratic apparatus whose decrees were obeyed to the letter.[PARAGRAPH:2]Architecture[PARAGRAPH:1]Impluvium[PARAGRAPH:1]The Impluvium was used in Benin architecture to store rainwater (see the building entry of the Impluvium in the pedia for details).[PARAGRAPH:1]City walls[PARAGRAPH:1]The Benin City walls have been known to Westerners since around 1500. Around 1500, the Portuguese explorer Duarte Pacheco Pereira, briefly described the walls during his travels. In Pereira's Esmeraldo de Situ Orbis, 1505, we read:[PARAGRAPH:1]"The houses are built of sun-dried bricks covered with palm leaves. Benin, which is 80 leagues [sic] long by 40 leagues [sic] broad, is always at war with its neighbours from whom it obtains captives, whom we buy at from 12 to 15 brass or copper manillas".[PARAGRAPH:1]Another description given around 1600, one hundred years after Pereira's description, is by the Dutch explorer Dierick Ruiters. Pereira's account of the walls is as follows:[PARAGRAPH:1]"This city is about a league long from gate to gate; it has no wall but is surrounded by a large moat, very wide and deep, which suffices for its defence". For more details, see the entry in the pedia: "The Ancient Walls of Benin" (Wonder).[PARAGRAPH:2]Military[PARAGRAPH:1]Operations[PARAGRAPH:1]Military operations relied on a well trained disciplined force. At the head of the host stood the Oba of Benin. The monarch of the realm served as supreme military commander. Beneath him were subordinate generalissimos, the Ezomo, the Iyase, and others who supervised a Metropolitan Regiment based in the capital, and a Royal Regiment made up of hand-picked warriors that also served as bodyguards. Benin's queen mother, the Iyoba, also retained her own regiment - the "Queen's Own". The Metropolitan and Royal regiments were relatively stable semi-permanent or permanent formations. The Village Regiments provided the bulk of the fighting force and were mobilized as needed, sending contingents of warriors upon the command of the king and his generals. Formations were broken down into sub-units under designated commanders. Foreign observers often commented favorably on Benin's discipline and organization as "better disciplined than any other Guinea nation", contrasting them with the slacker troops from the Gold Coast.[PARAGRAPH:1]Tactics[PARAGRAPH:1]Benin's tactics were well organized, with preliminary plans weighed by the Oba and his sub-commanders. Logistics were organized to support missions from the usual porter forces, water transport via canoe, and requisitioning from localities the army passed through. Movement of troops via canoes was critically important in the lagoons, creeks and rivers of the Niger Delta, a key area of Benin's domination. Tactics in the field seem to have evolved over time. While the head-on clash was well known, documentation from the 18th century shows greater emphasis on avoiding continuous battle lines, and more effort to encircle an enemy (ifianyako).Fortifications were important in the region and numerous military campaigns fought by Benin's soldiers revolved around sieges. Benin's military earthworks are the largest of such structures in the world, and Benin's rivals also built extensively. Barring a successful assault, most sieges were resolved by a strategy of attrition, slowly cutting off and starving out the enemy fortification until it capitulated. On occasion, however, European mercenaries were called on to aid with these sieges. In 1603-04 for example, European cannon helped batter and destroy the gates of a town near present-day Lagos, allowing 10,000 warriors of Benin to enter and conquer it. As payment, the Europeans received items, such as palm oil and bundles of pepper. The example of Benin shows the power of indigenous military systems, but also the role outside influences and new technologies brought to bear. This is a normal pattern among many nations.[PARAGRAPH:2]European contact[PARAGRAPH:1]Portugal[PARAGRAPH:1]The first European travelers to reach Benin were Portuguese explorers under João Afonso de Aveiro in about 1485. A strong mercantile relationship developed, with the Edo trading slaves and tropical products such as ivory, pepper and palm oil for European goods such as manillas and guns. In the early 16th century, the Oba sent an ambassador to Lisbon, and the king of Portugal sent Christian missionaries to Benin City. Some residents of Benin City could still speak a pidgin Portuguese in the late 19th century.[PARAGRAPH:1]England[PARAGRAPH:1]The first English expedition to Benin was in 1553, and significant trading developed between Europe and Benin based on the export of ivory, palm oil, pepper, and later slaves. Visitors in the 16th and 19th centuries brought back to Europe tales of "Great Benin", a fabulous city of noble buildings, ruled over by a powerful king. A fanciful engraving of the settlement was made by a Dutch illustrator (from descriptions alone) and was shown in Olfert Dapper's Naukeurige Beschrijvinge der Afrikaensche Gewesten, published in Amsterdam in 1668.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Netherlands[PARAGRAPH:1]Another Dutch traveler, David van Nyendael, visited Benin in 1699 and also wrote an account of the kingdom. Nyendael's description was published in 1704 as an appendix to Willem Bosman's Nauwkeurige Beschryving van de Guinese Goud-, tand- en Slave-kust. In his description, Nyendael states the following about the character of the Benin people:[PARAGRAPH:1]"The inhabitants of the Benin are in general a kind and polite people, of whom one with kindness might get everything he desires. Whatever might be offered to them out of politeness, will always be doubled in return. However, they want their politeness to be returned with likewise courtesy as well, without the appearance of any disappointment or rudeness, and rightly so. To be sure, trying to take anything from them with force or violence, would be as if one tries to reach out to the Moon and will never be left unreckoned. When it comes to trade, they are very strict and will not suffer the slightest infringement of their customs, not even a iota can be changed. Though, when one is willing to accept these customs, they are very easy-going and will cooperate in every way possible to reach an agreement".[PARAGRAPH:2]Art and cultural trade[PARAGRAPH:1]Scientific analysis of the brass (or "bronze") used to make the famous Benin plaques and other sculptures found that, beginning in the late 15th century, the metal (previously thought to have come from the Netherlands) began to derive from the Rhineland region of Germany. At that time, the brass was exported from Germany in the form of ring-shaped ingots which were used as currency in the trans-Atlantic slave trade (bought from the Portuguese and incorporated by the people in Benin as a metal source in sculpture), and subsequently melted down in Benin to produce Benin Bronzes.[PARAGRAPH:2]Notable figures (main points, details in the leader specific pages of the leaders from this implemented in this game/mod)[PARAGRAPH:1]Queen Idia[PARAGRAPH:1]Queen Idia was the wife of Oba Ozolua, the Oba who reigned in about 1481 AD. She was a famous warrior who received much of the credit for the victories of her son as his political counsel, together with her mystical powers and medicinal knowledge, were viewed as critical elements of Esigie's success on the battlefield. Queen Idia became more popular when an ivory carving of her face was adopted as the symbol of FESTAC in 1977.[PARAGRAPH:1]Emotan[PARAGRAPH:1]Emotan was a trader who sold her wares at the exact point where her statue now stands. She was historically credited with setting up the first primary school in the kingdom and saving the monarchy during one of its lowest moments. She helped the Oba Ewuare in reclaiming the throne from his usurper brother, Oba Uwaifiokun who reigned about 1432 AD.[PARAGRAPH:1]Queen Iden[PARAGRAPH:1]Queen Iden is yet another heroine whose sacrifice helped shape Benin Kingdom. She was the queen during the reign of Oba Ewuape in about 1700 AD. She is known to have volunteered herself as a sacrificial lamb for the welfare of her husband and that of the entire kingdom after she consulted the oracle and was informed that human sacrifice would be needed to appease the gods and restore peace and unity in the kingdom.[PARAGRAPH:1]General Asoro[PARAGRAPH:1]General Asoro the Warrior was the sword bearer to King Ovonramwen (the Oba of Benin) in 1897. He participated in the defence of Benin during the 1897 expedition, engaging the British expeditionary force sent to capture the Oba. A quote uttered by the general that "no other person [should] dare pass this road except the Oba" (So kpon Oba) was later translated to "SAKPONBA", which a well known road in Benin was named after.[PARAGRAPH:1]Chief Obasogie[PARAGRAPH:1]Chief Obasogie was not just an outstanding Benin warrior of old who defended the kingdom against external invasion but also a talented blacksmith and sculptor.[PARAGRAPH:2]Source:[PARAGRAPH:1]https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Benin</English>
		<French>[TAB]The Kingdom of Benin, also known as Great Benin or Benin Kingdom was a kingdom within what is now considered southern Nigeria. It has no historical relation to the modern republic of Benin, which was known as Dahomey from the 17th century until 1975. The Kingdom of Benin's capital was Edo, now known as Benin City in Edo State, Nigeria.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Benin Kingdom was one of the oldest and most developed states in the coastal hinterland of West Africa. It grew out of the previous Edo Kingdom of Igodomigodo around the 11th century AD; it was annexed by the British Empire in 1897.[PARAGRAPH:1]In the 15th and 16th centuries, the kingdom reached the height of its prosperity, expanding its territory, trading with European powers, and creating a remarkable artistic legacy in cast bronze, iron, brass, carved ivory, and other materials.[PARAGRAPH:2]Rituals and laws[PARAGRAPH:1]Human sacrifices[PARAGRAPH:1]Humans were sacrificed in an annual ritual in honour of the god of iron, where warriors from Benin City would perform an acrobatic dance while suspended from the trees. The ritual recalled a mythical war against the sky. Sacrifices of a man, a woman, a goat, a cow and a ram were also made to a god called "the king of death". The god, named Ogiuwu, was worshipped at a special altar in the centre of Benin City. There were two separate annual series of rites that honored past Obas. Sacrifices were performed every fifth day. At the end of each series of rites, the current Oba's deceased father was honored with a public festival. During the festival, twelve criminals, chosen from a prison where the worst criminals were held, were sacrificed. By the end of the eighteenth century, three to four people were sacrificed at the mouth of the Benin River annually, to attract European trade, according to one source.[PARAGRAPH:1]Burials[PARAGRAPH:1]The monarchy of Benin was hereditary; the eldest son was to become the new Oba. In order to validate the succession of the kingship, the eldest son had to bury his father and perform elaborate rituals. If the eldest son failed to complete these tasks, he might be disqualified from becoming king.[PARAGRAPH:1]Separation of son and mother[PARAGRAPH:1]After the son was installed as king, his mother - after having been invested with the title of Iyoba - was transferred to a palace just outside Benin City, in a place called Uselu. The mother held a considerable amount of power; she was, however, never allowed to meet her son - who was now a divine ruler - again.[PARAGRAPH:1]Divinity of the Oba[PARAGRAPH:1]In Benin, the Oba was seen as divine. The Oba's divinity and sacredness was the focal point of the kingship. The Oba was shrouded in mystery; he only left his palace on ceremonial occasions. It was previously punishable by death to assert that the Oba performed human acts, such as eating, sleeping, dying or washing. The Oba was also credited with having magical powers. He also controlled a powerful bureaucratic apparatus whose decrees were obeyed to the letter.[PARAGRAPH:2]Architecture[PARAGRAPH:1]Impluvium[PARAGRAPH:1]The Impluvium was used in Benin architecture to store rainwater (see the building entry of the Impluvium in the pedia for details).[PARAGRAPH:1]City walls[PARAGRAPH:1]The Benin City walls have been known to Westerners since around 1500. Around 1500, the Portuguese explorer Duarte Pacheco Pereira, briefly described the walls during his travels. In Pereira's Esmeraldo de Situ Orbis, 1505, we read:[PARAGRAPH:1]"The houses are built of sun-dried bricks covered with palm leaves. Benin, which is 80 leagues [sic] long by 40 leagues [sic] broad, is always at war with its neighbours from whom it obtains captives, whom we buy at from 12 to 15 brass or copper manillas".[PARAGRAPH:1]Another description given around 1600, one hundred years after Pereira's description, is by the Dutch explorer Dierick Ruiters. Pereira's account of the walls is as follows:[PARAGRAPH:1]"This city is about a league long from gate to gate; it has no wall but is surrounded by a large moat, very wide and deep, which suffices for its defence". For more details, see the entry in the pedia: "The Ancient Walls of Benin" (Wonder).[PARAGRAPH:2]Military[PARAGRAPH:1]Operations[PARAGRAPH:1]Military operations relied on a well trained disciplined force. At the head of the host stood the Oba of Benin. The monarch of the realm served as supreme military commander. Beneath him were subordinate generalissimos, the Ezomo, the Iyase, and others who supervised a Metropolitan Regiment based in the capital, and a Royal Regiment made up of hand-picked warriors that also served as bodyguards. Benin's queen mother, the Iyoba, also retained her own regiment - the "Queen's Own". The Metropolitan and Royal regiments were relatively stable semi-permanent or permanent formations. The Village Regiments provided the bulk of the fighting force and were mobilized as needed, sending contingents of warriors upon the command of the king and his generals. Formations were broken down into sub-units under designated commanders. Foreign observers often commented favorably on Benin's discipline and organization as "better disciplined than any other Guinea nation", contrasting them with the slacker troops from the Gold Coast.[PARAGRAPH:1]Tactics[PARAGRAPH:1]Benin's tactics were well organized, with preliminary plans weighed by the Oba and his sub-commanders. Logistics were organized to support missions from the usual porter forces, water transport via canoe, and requisitioning from localities the army passed through. Movement of troops via canoes was critically important in the lagoons, creeks and rivers of the Niger Delta, a key area of Benin's domination. Tactics in the field seem to have evolved over time. While the head-on clash was well known, documentation from the 18th century shows greater emphasis on avoiding continuous battle lines, and more effort to encircle an enemy (ifianyako).Fortifications were important in the region and numerous military campaigns fought by Benin's soldiers revolved around sieges. Benin's military earthworks are the largest of such structures in the world, and Benin's rivals also built extensively. Barring a successful assault, most sieges were resolved by a strategy of attrition, slowly cutting off and starving out the enemy fortification until it capitulated. On occasion, however, European mercenaries were called on to aid with these sieges. In 1603-04 for example, European cannon helped batter and destroy the gates of a town near present-day Lagos, allowing 10,000 warriors of Benin to enter and conquer it. As payment, the Europeans received items, such as palm oil and bundles of pepper. The example of Benin shows the power of indigenous military systems, but also the role outside influences and new technologies brought to bear. This is a normal pattern among many nations.[PARAGRAPH:2]European contact[PARAGRAPH:1]Portugal[PARAGRAPH:1]The first European travelers to reach Benin were Portuguese explorers under João Afonso de Aveiro in about 1485. A strong mercantile relationship developed, with the Edo trading slaves and tropical products such as ivory, pepper and palm oil for European goods such as manillas and guns. In the early 16th century, the Oba sent an ambassador to Lisbon, and the king of Portugal sent Christian missionaries to Benin City. Some residents of Benin City could still speak a pidgin Portuguese in the late 19th century.[PARAGRAPH:1]England[PARAGRAPH:1]The first English expedition to Benin was in 1553, and significant trading developed between Europe and Benin based on the export of ivory, palm oil, pepper, and later slaves. Visitors in the 16th and 19th centuries brought back to Europe tales of "Great Benin", a fabulous city of noble buildings, ruled over by a powerful king. A fanciful engraving of the settlement was made by a Dutch illustrator (from descriptions alone) and was shown in Olfert Dapper's Naukeurige Beschrijvinge der Afrikaensche Gewesten, published in Amsterdam in 1668.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Netherlands[PARAGRAPH:1]Another Dutch traveler, David van Nyendael, visited Benin in 1699 and also wrote an account of the kingdom. Nyendael's description was published in 1704 as an appendix to Willem Bosman's Nauwkeurige Beschryving van de Guinese Goud-, tand- en Slave-kust. In his description, Nyendael states the following about the character of the Benin people:[PARAGRAPH:1]"The inhabitants of the Benin are in general a kind and polite people, of whom one with kindness might get everything he desires. Whatever might be offered to them out of politeness, will always be doubled in return. However, they want their politeness to be returned with likewise courtesy as well, without the appearance of any disappointment or rudeness, and rightly so. To be sure, trying to take anything from them with force or violence, would be as if one tries to reach out to the Moon and will never be left unreckoned. When it comes to trade, they are very strict and will not suffer the slightest infringement of their customs, not even a iota can be changed. Though, when one is willing to accept these customs, they are very easy-going and will cooperate in every way possible to reach an agreement".[PARAGRAPH:2]Art and cultural trade[PARAGRAPH:1]Scientific analysis of the brass (or "bronze") used to make the famous Benin plaques and other sculptures found that, beginning in the late 15th century, the metal (previously thought to have come from the Netherlands) began to derive from the Rhineland region of Germany. At that time, the brass was exported from Germany in the form of ring-shaped ingots which were used as currency in the trans-Atlantic slave trade (bought from the Portuguese and incorporated by the people in Benin as a metal source in sculpture), and subsequently melted down in Benin to produce Benin Bronzes.[PARAGRAPH:2]Notable figures (main points, details in the leader specific pages of the leaders from this implemented in this game/mod)[PARAGRAPH:1]Queen Idia[PARAGRAPH:1]Queen Idia was the wife of Oba Ozolua, the Oba who reigned in about 1481 AD. She was a famous warrior who received much of the credit for the victories of her son as his political counsel, together with her mystical powers and medicinal knowledge, were viewed as critical elements of Esigie's success on the battlefield. Queen Idia became more popular when an ivory carving of her face was adopted as the symbol of FESTAC in 1977.[PARAGRAPH:1]Emotan[PARAGRAPH:1]Emotan was a trader who sold her wares at the exact point where her statue now stands. She was historically credited with setting up the first primary school in the kingdom and saving the monarchy during one of its lowest moments. She helped the Oba Ewuare in reclaiming the throne from his usurper brother, Oba Uwaifiokun who reigned about 1432 AD.[PARAGRAPH:1]Queen Iden[PARAGRAPH:1]Queen Iden is yet another heroine whose sacrifice helped shape Benin Kingdom. She was the queen during the reign of Oba Ewuape in about 1700 AD. She is known to have volunteered herself as a sacrificial lamb for the welfare of her husband and that of the entire kingdom after she consulted the oracle and was informed that human sacrifice would be needed to appease the gods and restore peace and unity in the kingdom.[PARAGRAPH:1]General Asoro[PARAGRAPH:1]General Asoro the Warrior was the sword bearer to King Ovonramwen (the Oba of Benin) in 1897. He participated in the defence of Benin during the 1897 expedition, engaging the British expeditionary force sent to capture the Oba. A quote uttered by the general that "no other person [should] dare pass this road except the Oba" (So kpon Oba) was later translated to "SAKPONBA", which a well known road in Benin was named after.[PARAGRAPH:1]Chief Obasogie[PARAGRAPH:1]Chief Obasogie was not just an outstanding Benin warrior of old who defended the kingdom against external invasion but also a talented blacksmith and sculptor.[PARAGRAPH:2]Source:[PARAGRAPH:1]https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Benin</French>
		<German>[TAB]The Kingdom of Benin, also known as Great Benin or Benin Kingdom was a kingdom within what is now considered southern Nigeria. It has no historical relation to the modern republic of Benin, which was known as Dahomey from the 17th century until 1975. The Kingdom of Benin's capital was Edo, now known as Benin City in Edo State, Nigeria.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Benin Kingdom was one of the oldest and most developed states in the coastal hinterland of West Africa. It grew out of the previous Edo Kingdom of Igodomigodo around the 11th century AD; it was annexed by the British Empire in 1897.[PARAGRAPH:1]In the 15th and 16th centuries, the kingdom reached the height of its prosperity, expanding its territory, trading with European powers, and creating a remarkable artistic legacy in cast bronze, iron, brass, carved ivory, and other materials.[PARAGRAPH:2]Rituals and laws[PARAGRAPH:1]Human sacrifices[PARAGRAPH:1]Humans were sacrificed in an annual ritual in honour of the god of iron, where warriors from Benin City would perform an acrobatic dance while suspended from the trees. The ritual recalled a mythical war against the sky. Sacrifices of a man, a woman, a goat, a cow and a ram were also made to a god called "the king of death". The god, named Ogiuwu, was worshipped at a special altar in the centre of Benin City. There were two separate annual series of rites that honored past Obas. Sacrifices were performed every fifth day. At the end of each series of rites, the current Oba's deceased father was honored with a public festival. During the festival, twelve criminals, chosen from a prison where the worst criminals were held, were sacrificed. By the end of the eighteenth century, three to four people were sacrificed at the mouth of the Benin River annually, to attract European trade, according to one source.[PARAGRAPH:1]Burials[PARAGRAPH:1]The monarchy of Benin was hereditary; the eldest son was to become the new Oba. In order to validate the succession of the kingship, the eldest son had to bury his father and perform elaborate rituals. If the eldest son failed to complete these tasks, he might be disqualified from becoming king.[PARAGRAPH:1]Separation of son and mother[PARAGRAPH:1]After the son was installed as king, his mother - after having been invested with the title of Iyoba - was transferred to a palace just outside Benin City, in a place called Uselu. The mother held a considerable amount of power; she was, however, never allowed to meet her son - who was now a divine ruler - again.[PARAGRAPH:1]Divinity of the Oba[PARAGRAPH:1]In Benin, the Oba was seen as divine. The Oba's divinity and sacredness was the focal point of the kingship. The Oba was shrouded in mystery; he only left his palace on ceremonial occasions. It was previously punishable by death to assert that the Oba performed human acts, such as eating, sleeping, dying or washing. The Oba was also credited with having magical powers. He also controlled a powerful bureaucratic apparatus whose decrees were obeyed to the letter.[PARAGRAPH:2]Architecture[PARAGRAPH:1]Impluvium[PARAGRAPH:1]The Impluvium was used in Benin architecture to store rainwater (see the building entry of the Impluvium in the pedia for details).[PARAGRAPH:1]City walls[PARAGRAPH:1]The Benin City walls have been known to Westerners since around 1500. Around 1500, the Portuguese explorer Duarte Pacheco Pereira, briefly described the walls during his travels. In Pereira's Esmeraldo de Situ Orbis, 1505, we read:[PARAGRAPH:1]"The houses are built of sun-dried bricks covered with palm leaves. Benin, which is 80 leagues [sic] long by 40 leagues [sic] broad, is always at war with its neighbours from whom it obtains captives, whom we buy at from 12 to 15 brass or copper manillas".[PARAGRAPH:1]Another description given around 1600, one hundred years after Pereira's description, is by the Dutch explorer Dierick Ruiters. Pereira's account of the walls is as follows:[PARAGRAPH:1]"This city is about a league long from gate to gate; it has no wall but is surrounded by a large moat, very wide and deep, which suffices for its defence". For more details, see the entry in the pedia: "The Ancient Walls of Benin" (Wonder).[PARAGRAPH:2]Military[PARAGRAPH:1]Operations[PARAGRAPH:1]Military operations relied on a well trained disciplined force. At the head of the host stood the Oba of Benin. The monarch of the realm served as supreme military commander. Beneath him were subordinate generalissimos, the Ezomo, the Iyase, and others who supervised a Metropolitan Regiment based in the capital, and a Royal Regiment made up of hand-picked warriors that also served as bodyguards. Benin's queen mother, the Iyoba, also retained her own regiment - the "Queen's Own". The Metropolitan and Royal regiments were relatively stable semi-permanent or permanent formations. The Village Regiments provided the bulk of the fighting force and were mobilized as needed, sending contingents of warriors upon the command of the king and his generals. Formations were broken down into sub-units under designated commanders. Foreign observers often commented favorably on Benin's discipline and organization as "better disciplined than any other Guinea nation", contrasting them with the slacker troops from the Gold Coast.[PARAGRAPH:1]Tactics[PARAGRAPH:1]Benin's tactics were well organized, with preliminary plans weighed by the Oba and his sub-commanders. Logistics were organized to support missions from the usual porter forces, water transport via canoe, and requisitioning from localities the army passed through. Movement of troops via canoes was critically important in the lagoons, creeks and rivers of the Niger Delta, a key area of Benin's domination. Tactics in the field seem to have evolved over time. While the head-on clash was well known, documentation from the 18th century shows greater emphasis on avoiding continuous battle lines, and more effort to encircle an enemy (ifianyako).Fortifications were important in the region and numerous military campaigns fought by Benin's soldiers revolved around sieges. Benin's military earthworks are the largest of such structures in the world, and Benin's rivals also built extensively. Barring a successful assault, most sieges were resolved by a strategy of attrition, slowly cutting off and starving out the enemy fortification until it capitulated. On occasion, however, European mercenaries were called on to aid with these sieges. In 1603-04 for example, European cannon helped batter and destroy the gates of a town near present-day Lagos, allowing 10,000 warriors of Benin to enter and conquer it. As payment, the Europeans received items, such as palm oil and bundles of pepper. The example of Benin shows the power of indigenous military systems, but also the role outside influences and new technologies brought to bear. This is a normal pattern among many nations.[PARAGRAPH:2]European contact[PARAGRAPH:1]Portugal[PARAGRAPH:1]The first European travelers to reach Benin were Portuguese explorers under João Afonso de Aveiro in about 1485. A strong mercantile relationship developed, with the Edo trading slaves and tropical products such as ivory, pepper and palm oil for European goods such as manillas and guns. In the early 16th century, the Oba sent an ambassador to Lisbon, and the king of Portugal sent Christian missionaries to Benin City. Some residents of Benin City could still speak a pidgin Portuguese in the late 19th century.[PARAGRAPH:1]England[PARAGRAPH:1]The first English expedition to Benin was in 1553, and significant trading developed between Europe and Benin based on the export of ivory, palm oil, pepper, and later slaves. Visitors in the 16th and 19th centuries brought back to Europe tales of "Great Benin", a fabulous city of noble buildings, ruled over by a powerful king. A fanciful engraving of the settlement was made by a Dutch illustrator (from descriptions alone) and was shown in Olfert Dapper's Naukeurige Beschrijvinge der Afrikaensche Gewesten, published in Amsterdam in 1668.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Netherlands[PARAGRAPH:1]Another Dutch traveler, David van Nyendael, visited Benin in 1699 and also wrote an account of the kingdom. Nyendael's description was published in 1704 as an appendix to Willem Bosman's Nauwkeurige Beschryving van de Guinese Goud-, tand- en Slave-kust. In his description, Nyendael states the following about the character of the Benin people:[PARAGRAPH:1]"The inhabitants of the Benin are in general a kind and polite people, of whom one with kindness might get everything he desires. Whatever might be offered to them out of politeness, will always be doubled in return. However, they want their politeness to be returned with likewise courtesy as well, without the appearance of any disappointment or rudeness, and rightly so. To be sure, trying to take anything from them with force or violence, would be as if one tries to reach out to the Moon and will never be left unreckoned. When it comes to trade, they are very strict and will not suffer the slightest infringement of their customs, not even a iota can be changed. Though, when one is willing to accept these customs, they are very easy-going and will cooperate in every way possible to reach an agreement".[PARAGRAPH:2]Art and cultural trade[PARAGRAPH:1]Scientific analysis of the brass (or "bronze") used to make the famous Benin plaques and other sculptures found that, beginning in the late 15th century, the metal (previously thought to have come from the Netherlands) began to derive from the Rhineland region of Germany. At that time, the brass was exported from Germany in the form of ring-shaped ingots which were used as currency in the trans-Atlantic slave trade (bought from the Portuguese and incorporated by the people in Benin as a metal source in sculpture), and subsequently melted down in Benin to produce Benin Bronzes.[PARAGRAPH:2]Notable figures (main points, details in the leader specific pages of the leaders from this implemented in this game/mod)[PARAGRAPH:1]Queen Idia[PARAGRAPH:1]Queen Idia was the wife of Oba Ozolua, the Oba who reigned in about 1481 AD. She was a famous warrior who received much of the credit for the victories of her son as his political counsel, together with her mystical powers and medicinal knowledge, were viewed as critical elements of Esigie's success on the battlefield. Queen Idia became more popular when an ivory carving of her face was adopted as the symbol of FESTAC in 1977.[PARAGRAPH:1]Emotan[PARAGRAPH:1]Emotan was a trader who sold her wares at the exact point where her statue now stands. She was historically credited with setting up the first primary school in the kingdom and saving the monarchy during one of its lowest moments. She helped the Oba Ewuare in reclaiming the throne from his usurper brother, Oba Uwaifiokun who reigned about 1432 AD.[PARAGRAPH:1]Queen Iden[PARAGRAPH:1]Queen Iden is yet another heroine whose sacrifice helped shape Benin Kingdom. She was the queen during the reign of Oba Ewuape in about 1700 AD. She is known to have volunteered herself as a sacrificial lamb for the welfare of her husband and that of the entire kingdom after she consulted the oracle and was informed that human sacrifice would be needed to appease the gods and restore peace and unity in the kingdom.[PARAGRAPH:1]General Asoro[PARAGRAPH:1]General Asoro the Warrior was the sword bearer to King Ovonramwen (the Oba of Benin) in 1897. He participated in the defence of Benin during the 1897 expedition, engaging the British expeditionary force sent to capture the Oba. A quote uttered by the general that "no other person [should] dare pass this road except the Oba" (So kpon Oba) was later translated to "SAKPONBA", which a well known road in Benin was named after.[PARAGRAPH:1]Chief Obasogie[PARAGRAPH:1]Chief Obasogie was not just an outstanding Benin warrior of old who defended the kingdom against external invasion but also a talented blacksmith and sculptor.[PARAGRAPH:2]Source:[PARAGRAPH:1]https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Benin</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]The Kingdom of Benin, also known as Great Benin or Benin Kingdom was a kingdom within what is now considered southern Nigeria. It has no historical relation to the modern republic of Benin, which was known as Dahomey from the 17th century until 1975. The Kingdom of Benin's capital was Edo, now known as Benin City in Edo State, Nigeria.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Benin Kingdom was one of the oldest and most developed states in the coastal hinterland of West Africa. It grew out of the previous Edo Kingdom of Igodomigodo around the 11th century AD; it was annexed by the British Empire in 1897.[PARAGRAPH:1]In the 15th and 16th centuries, the kingdom reached the height of its prosperity, expanding its territory, trading with European powers, and creating a remarkable artistic legacy in cast bronze, iron, brass, carved ivory, and other materials.[PARAGRAPH:2]Rituals and laws[PARAGRAPH:1]Human sacrifices[PARAGRAPH:1]Humans were sacrificed in an annual ritual in honour of the god of iron, where warriors from Benin City would perform an acrobatic dance while suspended from the trees. The ritual recalled a mythical war against the sky. Sacrifices of a man, a woman, a goat, a cow and a ram were also made to a god called "the king of death". The god, named Ogiuwu, was worshipped at a special altar in the centre of Benin City. There were two separate annual series of rites that honored past Obas. Sacrifices were performed every fifth day. At the end of each series of rites, the current Oba's deceased father was honored with a public festival. During the festival, twelve criminals, chosen from a prison where the worst criminals were held, were sacrificed. By the end of the eighteenth century, three to four people were sacrificed at the mouth of the Benin River annually, to attract European trade, according to one source.[PARAGRAPH:1]Burials[PARAGRAPH:1]The monarchy of Benin was hereditary; the eldest son was to become the new Oba. In order to validate the succession of the kingship, the eldest son had to bury his father and perform elaborate rituals. If the eldest son failed to complete these tasks, he might be disqualified from becoming king.[PARAGRAPH:1]Separation of son and mother[PARAGRAPH:1]After the son was installed as king, his mother - after having been invested with the title of Iyoba - was transferred to a palace just outside Benin City, in a place called Uselu. The mother held a considerable amount of power; she was, however, never allowed to meet her son - who was now a divine ruler - again.[PARAGRAPH:1]Divinity of the Oba[PARAGRAPH:1]In Benin, the Oba was seen as divine. The Oba's divinity and sacredness was the focal point of the kingship. The Oba was shrouded in mystery; he only left his palace on ceremonial occasions. It was previously punishable by death to assert that the Oba performed human acts, such as eating, sleeping, dying or washing. The Oba was also credited with having magical powers. He also controlled a powerful bureaucratic apparatus whose decrees were obeyed to the letter.[PARAGRAPH:2]Architecture[PARAGRAPH:1]Impluvium[PARAGRAPH:1]The Impluvium was used in Benin architecture to store rainwater (see the building entry of the Impluvium in the pedia for details).[PARAGRAPH:1]City walls[PARAGRAPH:1]The Benin City walls have been known to Westerners since around 1500. Around 1500, the Portuguese explorer Duarte Pacheco Pereira, briefly described the walls during his travels. In Pereira's Esmeraldo de Situ Orbis, 1505, we read:[PARAGRAPH:1]"The houses are built of sun-dried bricks covered with palm leaves. Benin, which is 80 leagues [sic] long by 40 leagues [sic] broad, is always at war with its neighbours from whom it obtains captives, whom we buy at from 12 to 15 brass or copper manillas".[PARAGRAPH:1]Another description given around 1600, one hundred years after Pereira's description, is by the Dutch explorer Dierick Ruiters. Pereira's account of the walls is as follows:[PARAGRAPH:1]"This city is about a league long from gate to gate; it has no wall but is surrounded by a large moat, very wide and deep, which suffices for its defence". For more details, see the entry in the pedia: "The Ancient Walls of Benin" (Wonder).[PARAGRAPH:2]Military[PARAGRAPH:1]Operations[PARAGRAPH:1]Military operations relied on a well trained disciplined force. At the head of the host stood the Oba of Benin. The monarch of the realm served as supreme military commander. Beneath him were subordinate generalissimos, the Ezomo, the Iyase, and others who supervised a Metropolitan Regiment based in the capital, and a Royal Regiment made up of hand-picked warriors that also served as bodyguards. Benin's queen mother, the Iyoba, also retained her own regiment - the "Queen's Own". The Metropolitan and Royal regiments were relatively stable semi-permanent or permanent formations. The Village Regiments provided the bulk of the fighting force and were mobilized as needed, sending contingents of warriors upon the command of the king and his generals. Formations were broken down into sub-units under designated commanders. Foreign observers often commented favorably on Benin's discipline and organization as "better disciplined than any other Guinea nation", contrasting them with the slacker troops from the Gold Coast.[PARAGRAPH:1]Tactics[PARAGRAPH:1]Benin's tactics were well organized, with preliminary plans weighed by the Oba and his sub-commanders. Logistics were organized to support missions from the usual porter forces, water transport via canoe, and requisitioning from localities the army passed through. Movement of troops via canoes was critically important in the lagoons, creeks and rivers of the Niger Delta, a key area of Benin's domination. Tactics in the field seem to have evolved over time. While the head-on clash was well known, documentation from the 18th century shows greater emphasis on avoiding continuous battle lines, and more effort to encircle an enemy (ifianyako).Fortifications were important in the region and numerous military campaigns fought by Benin's soldiers revolved around sieges. Benin's military earthworks are the largest of such structures in the world, and Benin's rivals also built extensively. Barring a successful assault, most sieges were resolved by a strategy of attrition, slowly cutting off and starving out the enemy fortification until it capitulated. On occasion, however, European mercenaries were called on to aid with these sieges. In 1603-04 for example, European cannon helped batter and destroy the gates of a town near present-day Lagos, allowing 10,000 warriors of Benin to enter and conquer it. As payment, the Europeans received items, such as palm oil and bundles of pepper. The example of Benin shows the power of indigenous military systems, but also the role outside influences and new technologies brought to bear. This is a normal pattern among many nations.[PARAGRAPH:2]European contact[PARAGRAPH:1]Portugal[PARAGRAPH:1]The first European travelers to reach Benin were Portuguese explorers under João Afonso de Aveiro in about 1485. A strong mercantile relationship developed, with the Edo trading slaves and tropical products such as ivory, pepper and palm oil for European goods such as manillas and guns. In the early 16th century, the Oba sent an ambassador to Lisbon, and the king of Portugal sent Christian missionaries to Benin City. Some residents of Benin City could still speak a pidgin Portuguese in the late 19th century.[PARAGRAPH:1]England[PARAGRAPH:1]The first English expedition to Benin was in 1553, and significant trading developed between Europe and Benin based on the export of ivory, palm oil, pepper, and later slaves. Visitors in the 16th and 19th centuries brought back to Europe tales of "Great Benin", a fabulous city of noble buildings, ruled over by a powerful king. A fanciful engraving of the settlement was made by a Dutch illustrator (from descriptions alone) and was shown in Olfert Dapper's Naukeurige Beschrijvinge der Afrikaensche Gewesten, published in Amsterdam in 1668.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Netherlands[PARAGRAPH:1]Another Dutch traveler, David van Nyendael, visited Benin in 1699 and also wrote an account of the kingdom. Nyendael's description was published in 1704 as an appendix to Willem Bosman's Nauwkeurige Beschryving van de Guinese Goud-, tand- en Slave-kust. In his description, Nyendael states the following about the character of the Benin people:[PARAGRAPH:1]"The inhabitants of the Benin are in general a kind and polite people, of whom one with kindness might get everything he desires. Whatever might be offered to them out of politeness, will always be doubled in return. However, they want their politeness to be returned with likewise courtesy as well, without the appearance of any disappointment or rudeness, and rightly so. To be sure, trying to take anything from them with force or violence, would be as if one tries to reach out to the Moon and will never be left unreckoned. When it comes to trade, they are very strict and will not suffer the slightest infringement of their customs, not even a iota can be changed. Though, when one is willing to accept these customs, they are very easy-going and will cooperate in every way possible to reach an agreement".[PARAGRAPH:2]Art and cultural trade[PARAGRAPH:1]Scientific analysis of the brass (or "bronze") used to make the famous Benin plaques and other sculptures found that, beginning in the late 15th century, the metal (previously thought to have come from the Netherlands) began to derive from the Rhineland region of Germany. At that time, the brass was exported from Germany in the form of ring-shaped ingots which were used as currency in the trans-Atlantic slave trade (bought from the Portuguese and incorporated by the people in Benin as a metal source in sculpture), and subsequently melted down in Benin to produce Benin Bronzes.[PARAGRAPH:2]Notable figures (main points, details in the leader specific pages of the leaders from this implemented in this game/mod)[PARAGRAPH:1]Queen Idia[PARAGRAPH:1]Queen Idia was the wife of Oba Ozolua, the Oba who reigned in about 1481 AD. She was a famous warrior who received much of the credit for the victories of her son as his political counsel, together with her mystical powers and medicinal knowledge, were viewed as critical elements of Esigie's success on the battlefield. Queen Idia became more popular when an ivory carving of her face was adopted as the symbol of FESTAC in 1977.[PARAGRAPH:1]Emotan[PARAGRAPH:1]Emotan was a trader who sold her wares at the exact point where her statue now stands. She was historically credited with setting up the first primary school in the kingdom and saving the monarchy during one of its lowest moments. She helped the Oba Ewuare in reclaiming the throne from his usurper brother, Oba Uwaifiokun who reigned about 1432 AD.[PARAGRAPH:1]Queen Iden[PARAGRAPH:1]Queen Iden is yet another heroine whose sacrifice helped shape Benin Kingdom. She was the queen during the reign of Oba Ewuape in about 1700 AD. She is known to have volunteered herself as a sacrificial lamb for the welfare of her husband and that of the entire kingdom after she consulted the oracle and was informed that human sacrifice would be needed to appease the gods and restore peace and unity in the kingdom.[PARAGRAPH:1]General Asoro[PARAGRAPH:1]General Asoro the Warrior was the sword bearer to King Ovonramwen (the Oba of Benin) in 1897. He participated in the defence of Benin during the 1897 expedition, engaging the British expeditionary force sent to capture the Oba. A quote uttered by the general that "no other person [should] dare pass this road except the Oba" (So kpon Oba) was later translated to "SAKPONBA", which a well known road in Benin was named after.[PARAGRAPH:1]Chief Obasogie[PARAGRAPH:1]Chief Obasogie was not just an outstanding Benin warrior of old who defended the kingdom against external invasion but also a talented blacksmith and sculptor.[PARAGRAPH:2]Source:[PARAGRAPH:1]https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Benin</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]The Kingdom of Benin, also known as Great Benin or Benin Kingdom was a kingdom within what is now considered southern Nigeria. It has no historical relation to the modern republic of Benin, which was known as Dahomey from the 17th century until 1975. The Kingdom of Benin's capital was Edo, now known as Benin City in Edo State, Nigeria.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Benin Kingdom was one of the oldest and most developed states in the coastal hinterland of West Africa. It grew out of the previous Edo Kingdom of Igodomigodo around the 11th century AD; it was annexed by the British Empire in 1897.[PARAGRAPH:1]In the 15th and 16th centuries, the kingdom reached the height of its prosperity, expanding its territory, trading with European powers, and creating a remarkable artistic legacy in cast bronze, iron, brass, carved ivory, and other materials.[PARAGRAPH:2]Rituals and laws[PARAGRAPH:1]Human sacrifices[PARAGRAPH:1]Humans were sacrificed in an annual ritual in honour of the god of iron, where warriors from Benin City would perform an acrobatic dance while suspended from the trees. The ritual recalled a mythical war against the sky. Sacrifices of a man, a woman, a goat, a cow and a ram were also made to a god called "the king of death". The god, named Ogiuwu, was worshipped at a special altar in the centre of Benin City. There were two separate annual series of rites that honored past Obas. Sacrifices were performed every fifth day. At the end of each series of rites, the current Oba's deceased father was honored with a public festival. During the festival, twelve criminals, chosen from a prison where the worst criminals were held, were sacrificed. By the end of the eighteenth century, three to four people were sacrificed at the mouth of the Benin River annually, to attract European trade, according to one source.[PARAGRAPH:1]Burials[PARAGRAPH:1]The monarchy of Benin was hereditary; the eldest son was to become the new Oba. In order to validate the succession of the kingship, the eldest son had to bury his father and perform elaborate rituals. If the eldest son failed to complete these tasks, he might be disqualified from becoming king.[PARAGRAPH:1]Separation of son and mother[PARAGRAPH:1]After the son was installed as king, his mother - after having been invested with the title of Iyoba - was transferred to a palace just outside Benin City, in a place called Uselu. The mother held a considerable amount of power; she was, however, never allowed to meet her son - who was now a divine ruler - again.[PARAGRAPH:1]Divinity of the Oba[PARAGRAPH:1]In Benin, the Oba was seen as divine. The Oba's divinity and sacredness was the focal point of the kingship. The Oba was shrouded in mystery; he only left his palace on ceremonial occasions. It was previously punishable by death to assert that the Oba performed human acts, such as eating, sleeping, dying or washing. The Oba was also credited with having magical powers. He also controlled a powerful bureaucratic apparatus whose decrees were obeyed to the letter.[PARAGRAPH:2]Architecture[PARAGRAPH:1]Impluvium[PARAGRAPH:1]The Impluvium was used in Benin architecture to store rainwater (see the building entry of the Impluvium in the pedia for details).[PARAGRAPH:1]City walls[PARAGRAPH:1]The Benin City walls have been known to Westerners since around 1500. Around 1500, the Portuguese explorer Duarte Pacheco Pereira, briefly described the walls during his travels. In Pereira's Esmeraldo de Situ Orbis, 1505, we read:[PARAGRAPH:1]"The houses are built of sun-dried bricks covered with palm leaves. Benin, which is 80 leagues [sic] long by 40 leagues [sic] broad, is always at war with its neighbours from whom it obtains captives, whom we buy at from 12 to 15 brass or copper manillas".[PARAGRAPH:1]Another description given around 1600, one hundred years after Pereira's description, is by the Dutch explorer Dierick Ruiters. Pereira's account of the walls is as follows:[PARAGRAPH:1]"This city is about a league long from gate to gate; it has no wall but is surrounded by a large moat, very wide and deep, which suffices for its defence". For more details, see the entry in the pedia: "The Ancient Walls of Benin" (Wonder).[PARAGRAPH:2]Military[PARAGRAPH:1]Operations[PARAGRAPH:1]Military operations relied on a well trained disciplined force. At the head of the host stood the Oba of Benin. The monarch of the realm served as supreme military commander. Beneath him were subordinate generalissimos, the Ezomo, the Iyase, and others who supervised a Metropolitan Regiment based in the capital, and a Royal Regiment made up of hand-picked warriors that also served as bodyguards. Benin's queen mother, the Iyoba, also retained her own regiment - the "Queen's Own". The Metropolitan and Royal regiments were relatively stable semi-permanent or permanent formations. The Village Regiments provided the bulk of the fighting force and were mobilized as needed, sending contingents of warriors upon the command of the king and his generals. Formations were broken down into sub-units under designated commanders. Foreign observers often commented favorably on Benin's discipline and organization as "better disciplined than any other Guinea nation", contrasting them with the slacker troops from the Gold Coast.[PARAGRAPH:1]Tactics[PARAGRAPH:1]Benin's tactics were well organized, with preliminary plans weighed by the Oba and his sub-commanders. Logistics were organized to support missions from the usual porter forces, water transport via canoe, and requisitioning from localities the army passed through. Movement of troops via canoes was critically important in the lagoons, creeks and rivers of the Niger Delta, a key area of Benin's domination. Tactics in the field seem to have evolved over time. While the head-on clash was well known, documentation from the 18th century shows greater emphasis on avoiding continuous battle lines, and more effort to encircle an enemy (ifianyako).Fortifications were important in the region and numerous military campaigns fought by Benin's soldiers revolved around sieges. Benin's military earthworks are the largest of such structures in the world, and Benin's rivals also built extensively. Barring a successful assault, most sieges were resolved by a strategy of attrition, slowly cutting off and starving out the enemy fortification until it capitulated. On occasion, however, European mercenaries were called on to aid with these sieges. In 1603-04 for example, European cannon helped batter and destroy the gates of a town near present-day Lagos, allowing 10,000 warriors of Benin to enter and conquer it. As payment, the Europeans received items, such as palm oil and bundles of pepper. The example of Benin shows the power of indigenous military systems, but also the role outside influences and new technologies brought to bear. This is a normal pattern among many nations.[PARAGRAPH:2]European contact[PARAGRAPH:1]Portugal[PARAGRAPH:1]The first European travelers to reach Benin were Portuguese explorers under João Afonso de Aveiro in about 1485. A strong mercantile relationship developed, with the Edo trading slaves and tropical products such as ivory, pepper and palm oil for European goods such as manillas and guns. In the early 16th century, the Oba sent an ambassador to Lisbon, and the king of Portugal sent Christian missionaries to Benin City. Some residents of Benin City could still speak a pidgin Portuguese in the late 19th century.[PARAGRAPH:1]England[PARAGRAPH:1]The first English expedition to Benin was in 1553, and significant trading developed between Europe and Benin based on the export of ivory, palm oil, pepper, and later slaves. Visitors in the 16th and 19th centuries brought back to Europe tales of "Great Benin", a fabulous city of noble buildings, ruled over by a powerful king. A fanciful engraving of the settlement was made by a Dutch illustrator (from descriptions alone) and was shown in Olfert Dapper's Naukeurige Beschrijvinge der Afrikaensche Gewesten, published in Amsterdam in 1668.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Netherlands[PARAGRAPH:1]Another Dutch traveler, David van Nyendael, visited Benin in 1699 and also wrote an account of the kingdom. Nyendael's description was published in 1704 as an appendix to Willem Bosman's Nauwkeurige Beschryving van de Guinese Goud-, tand- en Slave-kust. In his description, Nyendael states the following about the character of the Benin people:[PARAGRAPH:1]"The inhabitants of the Benin are in general a kind and polite people, of whom one with kindness might get everything he desires. Whatever might be offered to them out of politeness, will always be doubled in return. However, they want their politeness to be returned with likewise courtesy as well, without the appearance of any disappointment or rudeness, and rightly so. To be sure, trying to take anything from them with force or violence, would be as if one tries to reach out to the Moon and will never be left unreckoned. When it comes to trade, they are very strict and will not suffer the slightest infringement of their customs, not even a iota can be changed. Though, when one is willing to accept these customs, they are very easy-going and will cooperate in every way possible to reach an agreement".[PARAGRAPH:2]Art and cultural trade[PARAGRAPH:1]Scientific analysis of the brass (or "bronze") used to make the famous Benin plaques and other sculptures found that, beginning in the late 15th century, the metal (previously thought to have come from the Netherlands) began to derive from the Rhineland region of Germany. At that time, the brass was exported from Germany in the form of ring-shaped ingots which were used as currency in the trans-Atlantic slave trade (bought from the Portuguese and incorporated by the people in Benin as a metal source in sculpture), and subsequently melted down in Benin to produce Benin Bronzes.[PARAGRAPH:2]Notable figures (main points, details in the leader specific pages of the leaders from this implemented in this game/mod)[PARAGRAPH:1]Queen Idia[PARAGRAPH:1]Queen Idia was the wife of Oba Ozolua, the Oba who reigned in about 1481 AD. She was a famous warrior who received much of the credit for the victories of her son as his political counsel, together with her mystical powers and medicinal knowledge, were viewed as critical elements of Esigie's success on the battlefield. Queen Idia became more popular when an ivory carving of her face was adopted as the symbol of FESTAC in 1977.[PARAGRAPH:1]Emotan[PARAGRAPH:1]Emotan was a trader who sold her wares at the exact point where her statue now stands. She was historically credited with setting up the first primary school in the kingdom and saving the monarchy during one of its lowest moments. She helped the Oba Ewuare in reclaiming the throne from his usurper brother, Oba Uwaifiokun who reigned about 1432 AD.[PARAGRAPH:1]Queen Iden[PARAGRAPH:1]Queen Iden is yet another heroine whose sacrifice helped shape Benin Kingdom. She was the queen during the reign of Oba Ewuape in about 1700 AD. She is known to have volunteered herself as a sacrificial lamb for the welfare of her husband and that of the entire kingdom after she consulted the oracle and was informed that human sacrifice would be needed to appease the gods and restore peace and unity in the kingdom.[PARAGRAPH:1]General Asoro[PARAGRAPH:1]General Asoro the Warrior was the sword bearer to King Ovonramwen (the Oba of Benin) in 1897. He participated in the defence of Benin during the 1897 expedition, engaging the British expeditionary force sent to capture the Oba. A quote uttered by the general that "no other person [should] dare pass this road except the Oba" (So kpon Oba) was later translated to "SAKPONBA", which a well known road in Benin was named after.[PARAGRAPH:1]Chief Obasogie[PARAGRAPH:1]Chief Obasogie was not just an outstanding Benin warrior of old who defended the kingdom against external invasion but also a talented blacksmith and sculptor.[PARAGRAPH:2]Source:[PARAGRAPH:1]https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Benin</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
