<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- custom: imported from m-e mod (see main readme for mod abbreviation details in as of now credits section) (in (adjust to your mod path) C:\Program Files (x86)\Steam\steamapps\common\Sid Meier's Civilization IV Beyond the Sword\Beyond the Sword\Mods\Middle-earth\Assets\Modules\Platypedia\AdditionalText_CIV4GameText.xml) (but i also found them later in c2c mod and they are seemingly the same but the file is sadly/unfortunately way too bloated so going for the m-e mod one(s if talking about the assets themselves if i am not mistaken in thinking/saying so)) and then adjusted or not or yes or etcfor advciv-sas -->
<Civ4GameText>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_IMPROVEMENT_CITY_RUINS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Ruins are the remains of human-made architecture: structures that were once complete, as time went by, have fallen into a state of partial or complete disrepair, due to lack of maintenance or deliberate acts of destruction. Disasters, war and depopulation are the most common root causes, with many structures becoming progressively derelict over time due to long-term weathering and scavenging.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_IMPROVEMENT_GOODY_HUT_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Hut may refer to: Hut (dwelling), a small and crude shelter.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_IMPROVEMENT_FARM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A farm is an area of land, including various structures, devoted primarily to the practice of producing and managing food (produce, grains, or livestock), fibres and, increasingly, fuel. It is the basic production facility in food production. Farms may be owned and operated by a single individual, family, community, corporation or a company. A farm can be a holding of any size from a fraction of a hectare to several thousand hectares.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_IMPROVEMENT_FISHING_BOATS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A fishing vessel is a boat or ship used to catch fish in the sea, or on a lake or river. Many different kinds of vessels are used in commercial, artisanal and recreational fishing.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_WHALING_BOATS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Whaling is the hunting of whales mainly for meat and oil. Its earliest forms date to at least 3000 BC. Various coastal communities have long histories of sustenance whaling and harvesting beached whales. Industrial whaling emerged with organized fleets in the 17th century; competitive national whaling industries in the 18th and 19th centuries; and the introduction of factory ships along with the concept of whale harvesting in the first half of the 20th century.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_IMPROVEMENT_MINE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Mine or mines can refer to: Mining, extraction of mineral resources from the ground.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_IMPROVEMENT_WORKSHOP_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A workshop is a room or building which provides both the area and tools (or machinery) that may be required for the manufacture or repair of manufactured goods. Apart from the larger factories, workshops were the only places of production in the days before industrialisation.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_IMPROVEMENT_LUMBERMILL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A sawmill is a facility where logs are cut into boards.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_IMPROVEMENT_WINDMILL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A windmill is a machine which converts the energy of wind into rotational motion by means of adjustable vanes called sails or blades. The main use was originally for a grinding mill powered by the wind, reducing a solid or coarse substance into pulp or minute grains, by crushing, grinding, or pressing. Windmills have also been used to power sawmills and other industrial processes and as windpumps for obtaining fresh water from underground or for drainage of land.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_IMPROVEMENT_WATERMILL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A watermill is a structure that uses a water wheel or turbine to drive a mechanical process such as flour, lumber or textile production, or metal shaping (rolling, grinding or wire drawing).</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_IMPROVEMENT_PLANTATION_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A plantation is a large artificially established forest, farm or estate, where crops are grown for sale, often in distant markets rather than for local on-site consumption. The term plantation is informal and not precisely defined.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_IMPROVEMENT_QUARRY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A quarry is a type of open-pit mine from which rock or minerals are extracted. Quarries are generally used for extracting building materials, such as dimension stone, construction aggregate, riprap, sand, and gravel. They are often colocated with concrete and asphalt plants due to the requirement for large amounts of aggregate in those materials. The word quarry can include underground quarrying for stone, such as Bath stone.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_IMPROVEMENT_PASTURE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Pasture is land with vegetation cover used for grazing of livestock as part of a farm, or in ranching or other unenclosed pastoral systems or used by wild animals for grazing or browsing. Prior to the advent of factory farming, pasture was the primary source of food for grazing animals such as cattle and horses. It is still used extensively, particularly in arid regions where pasture land is unsuitable for any other agricultural production. In more humid regions, pasture grazing is exploited extensively for free range and organic farming.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_IMPROVEMENT_CAMP_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The term camp comes from the Latin word campus, meaning "field". Therefore, a campsite consists typically of open pieces of ground where a camper can pitch a tent or park a camper. More specifically a campsite is a dedicated area set aside for camping and for which often a user fee is charged. Campsites typically feature a few (but sometimes no) improvements.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_IMPROVEMENT_WELL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]An oil well is a general term for any boring through the earth's surface that is designed to find and acquire petroleum oil hydrocarbons. Usually some natural gas is produced along with the oil. A well that is designed to produce mainly or only gas may be termed a gas well.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_IMPROVEMENT_OFFSHORE_PLATFORM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]An offshore platform, also referred to as an oil platform or oil rig, is a large structure with facilities to drill wells and extract and process oil and natural gas and export the products to shore.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<!-- custom: not used in advciv-sas, implement if needed anyways etc
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_IMPROVEMENT_WINERY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A winery is a building or property that produces wine, or a business involved in the production of wine, such as a wine company. Some wine companies own many wineries. Besides wine making equipment, larger wineries may also feature warehouses, bottling lines, laboratories, and large expanses of tanks known as tank farms. The oldest winery in the world found to date is a 6,000 year old winery in the Areni region of Armenia, which is still a wine making region today.</English>
	</TEXT>
	-->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_IMPROVEMENT_COTTAGE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]In modern usage, a cottage is usually a modest, often cozy dwelling, typically in a rural or semi-rural location. However there are cottage-style dwellings in cities, and in places such as Canada the term exists with no connotations of size at all (cf. vicarage or hermitage). In the United Kingdom the term cottage also tends to denote rural dwellings of traditional build, although it can also be applied to dwellings of modern construction which are designed to resemble traditional ones ("mock cottages").</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_IMPROVEMENT_HAMLET_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A hamlet is usually a rural settlement which is too small to be considered a village, though sometimes the word is used for a different sort of community. The name comes from Anglo-Norman hamelet(t)e; Old French hamelet, the diminutive of Old French hamel. Another diminutive of Old French ham is possibly a cognate with similar words of Germanic origin. Compare with Dutch heem, German Heim, Swiss German cham or -kon, Old English ham and Modern English home, all derived from the Proto-Germanic *kham-. Historically, when a hamlet became large enough to justify building a church, it was then classified as a village. One example of a hamlet is a small cluster of houses surrounding a mill.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_IMPROVEMENT_VILLAGE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A village is a clustered human settlement or community, larger than a hamlet with the population ranging from a few hundred to a few thousands (sometimes tens of thousands), Though often located in rural areas, the term urban village is also applied to certain urban neighbourhoods, such as the West Village in Manhattan, New York City and the Saifi Village in Beirut, Lebanon, as well as Hampstead Village in the London conurbation. Villages are normally permanent, with fixed dwellings; however, transient villages can occur. Further, the dwellings of a village are fairly close to one another, not scattered broadly over the landscape, as a dispersed settlement.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_IMPROVEMENT_TOWN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A town is a human settlement larger than a village but smaller than a city. The size a settlement must be in order to be called a "town" varies considerably in different parts of the world, so that, for example, many American "small towns" seem to British people to be no more than villages, while many British "small towns" would qualify as cities in the United States.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_IMPROVEMENT_FORT_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Fortifications are military constructions and buildings designed for defence in warfare and military bases. Humans have constructed defensive works for many thousands of years, in a variety of increasingly complex designs. The term is derived from the Latin fortis ("strong") and facere ("to make").</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_IMPROVEMENT_FOREST_PRESERVE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A nature reserve (natural reserve, nature preserve, natural preserve) is a protected area of importance for wildlife, flora, fauna or features of geological or other special interest, which is reserved and managed for conservation and to provide special opportunities for study or research. Nature reserves may be designated by government institutions in some countries, or by private landowners, such as charities and research institutions, regardless of nationality. Nature reserves fall into different IUCN categories depending on the level of protection afforded by local laws.</English>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
